<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Corey Runkel</title>
    <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://runkelcorey.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Corey Runkel</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© C.N. Runkel 2021</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://runkelcorey.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Corey Runkel</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>YPFS Citation Style Language</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2021/03/24/ypfs-citation-style-language/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2021/03/24/ypfs-citation-style-language/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When I started at YPFS, we did all COVID all the time.
I&amp;rsquo;d wake up, get paid to doomscroll, and pump out some blogs about what was happening. When we reverted to case-writing, a huge backlog of cases had to be prepped for publication.
Many of these were years-old.
They neither shared common formatting nor common citations, and&amp;mdash;because the cases were so old&amp;mdash;the original authors had moved on to bigger and better things.
We needed to solve all the problems that come with a team distributed not only across space but also time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For literal centuries, publications have solved this problem with style guides and time-consuming editing practices.
However, these are only as strong as their enforcement.
Without savvy, patient editors and authors with hours to spare, editing for standardization rightfully takes a back seat to editing for clarity and content.
A somewhat newer solution involves distributing Word templates that authors simply fill in, Mad-Libs style.
But again, you run into the problem of enforcement.
The first time a line breaks where you don&amp;rsquo;t want it to, or you copy the source style along with the text, the Word template ceases to be &lt;em&gt;authoritative&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, for editors reviewing work years later, if citations aren&amp;rsquo;t perfect or comprehensive, finding the original document can be a bear.
These systems do not &lt;em&gt;link the product to the process&lt;/em&gt;.
They allow authors to keep &amp;ldquo;two sets of books&amp;rdquo;: one, incomplete but well-formatted, that gets published; another, complete but unstructured, located somewhere without a link tracing to it.
In this way, Word documents&amp;mdash;for all the ways they liberate formatting and track changes&amp;mdash;are little different from plain paper.
We have had &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hypertext&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;ways&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hypertext&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;connect&lt;/a&gt; product and process for years, but it is hard to generate buy-in.
Some compromise between accessibility (plain-text editors aren&amp;rsquo;t familiar to most) and utility (e.g. Markdown would be ideal) is usually required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our compromise is the amazing reference manager &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.zotero.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Zotero&lt;/a&gt;.
It builds citations using Citation Style Language (&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.citationstyles.org/en/stable/primer.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;CSL&lt;/a&gt;).
CSL imposes it style in Word documents using fields (kinda like those used often for page numbers or automatically updating dates) that it controls.
In this way it is authoritative.
Zotero feeds it information stored in its desktop app.
What you put in is put out on the page.
In this way it connects product to process: to create a correct and nice-looking bibliography requires citing throughout a document and inputting data correctly to Zotero, which is super easy to search and connects documents to their contexts on the web.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CSL, is also open source, which means that we could configure a style to our liking.
While we mostly like Chicago (author-date) style, I and another Research Associate updated it with some contextual information.
I learnt this XML-like language and have been deploying it with Git.
It&amp;rsquo;s my first experience developing software that people actually &lt;em&gt;use&lt;/em&gt;.
This makes a huge difference!
Working with something that will be used in the future by end-users made me think several steps ahead to maintain forward- and backward-compatibility, and reminded me how much I enjoy solving problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the code &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/runkelcorey/ypfs/blob/master/ypfs-mini.csl&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Morning bike ride at East Rock Park</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2021/03/13/morning-bike-ride-at-east-rock-park/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2021/03/13/morning-bike-ride-at-east-rock-park/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Spring returned to New Haven on Thursday!
A lot evaporated overnight as temperatures rose, and I was fortunate to snap these photos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/loz1Q4DzdI_vihdmX_Z66BNf_m64N4J2p85BXKfUBVn9zHWQuzq1s_hS9RMBIV8pMw_EB4cpdZjwQrtUcVXTBhl8wvOOsxAUJnGmMDoVoDt1SA2NWnFtCyf-wFx37QTu-eWHxz01NDX2KWAgKB2bkBlVqAl9r-QhlVQS2dtMD4CHbFjHO8ZHw5MMJC6Pd1l7yc5qavuYlKH_6EgKll2mCjQImGClZ7NbHlXMLcpqID-f3zOdm5QO2KnYXpQ1miv4pbg5l18cDy7uf4e9lj0e9Rt4icifNiXYkjeESOIzf45Q9A-BQmnL9TMplgTq3TMdfVlKYcNLK5iGYvIwwVwiu_TbAEWhe8QOVxZTjc2Fg6aEXE8hQSbWY19Ovg8p5O1X_Hg6WWmo-ElD2fll4Dmi3T1uvHMp_sE08P97A36nBnqeyjgbppDd0fkl1v220HPtVRObOZ2HOj46w5GGaKzslUJTjFgDcRLRJbge9vKSKy_ipISE9G6iCu5FjNPUZdVdjnMoJcqfvBuwvs3Dv9Mx3357h0ETz-Ii2VGrOwdZXmjLR2lsG2PRDdgAON7-M_V7_Yqcsypp_rK8YyZ0rYm-lCTaWpHZFMiOKYTDTfIcXWQk6M2Dz2JyUyNnGGMc-C_APmYGMr9yaaKQ0IaZYbzmeHP-uGS_DatTWy3wywQ8nC-8BhHe9PzjvM3EK5U6-8z3NFvyLa9tKYcoLD5cw4GoEeu4=w843-h903-no?authuser=0&#34; alt=&#34;The foggy path down from East Rock Park&#39;s &amp;quot;summit&amp;quot;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/IhNeBCC89xH1f9933SfL1fN1P-m0800DemZfpBVmK6_WwCaUp5X0ipeiDuSpOs47M3F8Hc7lAujodM1aoXXi-ZCIcC9DbYrQ8hf-dZD-lg29BJeVLgijCp-h1ZcXXm--uB20oqhj1CEyzok_m-xXU1tjWD8Ot2dmqyXQnHNxsaCxzwAbChSz6rjKtBzJLB_Mn67vbQ51G2VHMW8Wh7XVg5e2dsh6p-gcqH9EOPIyyfbeBO78ip6MRm9lqo9gATZsYPHv0ERhffZcC-Fo8qqrtOQSZJm8zveCTGFmouJwz07zoEOmv0PUgsbrEDGNk3dYiFpfC7Uc4kfY4jJiOsLFheQjy1uYD5MnXiqPP0u22HoSH4MEHH9_bHhiGZSz4L9Rafo7CHA6blTSo2VQfvWfbG5PxsvNsOE63AffUk4LyspNJ5ARneFUSdHtWovUxHvYtClJUNmWe4niQ3iUg9HS7nQ4e-urFQWgKJATqcpAKzZHeFsOMir5zRKDaaaxwsjsBv3fAu7HJ6hxBNRctTx86o8bi0SQLbD2NUJcUMMrN6kcYOoWs1QiEhUn-XdEtxn2mD54_N_pj1PUW1waOec0hoWTK2o49__xrUgSF9vyBtotqmu9sszYimiE59sDLmPnTwX73qrvZAjU95a8RFjGPZRFAANydcmwdbV3qX-Uu91VURvZudh6659h74WkkLYvjMniQQoLvMCyn3iffjODEzs8=w678-h903-no?authuser=0&#34; alt=&#34;A bike&#39;s eye view&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How long do actors have left?</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2020/12/07/how-long-do-actors-have-left/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2020/12/07/how-long-do-actors-have-left/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;My friend Avital wrote a great essay last year about an Instagram influencer.
The publication she released it has, unfortunately, flopped, but I will give the gist.
Lil Miquela&amp;rsquo;s 2.9 million followers pale in comparison to the platform&amp;rsquo;s biggest stars, but she has something they do not: an endless future.
Her computer-generated skin will never age, her fun setting will never be burdened by kids or sickness or hardship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The essay asks why, among the Zoomer clamor for authenticity, so many follow Lil Miquela&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;doings&amp;rdquo;.
Avital makes the obligatory genuflections toward the fact that nobody is doing real things on Instagram before digging into this issue that makes so quaint the normal Social Media is Artifice problem.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:The-point-of-thi&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:The-point-of-thi&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;unnecessary-fork-that-may-interest-those-who-have-not-read-jean-baudrillard&#34;&gt;Unnecessary fork that may interest those who have not read Jean Baudrillard&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She takes Jean Baudrillard as her starting point, skip down two paragraphs to , Baudrillard who &lt;a href=&#34;https://web.stanford.edu/class/history34q/readings/Baudrillard/Baudrillard_Simulacra.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;wrote&lt;/a&gt; in reference to Jorge Luis Borges&amp;rsquo; one-paragraph short story, &amp;ldquo;On Exactitude in Science&amp;rdquo;, translated by Andrew Hurley:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;In that  Empire, the Art of Cartography attained such Perfection that the map of a single Province occupied the entirety of a City, and the map of the Empire, the entirety of a Province.
In time, those Unconscionable Maps no longer satisfied, and the Cartographers Guilds struck a Map of the Empire whose size was that of the Empire, and which coincided point for point with it.
The following Generations, who were not so fond of the Study of Cartography as their Forebears had been, saw that that vast Map was Useless, and not without some Pitilessness was it, that they delivered it up to the Inclemencies of Sun and Winters.
In the Deserts of the West, still today, there are Tattered Ruins of that  Map, inhabited by Animals and Beggars; in all the Land there is no other Relic of the Disciplines of Geography.
—Suarez Miranda,Viajes de varones prudentes, Libro IV,Cap. XLV, Lerida, 1658&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Baudrillard inverts Borges&amp;rsquo; story.
Rather than the residents abandoning the map, they will choose it, since the real world offers so many more imperfections to be disgusted at and dreams unfulfilled.
After so many years, the map will win over the desert-bound kingdom.
We will then be left with the &amp;ldquo;desert of the real&amp;rdquo;, a sort of wasteland of reality.
Instead, everything is thrown to the economically productive artifice, which in this case is Lil Miquela and her cast of computer-generated characters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;back-to-the-main-branch&#34;&gt;Back to the main branch&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming at this from a background in movies, however, I&amp;rsquo;m interested what impact CGI talent will have on the movie industry.
It occurs to me that the actor-studio relations, which have been stable since United Artists was founded in 1919, may break apart again.
Then, studios controlled actors through exclusive deals and were able to pressure talent in their off-screen lives to a greater extent than today.
Avital quotes &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dazeddigital.com/beauty/head/article/41436/1/mixed-race-identity-cgi-influencers-lil-miquela&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;a marketing officer for an influencer management company&lt;/a&gt; to explain this makes so much business sense for studios:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you&amp;rsquo;re using regular influencers you have all the inherent risks of people living their lives; people can get DUI&amp;rsquo;s, get arrested, say non PC things. You&amp;rsquo;ll always have that risk. With CGI influencers you&amp;rsquo;ll have a markedly better chance of that not happening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The richest studios will be able to purchase better CGI, better ranges of motion, etc, and each successful studio will succeed by insulating itself for years (decades?) with its own signature characters, the way Disney has with its animated stars.
The studios will also be able to co-opt new politics quickly, to commodify the moment with ease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course human actors won&amp;rsquo;t be able to coexist.
Taking Baudrillard seriously, we should expect the current desire for authenticity to wear off at some point as viewers accept and expect computers to do the talking as they do the exploding now.
One upshot is that the incredibly beautiful star may fade (though its place will be taken by even less credible pixels) and famous human talent, to the extent it still resides in one person, will be a rangy voice or&amp;mdash;if motion capture remains viable against pure illustration&amp;mdash;an emotive face.
Even though it is not linear, specialization happens whenever new technologies are adopted:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the introduction of cinema made obsolete the need for thousands of local theater actors who could deliver lines&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;when sound was added, actors again had to deliver lines, but only once&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the decline of the musical has meant that the best actors need never dance; and [ultra-]HD &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.today.com/popculture/hd-unforgiving-actors-makeup-artists-wbna24581670&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;emphasized&lt;/a&gt; skin quality [and makeup departments].&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might take a while, but Hollywood will look even more like Broadway in its reduced size and lower pay as improved CGI routinizes talent.
Studios will be the big winners here.
But which studios?
My money&amp;rsquo;s on Disney and Dreamworks (Universal), which used terrible 2019 versions of The Lion King and Cats to test the limits of believability, but no other movie houses possess the CGI chops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are quite a few gaming companies that do, however.
This would be a textbook version of a sector undervalued by establishment media (if not by Wall Street) swallowing a legacy media company whole. Besides, they have practice.
In the gaming landscape, studios have always been dominant. They&amp;rsquo;ve already resolved muddled through the ethics of fake people doing fake actions in front of real audiences.
As more and more media companies jump into VR and Oculus gains traction, there&amp;rsquo;s an opportunity for reconvergence between games and film.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:The-point-of-thi&#34;&gt;The point of this piece is not to challenge Baudrillard. Even though we acknowledge and have learned from his book, that does not mean we can effectively combat it. His ephigraph, from Ecclesiastes, still rings true: &amp;ldquo;The simulacrum [that Lil Miquela is the faker] is never that which conceals the truth [that human Instagrammers are real]&amp;mdash;it is the truth which conceals that there is none [both are fake]. The simulacrum is true.&amp;rdquo; &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:The-point-of-thi&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Small economies face big mobile payments</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2020/11/13/small-economies-face-big-mobile-payments/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2020/11/13/small-economies-face-big-mobile-payments/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bloomberg Businessweek&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/features/2020-11-11/zelle-has-turned-dollar-starved-venezuela-into-a-cashless-test-lab&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;published&lt;/a&gt; an article this week on the rise of mobile payments provider Zelle in Venezuela, where inflation has pushed the price of a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloomberg.com/features/2016-venezuela-cafe-con-leche-index/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;café con leche&lt;/a&gt; to 890,000 bolivars.
Zelle, a money transfer service owned by large US banks, is at first glance an unlikely actor in this story.
Why would Venezuelans embrace a proxy of American financial power?
The article argues that Zelle&amp;rsquo;s dollars offer hygienic access to a stable currency.
Before covid, the Caracas-based consultancy Ecoanalítica &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wsj.com/articles/venezuela-in-historic-shift-moves-to-scale-back-fuel-subsidy-11590961477&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;estimated&lt;/a&gt; that only 15% of citizens have stable access to dollars.
Zelle simply sends dollars around US banks, circumventing the need for physical currency in a dollar-strapped, pandemic-addled country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, as people use a currency less, its legitimacy drops: those who accept bolivars for dollars demand higher and higher rates in return; Zelle (and other mobile payments providers with access to dollars) facilitate dollar spot trading for the masses.
Venezuelans are effectively hastening the bolivar&amp;rsquo;s demise.
Now, it is important to keep in mind that consumer transactions rarely add up to much when compared to large-value settlements by banks and governments, but the effect is there.
&lt;em&gt;Bloomberg&lt;/em&gt; reported that some XX% of Venezuelans maintain a foreign bank account, and a straw poll of Caracas retailers indicates that YY% accept Zelle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mobile payment providers have democratized and sped monetary policy in Venezuela.
One would expect Nicolas Maduro, Venezuela&amp;rsquo;s anti-American president, to curse as the national currency slips away in favor of the dollar.
However, Maduro welcomed this development.
&amp;gt;“I don’t see it as a bad thing … this process that they call ‘dollarization,’” he said during a November 2019 TV broadcast, adding, “thank God it exists!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have here the rare phenomenon that a government accepts the instability of its currency without providing its own alternative.
Transactions bewteen Venezuelan governments and officials still legally proceed in bolivars&amp;mdash;Trump administration sanctions have US accounts connected to thousands of officials&amp;mdash;but an estimated 60% of transactions in the country use greenbacks now.
This modifies the vision of monetary regulation articulated by Karl Polanyi in &lt;em&gt;The Great Transformation&lt;/em&gt;.
Polanyi saw the welfare state, land reform, and the fiats that valued currencies as scenes in the second act of a great &amp;lsquo;double movement&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, a double movement is the powerful destabilization of area thought to be fixed, followed by the frenzied creation of a mechanism to regulate that space.
Specifically, destabilizations in land, labor, and money wrought by the rise of the market economy in Second Industrial Revolution&amp;ndash;era Britain attracted Polanyi.
&lt;em&gt;The Great Transformation&lt;/em&gt; made important contributions to anthropology&amp;mdash;detailing how the market economy produced a mental shift not unlike Weber&amp;rsquo;s process of rationalization&amp;mdash;but let&amp;rsquo;s stay fixed to his account of the birth of monetary regulation.
Essentially, classic liberals agreed into existence the intellectual atmosphere necessary for economic liberalization:
&amp;gt;What made economic liberalism an irresistible force was this congruence of opinion between diametrically opposed outlooks; for what the ultrareformer Bentham and the ultratraditionalist Burke equally approved of automatically took on the character of self-evidence.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:Political-Econom&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:Political-Econom&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, to create a truly laissez-faire system is to create &amp;lsquo;fictitious commodities&amp;rsquo;, to subject things which cannot fluctuate like commodities to the same market discipline.
The chaos of the Second Industrial Revolution ensued, pulling people into the conditions Engels described in Manchester, scuffing up the land with mining tracts, and eroding people&amp;rsquo;s sense of stability by inflation and deflation.
After all the careful treatises, pamphlets, and speeches, people did not want to deal with the self-adjusting market.
Where &amp;ldquo;Laissez-faire was planned, planning was not.&amp;rdquo;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:The-Birth-of-the&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:The-Birth-of-the&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His account lands most viscerally when he discusses the welfare policies made for people, but it extends to money as well:
&amp;gt;central banking and the management of the monetary system were needed to keep manufactures and other productive enterprises safe from the harm involved in the commodity fiction as applied to money. Paradoxically enough, not human beings and natural resources only but also the organization of capitalistic production itself had to be sheltered from the devastating effects of a self-regulating market.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:Man-Nature-and-P&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:Man-Nature-and-P&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
To reduce it a great deal, businesses like stability, but a market-oriented approach to money actually involves a great deal of instability once foreign exchange is added to the equation.
In the Second Industrial Revolution, the source of instability, the commodity that was so fictional, was the gold standard.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:To-illustrate-it&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:To-illustrate-it&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
Some economic historians point to the gold standard&amp;rsquo;s breakdown, and then to economies&amp;rsquo; subsequent deflations and tightenings of credit as the trigger of the Great Depression.
Polanyi did too, and the connection with the greatest modern economic catastrophe served his purposes in &lt;em&gt;The Great Transformation&lt;/em&gt;.
As a result of the Depression, nations adopted &amp;lsquo;token currency&amp;rsquo;, which today we still have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up to this point, Polanyi&amp;rsquo;s relatively ancient history could also describe Venezuela&amp;rsquo;s relatively recent.
In brief, a commodity-backed money (in this case, oil) wreaks terrible damage on ~business~ and the populace by its wild gyrations.
In this case, the terror is inflation instead of deflation, but damage is still inflicted&amp;mdash;who the ~winners~ and ~losers~ are is reversed, if for only a short while.
But Maduro&amp;rsquo;s approval of the dollarization distinguishes now from then.
Polanyi writes of a resurgent nationalism that takes a country&amp;rsquo;s currency as its emblem:
&amp;gt;the new nationalism was the corollary of the new internationalism. [&amp;hellip;]  The national token currency was the certain safeguard of this relative security since it allowed the central bank to act as a buffer between the internal and the external economy.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:Market-and-Produ&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:Market-and-Produ&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast, Maduro relinquishes nationalism for the external economy.
Is this internationalism? American hegemony? It depends if you look at the dollar simply as the reserve currency of the world, or tack on its role in US global power, tending toward hegemony.
Regardless of the particular label, Maduro&amp;rsquo;s declaration was incongruous with his nationalism in other spheres of policy.
I would interpret this to agree with &lt;em&gt;Bloomberg&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rsquo;s take that &amp;ldquo;Venezuelans’ embrace of digital money is less a matter of choice than of necessity&amp;rdquo;, but that would seem to argue that Venezuela&amp;rsquo;s troubles tended inevitably to acquiescence to the dollar.
Instead, I want to emphasize that different governments react in different ways depending on their priority.
Despite Maduro&amp;rsquo;s dictatorial tendencies (and they can&amp;rsquo;t be ironed over), I think his admission grasps the reality of Venezuela&amp;rsquo;s situation and a possible &amp;ldquo;escape valve&amp;rdquo; (his words) for the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ascribe agency, and&amp;mdash;therefore&amp;mdash;intent to Maduro&amp;rsquo;s admission because another country facesa very similar situtation, but has dealt with it much differently.
For me the demonstration of two different approaches to the same problem is enough to poke holes in any account of the situation that claims inevitability.
However, this line of reasoning must be weighed against the fact that inflation is not (currently) as bad in this country.
Zimbabwe has played host to the world&amp;rsquo;s worst inflation for most of the new millennium, but the recent figures total in the hundreds of percent, not tens of thousands.
In July, the president accused the CEO of Econet, Zimbabwe&amp;rsquo;s largest mobile payments operator, with conspiring to undermine the country&amp;rsquo;s dollar peg.
This accusation is made all the more serious with the fact that about 90% of transactions take place through Econet.
It looks as though the process differs slightly from that in Venezuela&amp;mdash;instead of sending dollars through US bank accounts, Zimbabweans have physical dollars (or assets denominated in dollars) and trade Zollars&amp;mdash;but the idea is the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That this is Zimbabwe&amp;rsquo;s second attempt to ditch the (US) dollar in spite of national disfavour shows the national mindset at work here.
These two cases remind us how attractive a national currency can be, but also how tragically impractical.
Mobile payment providers facilitate and hasten old instabilities, leaving little room for fixed-rate currencies to thrive.
It&amp;rsquo;s unclear whether Polanyi&amp;rsquo;s conception of states strong enough to rein in their markets applied when he wrote &lt;em&gt;The Great Transformation&lt;/em&gt;, but it certainly does not now.
And you can bet that central banks are looking to Zimbabwe and Venezuela with anxiety, even though this scale of collapse requires more than just disruptive mobile payments.
I believe this fear is why regulators have thrown bureaucratic wrenches into the last-minute developments of promising startups and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloomberg.com/opinion/articles/2020-06-06/facebook-s-whatsapp-suffers-from-stigma-in-india-digital-payments?sref=Fne8FErw&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Facebook/WhatsApp&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2020-06-23/brazil-s-central-bank-suspends-whatsapp-payments?sref=Fne8FErw&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Libra&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:As-a-side-note-I&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:As-a-side-note-I&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:Political-Econom&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Political Economy and the Discovery of Society&amp;rdquo;. All chapters from &lt;em&gt;The&lt;/em&gt; still-copyrighted &lt;em&gt;Great Transformation&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:Political-Econom&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:The-Birth-of-the&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Birth of the Liberal Creed&amp;rdquo; &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:The-Birth-of-the&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:Man-Nature-and-P&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Man, Nature, and Productive Organization&amp;rdquo; &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:Man-Nature-and-P&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:To-illustrate-it&#34;&gt;To illustrate its fictitiousness, I&amp;rsquo;ll add a fact I read in some children&amp;rsquo;s encyclopedia many years ago: all the gold in the world would only build the first 55 feet or so of the Washington Monument, and no mother lodes have been found since then. It is a remarkably rare material, and one subject now to such investment. &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:To-illustrate-it&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:Market-and-Produ&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Market and Productive Organization&amp;rdquo; &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:Market-and-Produ&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:As-a-side-note-I&#34;&gt;As a side note, I think Ant Group&amp;rsquo;s halted IPO is a very different beast than the India and Brazil injunctions against Libra. China is under no threat from Ant or any of its businesses, for that matter. &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:As-a-side-note-I&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reserve liquidity facilities shift from advanced economies to emerging markets</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2020/07/01/reserve-liquidity-facilities-shift-from-advanced-economies-to-emerging-markets/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2020/07/01/reserve-liquidity-facilities-shift-from-advanced-economies-to-emerging-markets/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This post was originally &lt;a href=&#34;https://som.yale.edu/blog/reserve-liquidity-facilities-shift-from-advanced-economies-to-emerging-markets&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;published&lt;/a&gt; on the YPFS Systemic Risk blog&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On June 19, the European Central Bank (ECB) &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ecb.europa.eu/press/pr/date/2020/html/ecb.pr200619~8badb7725d.en.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;joined&lt;/a&gt; the central banks of England, Japan, and Switzerland in scaling back the frequency of their US dollar liquidity swaps with the Federal Reserve (Fed). &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.federalreserve.gov/regreform/reform-swaplines.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Central bank liquidity swap lines&lt;/a&gt; facilitate access to foreign capital during periods of international financial stress. While these bilateral swap operations with the Fed have slowed, the ECB &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ecb.europa.eu/press/pr/date/2020/html/ecb.pr200625~60373986e5.en.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; on June 25 the establishment of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://som.yale.edu/blog/ecb-announces-new-eurosystem-repo-facility-to-provide-euro-liquidity&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Eurosystem repo facility for central banks&lt;/a&gt; (EUREP). The new facility will complement the ECB’s current bilateral swap lines by allowing for less stable currencies to participate in repurchase agreements. This post summarizes the recent activity on Fed swap lines and documents the shift in currency facilities from those aimed at the sturdiest reserve institutions to those aimed at central banks with smaller stocks of dollars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;fed-swap-lines-remain-successful&#34;&gt;Fed swap lines remain successful&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the Global Financial Crisis (GFC), the Fed has maintained unlimited swap lines with the European Union, England, Japan, Canada, and Switzerland. On &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.federalreserve.gov/newsevents/pressreleases/monetary20200320a.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;March 23&lt;/a&gt;, it began offering daily, 7-day tenor swaps on these unlimited lines. This development came on the heels of a March 19 expansion of bilateral agreements detailed by a &lt;a href=&#34;https://som.yale.edu/blog/central-banks-use-swap-lines-to-maintain-the-flow-of-us-dollar?blog=111690&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;previous YPFS blogpost&lt;/a&gt;: the expanded facility would provide up to $60 billion for the banks of Australia, Brazil, South Korea, Mexico, Singapore, and Sweden, and up to $30 billion for the banks of Denmark, Norway, and New Zealand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During a dollar liquidity swap, the Fed enters into an agreement with another central bank that maintains an account at the Federal Reserve Bank of New York (FRBNY). The banks agree to perform two actions: first, the Fed’s dollars are exchanged for the foreign bank’s currency at the prevailing exchange rate; second, at some specified date in the near future, the foreign bank’s dollars are re-exchanged for their own currency at the same exchange rate as the original transaction, plus a small interest rate. The FRBNY is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.federalreserve.gov/monetarypolicy/files/FOMC_ForeignAuthorization.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;authorized&lt;/a&gt; by the Fed’s Open Market Committee under &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.federalreserve.gov/aboutthefed/section14.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Section 14&lt;/a&gt; of the Federal Reserve Act to establish swap lines, and has &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.federalreserve.gov/newsevents/pressreleases/swap-lines-faqs.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;emphasized&lt;/a&gt; the benefits to American households and businesses by ”helping to maintain the flow of credit to U.S. households and businesses by reducing risks to U.S. financial markets caused by financial stresses abroad.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the agreements peg both transactions to the same exchange rate, the Fed bears no risk that turmoil in foreign exchange markets translates to a loss of US dollars. Foreign central banks often use swap lines to get dollars that they can use to provide liquidity to domestic institutions in need of dollars. In 2007, the Fed lent money directly to US branches of European banks in addition to its heavy usage of the swap lines. The upshot of a liquidity swap was that, since the Fed’s swap was with the other central bank, it was not exposed to the risk of default by the downstream borrowing institutions; this risk was borne by the central bank, which determined who it would lend to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though financial strains among countries with standing dollar swap lines have thus far been much weaker than during the GFC, the rejuvenated lines were equally &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2020-06-19/central-banks-reduce-dollar-operations-as-market-stress-eases?sref=qZkWojPY&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;effective&lt;/a&gt; at quelling turbulent dollar funding markets. &lt;a href=&#34;https://fred.stlouisfed.org/series/DTWEXBGS&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Between March 6 and March 23&lt;/a&gt;, the US trade-weighted dollar index jumped to an historical high of 126.47, and posted its largest single-day percentage increase since the series was inaugurated in January 2006. With the acceleration of 7-day swaps on March 23, three days later the index subsequently posted its second largest drop since March 2009. It has not fluctuated by more than 1 point since April 7, though the index has remained higher and more volatile than recent, pre-pandemic levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;library(tidyverse) #plotting, data wrangling
library(lubridate) #dates

tradewt &amp;lt;- fredr(series_id = &amp;quot;DTWEXBGS&amp;quot;, units = &amp;quot;pch&amp;quot;) #retreive percent change in daily trade-weighted US dollar index using fredr
recessions &amp;lt;- read_csv(&amp;quot;start, end
2007-12-01, 2009-06-01
2020-02-01, NA&amp;quot;) #add recessions from https://fredhelp.stlouisfed.org/fred/data/understanding-the-data/recession-bars/
recessions[nrow(recessions), 2] &amp;lt;- Sys.Date() #update current recession with today&#39;s date

ggplot(tradewt) +
  geom_line(aes(date, value), color = &amp;quot;#286dc0&amp;quot;, show.legend = F) + #line plot of trade-weighted US dollar index
  geom_rect(data = mutate(filter(recessions, end &amp;gt;= min(tradewt$date)), #only include recessions ending after start of series
                          start = if_else(start &amp;lt; min(tradewt$date), min(tradewt$date), start)), #trim start of overhanging recession
            aes(xmin = start, xmax = end, ymin = -Inf, ymax = Inf), #define sides of rectangle
            fill = &amp;quot;#978d85&amp;quot;, #Yale shading color
            alpha = .33) + #opacity
  scale_x_date(expand = c(0,0), date_breaks = &amp;quot;2 years&amp;quot;, date_labels = &amp;quot;%Y&amp;quot;) +
  ggrepel::geom_label_repel(aes(date, value, label = datestring), data = mutate(slice_max(tradewt, order_by = abs(value), n = 6), datestring = format(date, &amp;quot;%b %d&amp;quot;)), min.segment.length = 0, label.padding = .1, segment.alpha = .6, show.legend = F, color = &amp;quot;#4a4a4a&amp;quot;) +
  labs(x = NULL, y = &amp;quot;Percent change&amp;quot;, title = &amp;quot;Daily change in trade-weighted US dollar index, 2006 - 2020&amp;quot;, subtitle = &amp;quot;Shaded areas indicate recessions, and six largest one-day swings are labeled&amp;quot;, caption = &amp;quot;Source: Federal Reserve Board of Governors&amp;quot;) +
  theme(plot.title = element_text(color = &amp;quot;#00356b&amp;quot;, vjust = -2), plot.subtitle = element_text(color = &amp;quot;#00356b&amp;quot;, vjust = -1), plot.caption = element_text(color = &amp;quot;#4a4a4a&amp;quot;), plot.margin = margin(r = 10),
        axis.title = element_text(color = &amp;quot;#222222&amp;quot;), axis.text = element_text(color = &amp;quot;#4a4a4a&amp;quot;), axis.ticks = element_line(color = &amp;quot;#222222&amp;quot;),
        panel.background = element_rect(fill = NA), panel.grid = element_line(color = &amp;quot;#dddddd&amp;quot;))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://runkelcorey.github.io/post/2020-07-01-reserve-liquidity-facilities-shift-from-advanced-economies-to-emerging-markets.en_files/figure-html/plot-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The speed and authority with which the Fed provides liquidity for the largest reserve currency market have &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ft.com/content/df9e34aa-9b5c-11ea-adb1-529f96d8a00b&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;bolstered&lt;/a&gt; the central bank’s reputation. This most recent resurgence of swap lines has led &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2020-03-31/fed-takes-on-role-of-world-s-central-bank-by-pumping-out-dollars?srnd=fixed-income&amp;amp;sref=qZkWojPY&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;some&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wsj.com/articles/the-fed-is-settling-into-its-role-as-the-worlds-central-bank-11585732095&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;assert&lt;/a&gt; that the Fed is not only a central bank to the US, but also to the world, offering short-term emergency liquidity when central banks &amp;ndash; liquid in their own currency &amp;ndash; are strapped for US dollars. As with domestic lender-of-last-resort operations, the transactions have always been initiated by a counterparty, never by the Fed. Although swap agreements are bilateral, the US &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.federalreserve.gov/regreform/reform-swaplines.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;has never drawn&lt;/a&gt; on a currency swap line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;focus-shifts-to-countries-with-weaker-reserves&#34;&gt;Focus shifts to countries with weaker reserves&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Fed’s deceleration of currency swaps prompted &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.economist.com/finance-and-economics/2020/06/20/the-successes-of-the-feds-dollar-swap-lines&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;praise&lt;/a&gt; for the speed and scale of relief. But the facility left unresolved the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ft.com/content/6882defd-bb7a-4732-a5de-a7a69886002d&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;plight&lt;/a&gt; of weaker, systemically less important currencies. Already burdened by higher interest rates on credit, countries without access to Fed swap lines saw a sharp uptick in the costs of accessing dollar funding markets, a Bank for International Settlements &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bis.org/publ/bisbull15.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; published in May found. Access to dollar funding has been exacerbated by capital outflows at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.iif.com/Portals/0/Files/content/2_IIF2020_April_CFR.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;rates higher than during the GFC&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an attempt to provide reserves for dollar-strapped reserve banks, the Fed and ECB have each established repurchasing (repo) facilities for their currencies. The facilities work similarly to currency swap lines, providing short term liquidity and protecting against credit risk by dealing only with central banks. However, these repo facilities lie one step closer to secured loans, requiring foreign central banks to post collateral should they default on loan repurchasing. To protect against exchange rate risk, eligible collateral consists only of sovereign securities denominated in the lender’s currency. For example, the Fed’s Foreign and International Monetary Authorities (FIMA) facility &amp;mdash; detailed in a previous YPFS &lt;a href=&#34;https://som.yale.edu/blog/fed-creates-dollar-repo-facility-for-central-banks-extending-liquidity-to-central-banks-that-don-t-have-fed-swap-lines&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;blogpost&lt;/a&gt; &amp;mdash; accepts US Treasury securities of any maturity, while the ECB’s EUREP accepts euro-denominated debt from any of its constituent states as well as the central bank itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These repo agreements allow foreign central banks to avoid dumping large amounts of sovereign bonds into &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.federalreserve.gov/newsevents/pressreleases/fima-repo-facility-faqs.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;illiquid markets&lt;/a&gt;, ensuring value for both the Fed and the foreign bank in need. But the facilities can be more limited than the swap lines due to shorter maturities and higher interest rates. The FIMA’s repo facility only offers overnight maturities. Though such maturities can be rolled over, the repo agreements contrast sharply in this regard with the swap lines, which offer up to 84-day maturities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, pricing is slightly steeper in FIMA and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ecb.europa.eu/press/pr/date/2020/html/ecb.pr200625_FAQ~8942d3d31d.en.pdf?470e666f74869ebb82847efce694bf7d&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;EUREP facilities&lt;/a&gt;. Where Fed central bank liquidity swaps add &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.davispolk.com/files/the_federal_reserves_actions_address_coronavirus_crisis.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;25 basis points to the overnight index swap (OIS), FIMA adds 25 basis points to the Interest Rate on Excess Reserves (IOER)&lt;/a&gt;. Currently the benchmark US overnight rate, the Federal Funds rate, stands at 0.05%, with the IOER at 0.10%. These prices potentially mean that liquidity will be cheaper for emerging markets than swap lines were for Singapore, which paid 1.09% for a &lt;a href=&#34;https://apps.newyorkfed.org/markets/autorates/fxswap&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;March&lt;/a&gt; swap, but more expensive than recent swaps with the Fed’s standing accounts, which have carried rates around 0.33%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ECB has yet to announce pricing for its facility, which will run until June 2021, but Turkey has been mentioned as a potential applicant. Bloomberg &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2020-06-25/ecb-sets-up-new-liquidity-facility-for-non-euro-central-banks?sref=qZkWojPY&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;reported&lt;/a&gt; that the nation had sought talks with the Group of 20 nations for its inclusion in bilateral swap agreements. For emerging markets, the International Monetary Fund has also been very active in approving emergency fund disbursement and stand-by facilities, and has introduced the new, “swap-like” &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.imf.org/en/About/Factsheets/Sheets/2020/04/17/short-term-liquidity-line&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Short-term Liquidity Line&lt;/a&gt;, and may be on track for support more given its &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cfr.org/blog/what-role-should-imf-play-responding-covid-19&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;still-large reserves&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Debt Mounts for US Retail and Lodging Mortgagors</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2020/06/18/debt-mounts-for-us-retail-and-lodging-mortgagors/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2020/06/18/debt-mounts-for-us-retail-and-lodging-mortgagors/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This post was originally &lt;a href=&#34;https://som.yale.edu/blog/debt-mounts-for-us-retail-and-lodging-mortgagors&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;published&lt;/a&gt; on the YPFS Systemic Risk blog&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Government-mandated shutdowns in response to the novel coronavirus have triggered delinquencies among commercial mortgages as businesses struggle with revenue. The purpose of this article is to characterize the risks to US commercial real estate posed by COVID-19 responses. Due to reporting incentives, data on mortgages packaged into commercial mortgage-backed securities (CMBS) is more accessible and granular than data on the whole commercial mortgage market. Even though CMBS-associated properties constitute just &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.chicagobusiness.com/commercial-real-estate/another-likely-coronavirus-consequence-rising-landlord-defaults&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;20% of outstanding multifamily and commercial debt&lt;/a&gt;, the data generated by such properties can indicate how the whole commercial real estate sector may be affected. On June 4, commercial real estate research firm Trepp reported its largest jump in delinquencies among mortgages involved in the $1.4 trillion CMBS market, with the rate spiking from 2.29% to 7.15%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is real stress on commercial landlords. But that stress sits narrowly within the commercial market. The same Trepp report disaggregated delinquencies, noting nearly 20% of lodging, and more than 10% of retail mortgages were delinquent in May. Less than 4% of multifamily, office, and industrial mortgages were delinquent over the same period. Despite historically high unemployment, government stimulus supports have perhaps helped sustain rental payments. Publicly traded equity real estate investment trusts (REITs) invested in apartments &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.spglobal.com/marketintelligence/en/news-insights/latest-news-headlines/us-reit-rent-tracker-mall-reit-cbl-received-27-of-billed-april-cash-rent-58888411&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;collected&lt;/a&gt; at least 93% of rents in April, with most trusts collecting 95% or more. Meanwhile, offices continue to operate remotely, and warehousing has become more valuable as delivery services take on new importance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;retail-shows-signs-of-life&#34;&gt;Retail shows signs of life&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The speed at which consumers return to retail and lodging will factor importantly into the viability of mortgages in those sectors. The same data on publicly traded equity REITs reports rent collection figures for several owners of regional malls and shopping centers. Overall, between 50% and 65% of April rents were collected in shopping centers, while regional malls collected just 26% to 30% of rental payments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As states re-open, rent payments may increase quite quickly. In Arizona, Florida, Georgia, and Texas, as of June 2, retail foot traffic &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.adweek.com/retail/retail-foot-traffic-returning-states-reopening-shopping-data/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;had already surged&lt;/a&gt; from its April nadir, but only to 38-52% of 2019 levels. Retail nationwide &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.census.gov/retail/marts/www/marts_current.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;grew&lt;/a&gt; 17.7% in May, beginning to make up for sales contractions in March and April of 8.3% and 14.7% respectively. Further, the distribution of volume among types of businesses is unknown. The lockdowns have already caused the bankruptcy of JC Penney and Hertz, with AMC movie theaters currently being &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/06/09/business/coronavirus-amc-movie-theaters-reopening.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;threatened&lt;/a&gt;. But stock data indicates that investors believe retail real estate has already bottomed out. After crashing in late February, prices of several large &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fool.com/investing/2020/06/09/retail-reits-are-on-fire.aspx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;mall operators&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloomberg.com/quote/BBREIT:IND&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;REITs&lt;/a&gt; have stabilized and trended up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;library(tidyverse)
library(lubridate)

read_csv(&amp;quot;../../static/data/reit.csv&amp;quot;) %&amp;gt;%
  group_by(symbol) %&amp;gt;%
  mutate(adjusted = 100*adjusted/adjusted[date == min(date)]) %&amp;gt;%
  ungroup() %&amp;gt;%
  ggplot(aes(date, adjusted)) +
  geom_line(aes(col = symbol), show.legend = F) +
  stat_summary(fun = &amp;quot;mean&amp;quot;, color = &amp;quot;#286dc0&amp;quot;, size = 1, geom = &amp;quot;line&amp;quot;, show.legend = F) +
  scale_color_grey() +
  scale_x_date(expand = c(0,0)) +
  scale_y_continuous(limits = c(0, 110), expand = c(0, 1)) +
  labs(x = NULL, y = &amp;quot;Percent of Feb. 21 closing price&amp;quot;, title = &amp;quot;Price change of NYSE-listed REITs since first confirmed case&amp;quot;, subtitle = &amp;quot;Unweighted daily average in blue&amp;quot;, caption = &amp;quot;Source: Yahoo Finance&amp;quot;) +
  theme(plot.title = element_text(color = &amp;quot;#00356b&amp;quot;, vjust = -1.67), plot.subtitle = element_text(color = &amp;quot;#00356b&amp;quot;, vjust = -1), plot.caption = element_text(color = &amp;quot;#4a4a4a&amp;quot;),
        axis.title = element_text(color = &amp;quot;#222222&amp;quot;), axis.text = element_text(color = &amp;quot;#4a4a4a&amp;quot;), axis.ticks = element_line(color = &amp;quot;#222222&amp;quot;),
        panel.background = element_rect(fill = NA), panel.grid = element_line(color = &amp;quot;#dddddd&amp;quot;),
        legend.position = &amp;quot;bottom&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Warning: Removed 47 rows containing non-finite values (stat_summary).
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Warning: Removed 23 row(s) containing missing values (geom_path).
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://runkelcorey.github.io/post/2020-07-01-debt-mounts-for-us-retail-and-lodging-mortgagors.en_files/figure-html/reit_plot-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The market’s gradual recovery may have been informed by other indicators than the overall delinquency rate. Though 7.15% of securitized commercial mortgages were delinquent in May, 70% of those were only one month late. Trepp noted that a large number of mortgages remained in their 30-day grace period or actually reverted to current on their payments, though historically high delinquencies should still be expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite these expectations of recovery, the woes for commercial real estate may have just begun. Financial Times &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ft.com/content/b8eac068-e7c9-42ea-b9bf-6e2b4666f5c3&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;pointed&lt;/a&gt; to June as a crucial test for businesses, since debt two months late often triggers serious penalties. Moreover, data collected by the Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis since 1991 &lt;a href=&#34;https://fred.stlouisfed.org/series/DRCRELEXFACBS&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;show&lt;/a&gt; commercial delinquencies spiking as recessions end (Fig 2). Moreover, bond prices for CMBS exposed to lodging have tumbled. The same Financial Times article noted that BBB-rated tranches exposed to lodging shed approximately 40% of their value since early March. The asset specificity of hotels only lowers the value of real estate already faced with structural devaluation by services such as Airbnb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;delin &amp;lt;- fredr(series_id = &amp;quot;DRCRELEXFACBS&amp;quot;) #retreive delinquency data using fredr
recessions &amp;lt;- read_csv(&amp;quot;start, end
1990-07-01, 1991-03-01
2001-03-01, 2001-11-01
2007-12-01, 2009-06-01
2020-02-01, NA&amp;quot;) #add recessions from https://fredhelp.stlouisfed.org/fred/data/understanding-the-data/recession-bars/
recessions[nrow(recessions), 2] &amp;lt;- Sys.Date() #update current recession with today&#39;s date

ggplot(delin) +
  geom_line(aes(date, value), color = &amp;quot;#286dc0&amp;quot;, show.legend = F) + #line plot of trade-weighted US dollar index
  geom_rect(data = mutate(filter(recessions, end &amp;gt;= min(delin$date), start &amp;lt;= max(delin$date)), #only include recessions ending after start of series and beginning before end of series
            start = if_else(start &amp;lt; min(delin$date), min(delin$date), start)), #trim start of overhanging recession
            aes(xmin = start, xmax = end, ymin = -Inf, ymax = Inf), #define sides of rectangle
            fill = &amp;quot;#978d85&amp;quot;, #Yale shading color
            alpha = .33) + #opacity
  scale_x_date(expand = c(0,0), date_breaks = &amp;quot;2 years&amp;quot;, date_labels = &amp;quot;%Y&amp;quot;) +
  scale_y_continuous(expand = c(0,0)) +
  labs(x = NULL, y = &amp;quot;Rate&amp;quot;, title = &amp;quot;Commercial delinquency rate, 1991Q1 - 2019Q4&amp;quot;, subtitle = &amp;quot;Shaded areas indicate recessions&amp;quot;, caption = &amp;quot;Source: Federal Reserve Board of Governors&amp;quot;) +
  theme(plot.title = element_text(color = &amp;quot;#00356b&amp;quot;, vjust = -2), plot.subtitle = element_text(color = &amp;quot;#00356b&amp;quot;, vjust = -1), plot.caption = element_text(color = &amp;quot;#4a4a4a&amp;quot;), plot.margin = margin(r = 10),
        axis.title = element_text(color = &amp;quot;#222222&amp;quot;), axis.text = element_text(color = &amp;quot;#4a4a4a&amp;quot;), axis.ticks = element_line(color = &amp;quot;#222222&amp;quot;),
        panel.background = element_rect(fill = NA), panel.grid = element_line(color = &amp;quot;#dddddd&amp;quot;))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://runkelcorey.github.io/post/2020-07-01-debt-mounts-for-us-retail-and-lodging-mortgagors.en_files/figure-html/delinquencies-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;support-for-commercial-real-estate-must-proceed-carefully&#34;&gt;Support for commercial real estate must proceed carefully&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Landlords and owners are navigating treacherous waters should commercial tenants require serious rent assistance. While CMBS loans tend to be non-recourse, it is &lt;a href=&#34;https://spcllp.com/nader-pakfar-risks-non-recourse-carveouts-cmbs-loans/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;standard practice&lt;/a&gt; for loans to feature “bad boy” covenants designed to guard against principal-agent risk. Such covenants provide recourse in the event that borrowers commit actions that (in normal times) are irresponsible. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.arentfox.com/perspectives/alerts/main-street-lending-programs-are-they-compatible-traditional-real-estate&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Real estate&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.maddinhauser.com/Law/DrawCases.aspx?CaseID=3881&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;attorneys&lt;/a&gt; point to two such actions in particular: significant rent renegotiation, and taking on senior indebtedness without investor consent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;US programs have thus far steered clear of these debt covenants, and offer viable channels should further support be authorized. The Payroll Protection Program (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sba.gov/funding-programs/loans/coronavirus-relief-options/paycheck-protection-program&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;PPP&lt;/a&gt;), offering forgivable and unsecured loans to businesses, recently expanded the amount that could be used for non-payroll expenses to 40%, opening the door to rent support. Borrowing terms for the three programs under the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.federalreserve.gov/monetarypolicy/mainstreetlending.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Main Street Lending Program&lt;/a&gt; have also &lt;a href=&#34;https://som.yale.edu/blog/federal-reserve-amends-main-street-lending-program&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;eased&lt;/a&gt;. The Priority and Extended lending facilities (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.federalreserve.gov/newsevents/pressreleases/files/monetary20200608a2.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;MSPLF&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.federalreserve.gov/newsevents/pressreleases/files/monetary20200608a3.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;MSELF&lt;/a&gt;, respectively) require loans to be secured, and prohibit subordination, but carve out exceptions for outstanding mortgage debts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that these programs appear to avoid the dangers posed by “bad boy” covenants, it seems likely that strained borrowers are equipped with the resources to secure credit lifelines to at least prolong defaults for several more months. On the other hand, it seems unlikely that the Federal Reserve (Fed) would engage private CMBS markets in a more direct fashion. Thus far only two Fed actions support private CMBS. In March it &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.federalreserve.gov/newsevents/pressreleases/monetary20200323a.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;included agency CMBS in its plan to make Open Market Desk purchases&lt;/a&gt; of $200 billion of MBS, and in April it expanded the eligible collateral for the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.federalreserve.gov/monetarypolicy/talf.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Term-Asset Securities Lending Facility&lt;/a&gt; to include AAA tranches of CMBS. A previous YPFS article &lt;a href=&#34;https://som.yale.edu/blog/fed-actions-help-agency-mreits-step-off-the-liquidity-roller-coaster&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;found&lt;/a&gt; that the Fed’s purchasing announcement had a positive effect on agency mortgage REITs (mREITs) while having only minimal effects on non-agency residential mortgage REITs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Equity REITs face different issues, principally those of eligibility and restrictions on usage. While property management companies are eligible for both PPP and MSLF loans, it is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jdsupra.com/legalnews/federal-reserve-further-expands-main-87251/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;unclear&lt;/a&gt; as to whether equity REITs are eligible. They may violate the Small Business Administration’s rules making ineligible for loans “&lt;a href=&#34;https://gov.ecfr.io/cgi-bin/text-idx?SID=fa53a93b56da0512f225f4fbcf044d0c&amp;amp;mc=true&amp;amp;node=se13.1.120_1110&amp;amp;rgn=div8&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;developers and landlords that” generally “do not actively use or occupy the assets acquired or improved with the loan proceeds.&lt;/a&gt;” However, equity REITs have applied for, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mycentraloregon.com/2020/04/29/luxury-hotels-real-estate-investment-trusts-benefited-from-ppp-loans/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;received&lt;/a&gt; PPP loans, potentially pushing this issue to the oversight bodies &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.brookings.edu/blog/fixgov/2020/04/15/congressional-oversight-of-the-cares-act-could-prove-troublesome/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;authorized&lt;/a&gt; by the CARES Act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the CARES Act prohibits the payment of dividends by corporations receiving support. While several programs have received blanket waivers from the Treasury Department, the Main Street Lending Facility &lt;a href=&#34;https://som.yale.edu/blog/federal-reserve-amends-main-street-lending-program&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;has not&lt;/a&gt;. The legal structure of REITs requires the payment of dividends, and many REITs have &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.barrons.com/articles/reit-investors-can-expect-dividends-to-be-paid-mostly-in-stock-51586091600&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;opted&lt;/a&gt; to pay mostly in stock. REIT trade associations have &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rer.org/docs/default-source/comment-letters/2020/4-22-20-main-street-lending-program-comment-letter.pdf?sfvrsn=671a0542_2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;already written&lt;/a&gt; to the Treasury Department requesting a waiver for this particular case, while the Internal Revenue Service has &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.bloombergtax.com/daily-tax-report/irs-loosens-requirements-on-reit-cash-to-promote-liquidity&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;reprised&lt;/a&gt; rules adopted during the Global Financial Crisis, allowing REITs to hold (and therefore distribute) less cash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The New York Times &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/06/05/business/economy/coronavirus-commercial-real-estate.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;highlighted&lt;/a&gt; name-brand tenants&amp;ndash;Gap, LVMH, Starbucks&amp;ndash;that had stopped paying rent and started renegotiating leases. The article noted that “the strongest tenants — those most able to pay — are driving the hardest for a discount.” When renters know that the options for landlords are either lease renegotiation or a total loss of income, those with the ability to pay may augment the demands of those that cannot pay, further pressuring landlords.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Deloitte &lt;a href=&#34;https://www2.deloitte.com/us/en/insights/economy/covid-19/covid-19-implications-for-commercial-real-estate-cre.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; noted that real estate development had flagged, with more than half of US construction firms surveyed halting projects. Social distancing rules precipitated decreased demand and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mercurynews.com/2020/04/04/coronavirus-delivers-first-blow-against-construction-economy-could-knock-it-out/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;disrupted&lt;/a&gt; construction sites. Commercial real estate’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reit.com/data-research/research/nareit-research/what-can-past-real-estate-construction-cycles-tell-us-about&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;sensitivity&lt;/a&gt; to economic downturns compounded the effects of decreased demand. The Deloitte report suggested that developers adapt rental properties to meet the needs of a changed society and strengthen resilience to future pandemics. The shock to brick-and-mortar businesses is likely to accelerate permanent transitions to online retail, work, and customer service across sectors. While several large &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theverge.com/facebook/2020/5/21/21265699/facebook-remote-work-shift-workforce-permanent-covid-19-mark-zuckerberg-interview&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;companies&lt;/a&gt; have started these transitions, they will &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2020-05-15/even-the-pandemic-can-t-kill-the-open-plan-office?sref=qZkWojPY&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;likely&lt;/a&gt; take several years to complete. Such a timeframe would flatten and spread the risks to commercial real estate finance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast, the greatest short-term risks posed by US commercial mortgages sit narrowly in lodging and retail, though high-turnover coworking spaces have already seen slashed revenues. CMBS-associated mortgages account for one fifth of outstanding commercial debt. While data are more widely and finely available for properties underlying CMBS loans, concerns similar to those discussed above exist with respect to non-securitized commercial mortgages. Where investors are exposed to lodging, prices have slumped, and questions abound regarding the sector&amp;rsquo;s long-term viability as nearly 20% of the CMBS-associated mortgages were reported delinquent in May. Retail activity is growing, but there is concern as to whether the recovery will be fast enough to stave off default in a sector with more than 10% of securitized mortgages in delinquency, which could hamper the real economy’s general pace of recovery.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Federal Reserve further expands access to Municipal Liquidity Facility</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2020/06/09/federal-reserve-further-expands-access-to-municipal-liquidity-facility/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2020/06/09/federal-reserve-further-expands-access-to-municipal-liquidity-facility/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This post was originally &lt;a href=&#34;https://som.yale.edu/blog/federal-reserve-further-expands-access-to-municipal-liquidity-facility&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;published&lt;/a&gt; on the YPFS Systemic Risk blog&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On June 3, the Federal Reserve Board of Governors &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.federalreserve.gov/aboutthefed/boardvotes.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;unanimously approved&lt;/a&gt; a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.federalreserve.gov/newsevents/pressreleases/monetary20200603a.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;second expansion&lt;/a&gt; of eligibility under its Municipal Liquidity Facility (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.federalreserve.gov/monetarypolicy/muni.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;MLF&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Authorized by the CARES Act, the MLF can purchase up to $500 billion of newly-issued bonds from qualifying municipalities, using funds from the Fed and Treasury. Until this latest action, the MLF had restricted the eligibility of cities and counties based only on their population. The newest terms guarantee the eligibility of at least two political subdivisions and two revenue-bond issuers from each state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The expansion comes after the Fed &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2020-06-03/fed-expands-municipal-loan-program-to-include-smaller-borrowers&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;once again weathered criticism&lt;/a&gt; from state governors and representatives that the MLF’s eligibility criteria were too narrow. The original MLF criteria designated states, the District of Columbia, cities larger than one million residents, counties larger than two million residents, and one revenue-bond issuer (such as a utility or transit authority) per state as the only eligible recipients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In effect, the original term sheet ceded borrowing privileges to just &lt;a href=&#34;https://som.yale.edu/blog/federal-reserve-announces-new-municipal-liquidity-facility?blog=111690&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;10 cities and 16 counties&lt;/a&gt;. The Federal Reserve at the time said states could funnel the proceeds from bond sales to smaller cities and counties whose budgets had been strained by the effects of the novel coronavirus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this approach, while preserving the Fed’s historical distance from small borrowers, ran into several issues. For instance, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.politico.com/news/2020/04/23/fed-municipal-rescue-205831&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;some states lack the organizational infrastructure to lend to cities and counties&lt;/a&gt;. More importantly, several states face legal impediments to borrowing. Twenty-one &lt;a href=&#34;http://pewtrusts.org/~/media/assets/2017/06/sfh_strategies_for_managing_state_debt_final.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;states require referenda&lt;/a&gt; to issue debt at levels demanded by COVID-19 disruptions, while a &lt;a href=&#34;https://som.yale.edu/blog/barriers-to-access-impede-utilization-of-municipal-liquidity-facility&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;previous YPFS blogpost&lt;/a&gt; noted that several more states require legislative supermajorities to push through bond issuances. The current situation presents unique challenges to meeting such requirements, given that social distancing demands have closed many governing bodies and forestalled the possibilities of voting. In many cases, safe alternatives have not yet been designed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Members of Congress &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.shaheen.senate.gov/news/press/shaheen-urges-fed-to-fix-rules-that-block-city-county-governments-from-receiving-direct-covid-19-relief&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;criticized&lt;/a&gt; the Fed’s narrow interpretation of the CARES Act, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.congress.gov/bill/116th-congress/house-bill/748/text#HA1CEBDD35FD448DB9F77B49E23EADB58&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;which did not specify eligibility criteria&lt;/a&gt; for the MLF. The Fed’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://som.yale.edu/blog/federal-reserve-expands-eligibility-for-municipal-liquidity-facility&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;first expansion&lt;/a&gt; on April 27 extended the program from September 30 to December 31, and lowered the eligibility thresholds from 1 million residents per city and 2 million residents per county to 500,000 and 1 million,  respectively. As a result, the total number of eligible cities and counties increased from 26 to 227. However, even under the amended criteria, several states still lacked a single municipality that met the population threshold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The June 3 terms lowered the thresholds again to 250,000 residents per city and 500,000 residents per county. Should a state lack one or two municipalities that meet these thresholds, governors may designate one or two of the largest ineligible cities or counties. Governors may also designate two non-governing entities that currently issue bonds secured by government revenue. Additionally, multi-state revenue-bond issuers, such as the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey and the Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority, are now also eligible issuers, provided that minimum credit rating thresholds are met.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Fed has not changed the original terms regarding the MLF’s size, and eligible uses of funds. The facility is authorized to purchase up to $500 billion in eligible bonds (allocated among the states as &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.newyorkfed.org/medialibrary/media/markets/municipal-liquidity-facility-eligible-issuers&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;proportions of FY2017 general revenue&lt;/a&gt;), and is backstopped by an equity investment of $35 billion from the Treasury’s Exchange Stabilization Fund, as authorized by the CARES Act. The facility takes the form of a special purpose vehicle (SPV) established by the Fed under Section 13(3) of the Federal Reserve Act. The facility may purchase “&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.federalreserve.gov/newsevents/pressreleases/files/monetary20200603a1.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;tax anticipation notes (TANs), tax and revenue anticipation notes (TRANs), bond anticipation notes (BANs), revenue anticipation notes (RANs),&lt;/a&gt;” and similar bonds with maturities no longer than 36 months, funding up to 20% of a state, county, city, or revenue-bond issuer’s revenue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Small cities are particularly sensitive to economic shocks due to their dependence on sales tax. Brookings &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.brookings.edu/blog/the-avenue/2020/03/31/when-will-your-city-feel-https://www.brookings.edu/blog/the-avenue/2020/03/31/when-will-your-city-feel-the-fiscal-impact-of-covid-19/the-fiscal-impact-of-covid-19/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;reported&lt;/a&gt; that cities in the Midwest, generally smaller than those in the dense East and heavily urbanized West, rely more on sales taxes. Whereas property values are assessed not more than once a year, and income taxes are filed annually, sales tax receipts enter municipal finances at frequencies varying between once a month and once a year. These higher-frequency collections mean that shocks affect sales tax revenues much more quickly than other types of taxes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compounding pressure on the MLF to purchase small-city debt are high-population thresholds and use restrictions on CARES Act grants. Under the Coronavirus Relief Fund, only municipalities with 500,000 residents or more are &lt;a href=&#34;https://home.treasury.gov/system/files/136/Census-Data-and-Methodology-Final.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;eligible&lt;/a&gt; and funds may only be used for &lt;a href=&#34;https://home.treasury.gov/system/files/136/Coronavirus-Relief-Fund-Guidance-for-State-Territorial-Local-and-Tribal-Governments.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;necessary and unexpected expenditures&lt;/a&gt; demanded by COVID-19. Thus, monies cannot be used to compensate for reduced sales tax receipts, a use that is permissable for proceeds from MLF bond purchases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MLF marks &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.politico.com/news/2020/04/09/fed-to-buy-municipal-debt-178222&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;the first time&lt;/a&gt; the Federal Reserve has waded into direct purchases of municipal bonds. In 2011, in the wake of the Global Financial Crisis, Republicans in both chambers &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wsj.com/articles/SB10001424052748704739504576067602380461160&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;balked&lt;/a&gt; at suggestions from Democrats that the federal government bail out municipalities. The then-Chair of the Federal Reserve, Ben Bernanke, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.govinfo.gov/content/pkg/CHRG-112shrg68184/html/CHRG-112shrg68184.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;said&lt;/a&gt; that the Fed had “no expectation or intention to get involved in state and local finance.” The Fed’s legal authority to buy municipal bonds extended to only 2% of the market, and Bernanke noted that there might be other legal restrictions under the Dodd-Frank Act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, in spite of the Fed’s historic distance from municipal debt, the efficacy of the MLF may lead to deeper involvement in municipal finances. The initial announcement of the MLF in April immediately stabilized a $4 trillion market that saw AAA yields &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ft.com/content/e2d20041-0d86-4dea-8016-d1cfcc01f4c0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;jump from just under 1% to just under 3% in a matter of days&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Politico &lt;a href=&#34;https://nam05.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fsubscriber.politicopro.com%2Fdatapoint%2F2020%2F05%2Fpro-analysis-what-you-need-to-know-about-the-municipal-bond-market-101286&amp;amp;data=02%7C01%7Ccorey.runkel%40yale.edu%7Cfcd2daef45404ac856f708d80bade8a3%7Cdd8cbebb21394df8b4114e3e87abeb5c%7C0%7C0%7C637272188841278572&amp;amp;sdata=QLHhjyolYQ3O%2F9SU2ZQfZXgHOnyneICd%2Bjfgje5R7uI%3D&amp;amp;reserved=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;pointed&lt;/a&gt; to House Ways &amp;amp; Means Chair Richard Neal as a catalyst for more intervention in munis. Even before the novel coronavirus, the former mayor of Springfield, Massachusetts, had established himself as a supporter of municipal bonds. However, aid may instead come from traditional fiscal policy routes should the Fed hold firm on its new eligibility thresholds. Neal represents Springfield and its enclosing county Hampden, each of which just miss these newest MLF population thresholds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus far, Illinois is the only state to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ft.com/content/5393bdc7-02a2-4ec7-81c3-4d6088216a6c&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;announce&lt;/a&gt; its participation in the MLF, issuing $1.2 billion in 12-month maturities at 3.82%.The MLF became operational on May 26.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>US Housing</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/project/housing/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/project/housing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project is majorly on hold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love the idea that all these super materialist forces influence how we act and think, and the home is just about the most materialist symbol.
In this country, homes take on new financial dimensions as bastions of wealth, new aspirational dimensions as the base of American Dreams, and&amp;mdash;with covid&amp;mdash;make up the lifeworlds of a good chunk of people.
Housing politics occupied the last year of my time UVA, between the Urban Planning and Politics departments, with &lt;a href=&#34;../../publication/thesis/actors-motive.html&#34;&gt;my undergrad thesis&lt;/a&gt; capping the year.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>YPFS citation engine</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/project/ypfs-csl/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/project/ypfs-csl/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This bit of code takes in Zotero entries and outputs formatted citations.
I wrote about it &lt;a href=&#34;../../2021/03/24/ypfs-citation-style-language/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>YPFS ggplot theme</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/project/ypfs-theme/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/project/ypfs-theme/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project is a bit on hold as I strike the right balance between accessibility and flexibility.
It makes use of &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/yixuan/showtext&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;showtext&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which allows for the installation of custom fonts, but doesn&amp;rsquo;t handle extremely high and low quality as well as &lt;a href=&#34;https://ggplot2.tidyverse.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;ggplot2&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we at YPFS spent our whole days blogging about the pandemic&amp;rsquo;s toll on economies worldwide, we put out a lot of graphs, and they all looked different.
This isn&amp;rsquo;t the biggest deal, but consistent style goes a long way to weave different research threads together.
And with a &lt;a href=&#34;https://yaleidentity.yale.edu/web&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;typekit&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://toolness.github.io/accessible-color-matrix/?n=white&amp;amp;n=light&amp;amp;n=emphasis&amp;amp;n=Yale%20blue&amp;amp;n=black&amp;amp;v=F9F9F9&amp;amp;v=63AAFF&amp;amp;v=286DC0&amp;amp;v=00356B&amp;amp;v=222222&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;palette&lt;/a&gt; as beautiful as Yale&amp;rsquo;s, using Excel and Calibri is something of a shame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This repository is an evolving project to standardize the production of figures within R, an open-source statistical package. Researchers who publish with[in] the Yale School of Management will recognize its distinct use of Helvetica Neue, while affiliated with the University at large will recognize that typekit and palette of blues. However, conforming to the school&amp;rsquo;s style can be a time-consuming process, likely to be ignored in favor of other work. A standard theme can plug the gap caused by tedious formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>YPFS web scraper</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/project/ypfs-translator/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/project/ypfs-translator/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;RAs would told me how much time it takes to enter metadata into both Zotero and &lt;a href=&#34;ypfs.som.yale.edu&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;our own archive&lt;/a&gt;.
Because our Zotero library captures more information than our archive, the ideal solution was to export Zotero information to our Drupal content management system.
However, YPFS gets no love from Yale&amp;rsquo;s business-school IT department.
We ultimately find a lot of workarounds to aid our work, and it was no different here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way to cut down on time spent entering metadata was the reverse: instead of exporting to our archive, we could export &lt;em&gt;from&lt;/em&gt; our archive.
This is where Zotero comes in.
It accepts a number of different formats for bibliographic information stored on websites.
Unfortunately, our website exposes metadata in none of these &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.zotero.org/support/dev/exposing_metadata&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;standard&lt;/a&gt; formats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, we needed to slightly modify our idea of how to transfer data between Zotero and our archive.
In this case, we &lt;em&gt;imported&lt;/em&gt; from our archive.
Zotero &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zotero/translators/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;allows&lt;/a&gt; people to volunteer translators that let Zotero read metadata on specific sites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned the basics of JavaScript to write &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zotero/translators/pull/2358&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; bit of code.
This totally felt like learning a new language.
My previous experience with programming had really been limited to data science.
I was accustomed to static products like a plot or table.
Here, I contended with interactivity&amp;mdash;in which a command is triggered by an end-user action&amp;mdash;and inputs not yet defined (a/k/a new webpages created in the future).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result is a plug-in that, once accepted by Zotero&amp;rsquo;s administrators, will allow all users of Zotero to import directly from our archive.
Significantly, it is the only website-specific translator I&amp;rsquo;ve seen that accepts more than just webpage snapshots or PDFs.
This translator will accept audio, video, Word documents, images, you name it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Political Impacts of Residential Mortgages in Crisis</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/publication/thesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/publication/thesis/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>David Lynch is Toying With Us</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2020/02/15/david-lynch-is-toying-with-us/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2020/02/15/david-lynch-is-toying-with-us/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I write this post while watching &lt;em&gt;Rabbits&lt;/em&gt;, a work of exceptional mystery but unexceptional tension.
Lynch casts two regulars&amp;mdash;Laura Harring and Naomi Watts&amp;mdash;opposite one newbie&amp;mdash;Scott Coffey&amp;mdash;as man-sized rabbits in what appears to be the &lt;em&gt;Blue Velvet&lt;/em&gt; apartment set.
These short films, available &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLSSx9jvH6luUPl-bqfqaJ8z8vHDqlu5ji&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;on YouTube&lt;/a&gt;, trip over several of Lynch&amp;rsquo;s signature aspects: characters sing haunting songs; mundane life is treated as a social experiment; and Angelo Baldametti&amp;rsquo;s synthesizers underscore everything.
&lt;em&gt;Rabbits&lt;/em&gt; insists that we examine our own tastes and be comfortable with those answers (and inevitably unanswered questions).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though it offers no plot or characters that could create tension in a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=j56WPBaiPYQ&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;conventional story structure&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Rabbits&lt;/em&gt; is seriously intriguing, and hints at larger, unobserved meanings.
This intrigue is not uncommon; in fact, my theory of late has been that Lynch understands that his viewers feel the hints and the suggestions at something grander, his films all metaphysical McGuffins.
In his films, characters do not look at one another&amp;mdash;they see, in flashy close-ups, the uncertain eyes of the other.
Leading women are never conventionally pretty&amp;mdash;they are fantastically upbeat and implausibly platinum, hysterical results of Hollywood insecure appeal to men&amp;rsquo;s wallets.
Cars do not traverse from point to point&amp;mdash;headlights sprint over dark, twisting roadways.
These are cinematic clichés, style that heightens substance when it is used eagerly and genuinely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2013/04/18/lynchrabbits1024_wide-81b3911888e86e687da1a0370b19cc026967ef0d.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Set of *Rabbits*. The camera moves from this fixed position exactly once to zoom in on the telephone.&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is nothing substantive about &lt;em&gt;Rabbits&lt;/em&gt;: Lynch&amp;rsquo;s mastery over cinematic cliché is taken to the brink, and over.
In many Lynch films since &lt;em&gt;Blue Velvet&lt;/em&gt;, characters utter non-sequiters in total deadpan; but in &lt;em&gt;Rabbits&lt;/em&gt;, they utter nothing but non-sequiters, with no story to speak of!
This Baldametti score then adds style to substanceless grunts, sounds English speakers will recognize as words but not as meaningful sentences.
And with some serious hilarity, Lynch adds a sitcom applause over the entrances of each character into this one-room apartment and laughtracks after sentences like &amp;ldquo;It is 7pm&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;I almost forgot.&amp;rdquo;
These outbursts, audio cues to at-home viewers that Important or Funny happenings are taking place, mock TV shows like the &lt;em&gt;Big Bang Theory&lt;/em&gt;, whose live audiences treat academic jargon and references to comic books as the basis for side-splitting guffaws.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The distance between the intelligibility of plot in &lt;em&gt;Rabbits&lt;/em&gt; and the connotations of its audio cues emphasize the contingency of language and the ability of convention to invent meaning from nothing.
It is indisputable that Baldametti&amp;rsquo;s score is ominous, alerting viewers that Something Is Happening, or that audience laughter is comedic, alerting viewers that a Joke Is Occurring.
But simply because a connotation is indisputable does not make it true.
None would dispute the scores ominousness or the audiences laughter because the years of TV and film that we have watch have taught us to connect certain sounds to certain moments.
The work starts with children&amp;rsquo;s tales, where morality is stark and the audio cues used to reinforce a grand, unified message.
By grounding these otherwise unintelligible cues in extra-cinematic morality or realistic emotions, we learn to couple low, industrial sounds with alertness, and human laughter with comedy.
&lt;em&gt;Rabbits&lt;/em&gt; attempts to elicit those emotions by only employing the signifier, while ditching the plot points signified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.ytimg.com/vi/NiOx5yJx-jc/maxresdefault.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The *Persona*-like dream sequences. Nothing says for sure these rabbits sleep, but shifts in color and a demonic face that hovers in the upper left-hand corner match dream sequences in Lynch&#39;s other films.&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps one can argue that the words which immediately precede and follow the &lt;em&gt;Persona&lt;/em&gt;-like interpolated dream sequences are Important, but I am not convinced.
I propose that &lt;em&gt;Rabbits&lt;/em&gt; is David Lynch toying with us.
He wants to know if he can make pure entertainment, works without useful or familiar stories, but which nonetheless strap us into rollercoasters of joy, despair, nostalgia, and humor.
In his other works, this plays out seamlessly.
I (the viewer) achingly try to pin down the plot, and then the meaning of the narrative he created.
This process feels possible, but always out-of-reach in his other works, which ditch the rabbit heads and opt for sequences of dialog that I recognize as events and narrative momentum.
But in &lt;em&gt;Rabbits&lt;/em&gt;, the dissonance between signifier and signified makes the effect clear.
In &lt;em&gt;Rabbits&lt;/em&gt;, the laughter and music become parodic, pointing at the fact that in &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; language, cinematic or otherwise, our grunts are intelligible for no reasons other than Pavolvian repitition and the magic fizz of neurons.
Language is contingent, subject to chance mutation and adoption, and not subject to deep structures or extra-personal validity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Putting Theory in its Place</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2020/01/20/putting-theory-in-its-place/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2020/01/20/putting-theory-in-its-place/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When statistics disagree with words, theory can be an effective arbitrator. These disciplinary stories impose an otherwordly coherence on an incoherent world. With so much information at hand, I became addicted to theory for this very quality. The few bad habits I struggle to kick have (thankfully) instilled a probably irrational fear of new bad habits. Unfortunately, in kicking these habits and warding off others, I turned to theory to make my decisions. In doing so, I appealed to ever more abstract and cloudy narratives to buttress those closer to the ground (for theory can only be invalidated by other theories). And so, my first two years of undergrad were marked by a myopic embrace that left me pretentious and ill-suited to conditions on the ground floor of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Letting go of theory as the source of knowledge has been such a difficult process for me because of issues I have trusting others&amp;mdash;I compulsively check my girlfriend in areas where she by so many miles has the upper hand of practical and, yes, theoretical experience. By listening to an argument, I myself pass judgment on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://writing.upenn.edu/~taransky/Barthes.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;death of its author&lt;/a&gt;. While I enjoy this ultimate power, it cannot explain why I return to theory when all else fails&amp;mdash;indeed, it is a famed theorist&amp;rsquo;s failure that prompts one of my swift judgments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, it&amp;rsquo;s on the continued survival of authors after meeting my scrutiny that I base my returns. The reasons for these positive judgments are no doubt varied and incoherent to some, but I am sure that many follow a similar pattern. First, a writer will introduce familiar concept in unfamiliar language. Then, this language&amp;mdash;combined with elongated sentences&amp;mdash;renders said once-familiar concept gobbledygook. At this point, my capacity for calling BS on difficult works is hindered by my choice to read almost exclusively ~the classics~. This choice, and the knowledge of this choice, activates a psychological muscle in me that translates prestige as authority. When aggregated, this muscle operates as a sociological pressure. Seen below, the Tennis Court Oath makes abundantly clear in whom authority rests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/6/6d/Le_Serment_du_Jeu_de_paume.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Jacques-Louis David&#39;s *Tennis Court Oath* uses attention to show where power lies. &#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This all vindicates Nietzsche&amp;rsquo;s quote &amp;ldquo;I am not understood. Hence my authority.&amp;rdquo; This logic does not bode well for readers, however. Blinded by high-wattage prestige, one loses with the ability to criticize the ability to think. The authority that difficult, highly-regarded theory held over me also held me in its sway: I assumed that there was something essential to living life to be plumbed in theory, rather than a story told using the dictionary of a particular discipline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last year, I have maintained a weaning off of theory by, ironically, reading more theory. Richard Rorty refreshed pragmatism for a theory-weary America&amp;mdash;not by assuring us that what works in practice works regardless of the theory, but by stabbing epistemology in the back with what can best be termed an analytic deconstruction. Understanding his work proved to be a crucial step in unlearning much of what school had taught me, but elsewhere in my life, I clung to theory, thinking that the less-rigorous exercise, wellness, and movie literature could still be optimized by a turn towards theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I found were concrete ways in which that thought&amp;mdash;that life could be optimized by theory&amp;mdash;disappointed me. This disappointment brought the set of things I Know to Be True up with the set of things I &lt;em&gt;Think&lt;/em&gt; I Know to Be True. In other words, what I had read was made real before my eyes, elevating that knowledge to second-nature status. The vehicle for this realization was cooking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had begun really trying to cook two years ago, when I spurned the atrocities of my university&amp;rsquo;s dining hall. I asked for an Instant Pot that Christmas, and found hundreds of recipes to choose from. What the recipes called for, I did diligently. My girlfriend rarely challenged these steps, for the Instant Pot admits no air to its chamber, let alone the senses that allow facilitate good cooking. Recently, however, I&amp;rsquo;ve moved away from the Instant Pot in pursuit of perfectly-tuned seasoning and picturesque browning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In doing so, the superior wisdom of the cooks around me&amp;mdash;my girlfriend most loudly&amp;mdash;has battered the recipes I originally held so high. Trusting my own senses, and thinking critically about each step, have been given a newfound priority. The genius of cooking is that the tongue is already a great judge of cooking! In this light, it is immediately clear that famous names and convoluted explanations offer nowhere near the precision and attention that the mouth serves up instantaneously. &amp;ldquo;To write is to reach&amp;rdquo; said Barthes, and to cook might as well be added to that list. Each attempt is a venture into unknown territory, where local knowledge trumps the views from nowhere offered by orphaned recipes on cooking websites. Samin Nosrat&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/985508716&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Salt, Fat, Acid, Heat&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; grounds this truth with a million stories of direction-following as well as rule-breaking. The book explicitly claims to induct the laws of good cooking, but, implicitly, it works because of her history in kitchens around the world. She resists listicle format, step-by-step instructions in favor of narrative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This decision allows for reflection and judgment, and she constantly refers back to cooks&amp;rsquo; own palettes, finger tips, and eardrums. This reference (and deference) does the real work of teaching, imploring readers to become writers and eaters to become cooks. Trying to assimilate her principles with her recipes has already improved my cooking, and the fearlessness with which I annotate her beautifully-illustrated hardback has been a quietly-empowering experience. Cooking has shown me what my great professor Marlon Ross once told me, that great work speaks up to theory instead of letting theory talk down to it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>*Just Mercy* – a Legal Drama Adaptation That Fails to Do Justice to a Compelling Memoir</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2019/12/25/just-mercy-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2019/12/25/just-mercy-review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Edit 1/20/2020: check out &lt;a href=&#34;https://popculturebento.com/just-mercy-a-legal-drama-adaptation-that-fails-to-do-justice-to-a-compelling-memoir/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;em&gt;Pop Culture Bento&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*Just Mercy*’s most powerful scenes concern three different people condemned to death, all legally represented by Bryan Stevenson (Michael B. Jordan). These scenes punctuate the film, as we witness Stevenson’s growth from timid law student to successful advocate for those on death row. The strengths of *Just Mercy*—the eponymous memoir by Stevenson—lie in its plot and the range of lives contained within. But while the movie safely navigates the politics of portraying incarceration and gross injustice, it runs aground by bashing its viewership over the head by over-telling a story well shown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We see, first, the timid intern some 800-miles south of Harvard to meet a man his own age on death row. We see, then, the execution of Herb Richardson, a veteran who developed PTSD during Vietnam and proceeded to detonate a bomb on a lover’s porch. Finally, we see Walter McMillan (Jamie Foxx) run the gauntlet of police and legal implements to win freedom for a crime he did not commit, that canonic Southern Sin of murdering a white woman whilst Black. This story dominates &lt;em&gt;Just Mercy&lt;/em&gt;, and exposes features of the legal system in Monroeville, AL (the literary and extra-literary site of &lt;em&gt;To Kill a Mockingbird&lt;/em&gt;) that the average viewer would not believe existed in the 1980s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jordan cracks the ‘rational’ suspicions of the first two inmates, seeming both cool-headed and eager. He is at his best showing off these gifts, gifts the real Bryan Stevenson possesses, of blind understanding and unflappability. The stories of these men evoke grief and frustration without the aid of embellishment, and Just Mercy refrains admirably in their cases. And it is mostly free from fetish, a necessity that prisoner-centric films still neglect. With Walter McMillan, however, Jordan plays somewhat different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Walter McMillan, Stephenson transforms into the Atticus Finch archetype he jokes about. I had hoped for a courtroom monologue-free drama—true to life—but &lt;em&gt;Just Mercy&lt;/em&gt; just could not resist. Part of this discrepancy is a defect of the book-film transubstantiation: the book budgets roughly 10% of its pages to legal history and explaining the appeal process for Alabama death row inmates. Instead of devising some snappy montage (à la Michael Lewis film adaptations) explaining Alabama’s criminal processing and social statics showcasing racial disparities, &lt;em&gt;Just Mercy&lt;/em&gt;, the movie, uses Jordan and legal assistant Eva Ansley (Brie Larson) as mouthpieces. What results are dialogues where both characters tell the other what they clearly already know. &lt;em&gt;Just Mercy&lt;/em&gt; has not caught the trend of making its viewers think, spoon-feeding plot and context at its own expense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, Jordan says what doesn’t need to be said. When he visits McMillan’s family, extended family, and neighbors, it’s clear that Bryan Stevenson cares, that he goes beyond to help this man and his family, that he does not indict the men he sees (legally or illegally) on death row. Jordan uses his tremendously expressive face—clenched jaws and furrowed brows, or his 500-watt smile—to summon indignation or pleasure. He could very well have been the right actor for this movie, but his script sounds trite, due to his own delivery and adjustments, or to an overzealous writer/producer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honestly, I think much of *Just Mercy*’s shortcomings fall on director Destin Daniel Cretton, though surely the suits at Warner Bros. pushed the platitudes whenever possible. I do not mind adaptations heightening the drama of a book, but they must pass a few criteria:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Major plot events represented faithfully: Here, the movie receives close to full marks. The first meeting on death row, execution, and first trial are close to perfect, but the release of Walter McMillan sees Stevenson lecturing the courtroom before judgment is passed. This is stupid as well as melodramatic; part of the book’s brilliance is its emphasis on how pedestrian structural racism and indigent defense is in the legal system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adding to this mis-adaption is the portrayal of Monroeville’s prosecutor. Prosecutors have jobs, they have staffs, and they have electorates. These facts make their jobs less about justice than legal statistics and relationships with the police department. In the final 16 minutes, the prosecutor somehow turns from the patronizing careerist of the first two hours to sheepish moral man in full realization of his mistake. In reality, the state’s case was untenable. There was no uplifting realization by the white prosecutor that justice had not been served.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The adapted work’s environment communicated: This component is *Just Mercy*’s worst. The book leadens Stevenson’s journey with the twin histories of criminal prosecution and racism in America. As I mentioned before, the book resorts to chunky dialogue to explain basic facts of prosecution, but with no reference to the wider scope of these facts, no sense that these convictions happen in every jurisdiction in the United States.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Embellishments add to the message: I’m of two minds here. Jordan’s sermonizing belies Stevenson’s cool-headed determination. He was not Thurgood Marshall in the courtroom. But the adjustments to Walter McMillan’s incarceration were, at times, nice substitutes. Never in the book does Walter engage in a single aggressive or even energetic act. Here we see him thrashing against the human restraints that envelop him. The sense of rage, devoid in the book, is understandable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Just Mercy&lt;/em&gt; turns a book powerful for its facticality into something expected and over-determined. No one who reads the facts of this case would have the need to decipher, yet the all-too-familiar scenes of excessive force and righteousness of Michael B. Jordan as Bryan Stevenson are so obviously coded as to rob any viewers of their right to interpretation. The movie wins when getting out of its own way, offering the un-cinematic particularities (a scratchy record full of dread just before the electric chair) and plain humanity (Stevenson joking with his first client, about what he won’t say) of, you know, real humans. It is a poignant story of what it means for anyone with a modicum of power to remember the wrongs that have already happened instead of trying to inscribe their own story ignorant of what has come before. But check out the book instead from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/1119116448&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;your local library&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jojo Rabbit Explores Universal Notions of Morality through a Childlike Perspective</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2019/11/30/jojo-rabbit-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2019/11/30/jojo-rabbit-review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Edit 11/30/2019: check &lt;a href=&#34;https://popculturebento.com/jojo-rabbit-explores-universal-notions-of-morality-through-a-childlike-perspective/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; out at &lt;em&gt;Pop Culture Bento&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine a Beaux Arts mashup of &lt;em&gt;The Great Dictator&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Life is Beautiful&lt;/em&gt; set inside a &lt;em&gt;Moonrise Kingdom&lt;/em&gt; prequel. Can’t? Taika Waititi has. &lt;em&gt;Jojo Rabbit&lt;/em&gt; finds a small, timid Hitler Youth (the &lt;em&gt;Moonrise Kingdom&lt;/em&gt; bit) named Jojo (Roman Griffin Davis) in a world much too big for him. Waititi brings the fanaticism and anti-Semitism of Nazi Germany into close quarters by portraying Jojo’s imaginary friend, Adolf Hitler. His portrayal is an incredible use of dramatic irony: we see the craziness of Hitler’s cult of personality and ideology, while the ten year-old sees his idol. Same as any sports star, Jojo’s room is decked out in memorabilia and posters to the Führer’s power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Waititi The Actor mirrors Chaplin by lampooning Hitler’s decisions and imitating his manner of speech. All the silliness you’d expect from a ten year-old is there, along with biting jokes for those geopolitically inclined. On a different level, Waititi The Director channels &lt;em&gt;Life is Beautiful&lt;/em&gt; by showing us a world three feet high instead of six. Jojo Rabbit is a coming-of-age tale, with adults tugging at the strings of his life behind some curtain of maturity. These adults are sometimes imbeciles (low-level Nazi soldiers), sometimes courageous (Jojo’s mother [Scarlett Johannson]), and sometimes both depending on the situation (washed up Captain Klenzendorf [Sam Rockwell]). They operate formally in the adult realm, which inexorably approaches and darkens Jojo’s world throughout the film, but Waititi The Screenwriter manages to find great laughs in the childlike tendencies of even the Gestapo. This is not to say that the director makes fun of the culture of fear or terrible tragedy that infected Nazi Germany. He finds laughs in both dark and lighter moments by exposing the ridiculousness of Nazism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me say this again: Jojo Rabbit is hilarious, sharing atmosphere with &lt;em&gt;The Grand Budapest Hotel&lt;/em&gt;. And it is because of this childlike urgency and earnestness that the emotional content impresses so thoroughly. It is every bit as solemn as *Budapest*’s gravest moments, without the reverence. The Gestapo comes, as it always does, for Elsa (Thomasin McKenzie), a friend of Jojo’s dead sister living in her room. McKenzie packs emotion to spare. With tenuous power over Jojo as his physical and intellectual superior, she delivers stinging rebukes of Jojo’s indoctrination, while ultimately boxing herself up in his attic. This confinement heightens every interaction with her, and allows her to speak beyond her situation for people in hiding everywhere. Jojo Rabbit navigates conflicting ideas of right and wrong, exploiting the disagreements to heartbreaking, funny, or joyous ends.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>American Heartbreak</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2019/11/21/american-heartbreak/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2019/11/21/american-heartbreak/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am the American heartbreak–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rock on which Freedom&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stumped its toe–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The great mistake&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That Jamestown made&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Long ago&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;— Langston Hughes
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever I try to recall this poem, I search for &amp;ldquo;Plymouth Rock poem&amp;rdquo;, and freak out beacuse I can&amp;rsquo;t find it for a few seconds. This is because, all along, Hughes alludes to the founding of our nation without ever saying so. He points to our founding virtue, Freedom, and asks the reader to define it&amp;mdash;suddenly&amp;mdash;in their head. This question calls up our national myth, of virile men casting off the oppressive British yoke, which implants in Americans a desire for revolution and newness and independence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find this desire each time I encounter American colonial history. There is the Massachusetts Bay colonizers, and the Virginia Company of London, more than anything else I want to race forward to 1776. American history teaching defaults to setting our cast of characters on the North American continent in order to reach revolution, with that noble end somehow justifying everything that came before (if not ethically, then morally: we suffered, and thus &lt;em&gt;deserve&lt;/em&gt; Freedom). In the same way, the outposts of our frontiersmen and women served to legitimize the murder of indigenous people, conquest of Mexican territory, and deaths of our own colonizers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this myth may be just that, it is a powerful story that is consistently told. Hughes rides its momentum, immediately clipping America&amp;rsquo;s great strides towards Freedom with the realities of chattel slavery. Nothing could be further from Freedom. But Hughes is acknowledging the promise of Freedom: one&amp;rsquo;s heart can&amp;rsquo;t break if it doesn&amp;rsquo;t first beat. By acknowledging the promise along with its failure, Hughes ties this heartbreak inextricably to our nation&amp;rsquo;s founding. This is &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; American heartbreak, bound up with the 400-year history of democracy in Jamestown. Hughes pulls us&amp;mdash;with present tense, with reference to Jamestown, by describing something so hard, so immovable, so central to that other early colony&amp;mdash;into the contradiction hidden in our nation&amp;rsquo;s founding, and still so hidden today.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3 Things I Learned from my Marathon</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2019/11/16/3-things-i-learned-from-my-marathon/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2019/11/16/3-things-i-learned-from-my-marathon/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Let me avoid&amp;mdash;for all our sakes&amp;mdash;transforming my blog into a clichéd, over-exposed photo essay of my personal struggle running. That being said, I was struck, as it was impossible not to be, by several aspects of the race weekend:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Marathons are a fucking business. The City of Richmond anaesthetized its downtown and a good chunk of its of the scenery for this event. Unimaginably, the $100 entry fees are well-priced (at least for the marathon). Every mile brought, alternately, water, powerade, and port-a-johns or a live band. The entire day preceding was filled with events and vendors at Richmond&amp;rsquo;s convention center. In addition to the requisite race shirt, medal, and very necessary blanket, the finish line included yoga sessions, beer on tap, and pizza, all included. Meeting this massive coordination of resources were runners&amp;mdash;truly of all types&amp;mdash;swaddled in air-wicking this and energy-conserving that. They came and came, some twenty odd thousand, the majority towing families, friends, and track clubs. As a lone runner with 4 year-old shoes, all this &lt;em&gt;baggage&lt;/em&gt; was so apparent. And sometimes this baggage wanted to make itself known, with a glimmering wristwatch or suspension systems for their extraneous gear. At day&amp;rsquo;s end, however, there are no shortcuts through 26.2 miles. Your \$250 Vaporfly&amp;rsquo;s are no match for my ragged Kinvara 5&amp;rsquo;s if my breath is measured and stride high.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;My stride, however, was not high. This was absolutely an ordeal, if not quite of epic proportions. Due mostly to the hard shock of tarmac and my injury-diminished mileage these last few weeks, my calves began to make their presence felt about 4 miles in, which was about 10 miles earlier than I had hoped. Still, Richmond&amp;rsquo;s gentle terrain kept my pretty good until mile 16, when:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wind made forward progress suddenly a thing to think about, instead of do&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My dinner finally caught up with me
Fighting these knocked me out of a stride I had found for the first time around the half-marathon mark. I made it through the next ten miles because of the runners showing me left and right how to fight, and the outstanding spectators. During my training, I probably saw a total of 200 people, most of which were at a single park in Charlottesville. Here I could not run 100 meters without a banana, a high-five, or a swig of Miller Lite. At mile 21, I heard the first call for &lt;strong&gt;BEER&lt;/strong&gt;, and double taked, able to snake across the road to the last volunteer. That helped.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;This was as much a marathon as it was a real estate tour. I had always drove through Monument Ave. and thought it quaint in comparison to New Orleans&amp;rsquo; St. Charles St. It turns out that is not where Richmond&amp;rsquo;s wealthy live. Continue on Monument, crossing over the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.oxfordscholarship.com/view/10.1093/acprof:oso/9780199977260.001.0001/acprof-9780199977260-chapter-12&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;freeway built to punish Black neighborhoods for school integration&lt;/a&gt;, and you&amp;rsquo;ll enter Henrico County. There Riverview Dr. follows lazily the James, and hundred-acre estates dominate both City and County waterfronts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parasite Refreshes Horror with a Hefty Dose of Social Realism</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2019/11/11/parasite-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2019/11/11/parasite-review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Edit 11/15/2019: check &lt;a href=&#34;https://popculturebento.com/parasite-refreshes-horror-with-a-hefty-dose-of-social-realism/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; out at &lt;em&gt;Pop Culture Bento&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No review—drawn inevitably from the vocabulary and lessons of preceding films—will do the novelty and creativity of Bong Joon-ho’s masterpiece justice. &lt;em&gt;Parasite&lt;/em&gt; is the best film to be released since &lt;em&gt;Mad Max: Fury Road&lt;/em&gt;, possibly since &lt;em&gt;12 Years a Slave&lt;/em&gt;. *Parasite*’s uncanny setting makes possible its combination of comedy and horror that justifies the second act’s shocking twists. In this way, it can be seen as the Korean and class counterpart to Get Out, with more emphasis on the realism than the horror.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film is set in a contemporary Metropolis: its sprawling poverty serves the hermetically-sealed homes of the super-rich. Bong dances over the border between these realms, following—classically—the help that enters and exits these homes daily. In the title credits, we watch a drunk piss on the English basement-home of our star family, who are unemployed and failing to keep up with the vagaries of capitalism. When an unexpected chance to tutor at the home of a super-rich family opens, our family jumps at the opportunity. This first hour is a riot. Full of wit, we see them exploit the naïvete of the super-rich, locating the meaning behind ‘parasite’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But *Parasite*’s trick is its information imbalances. In Act I, our family colludes to carve out for themselves a way to live. Act II see-saws back this imbalance. Events begin to happen to our family rather than by our family. Still, Bong doesn’t shroud us in a JJ Abrams information fog, with terrors leaping out from dark corners of the screen. Instead, we see how the super-rich, themselves, feed off Korea’s underclass, dictating their schedule, their names, their words. Their financial insecurity keeps them in the thrall of this rich family, and pushes them to box out any competitors. These economically-violent delights have physically-violent ends. Where many films inspect class, the invisible fence that separates rich and poor, this film inspects wealth’s first derivative, inequality: we watch in real time as those invisible fences are built. &lt;em&gt;Parasite&lt;/em&gt; shows how the cherries that top the artisanal cakes drip with the blood of the poor.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Aspirational Efficiency</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2019/11/07/aspirational-efficiency/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2019/11/07/aspirational-efficiency/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The easiest way to derail any work that I am doing is by linking to an article ranking and comparing things that will help me live a better life. That article might rank the 10 best productivity apps, it may uncover new services which partition and categorize every second of my day, or&amp;mdash;as it did yesterday&amp;mdash;it could offer me a phone that can satisfy my needs immediately, stripping my day of wasted time. The only certainty is that I, in my manifold time management skills, will click on that link.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought this was a phenomenon entirely local to myself until I saw this &lt;a href=&#34;https://aeon.co/essays/how-did-being-happy-become-a-matter-of-relentless-competitive-work&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; from Aeon, noting that life management has become a juggernaut in consumer retail, with &amp;ldquo;self-care and anti-stress products now rounding out the bestseller list on Amazon&amp;rdquo;. We&amp;rsquo;ve reined in other animals, organizations of people, and our bodies by calibrating each measurable parameter, so why not do the same for our minds? Unfortunately, we don&amp;rsquo;t seem quite as pliant as the optimization equations imply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This logic, made inexorable by limitless access to information, tugs at our happiness. Behind whatever tool or activity or person present before us lurks an alternative, a next-best option. This idea has driven every rationalist attempt at decision making, but its actual calculus has changed considerably since the 1990s. Before then, catalogued libraries and television delivered then-unprecedented access to information. The task of research had become immediately more accessible, but also less clear. Suddenly, more and more causes sprang up to explain each effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The move from card catalogues and TV to Wikipedia and on-demand streaming was a leap in this dimension. Different from past moves was the sheer scale of new information. The closest comparison to make would likely be the telegram that could relay news around the world in minutes, but that did not solve the last-mile problem that our phones and computers did. Similar to past moves is the growing illusion of choice. Most definitions model illusory choice as a free decision between a constrained set of options, like choosing from a soda machine that offers a dozen brands but where every choice is a Coca-Cola product. But rather than onstrained options, I interpret illusory choice as constrained decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our brain budgets time and resources based on prior neurological sequences, updating expectations with each iteration. While we may understand how normal it is not to find an exhaustive cost-benefits comparison of the more than 2,000 results for &amp;ldquo;thimble&amp;rdquo; on Amazon, our brains may not. Our expectations have been conditioned by the norms of evidence-based administration to treat anything less than exhaustive comparisons as failure. This extends to our lives, where exhaustive comparison has meant nothing less than exhaustion. Where once, exhaustive comparisons meant eyeballing dozens, now it means eyeballing hundreds, thousands, or millions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our internal search processes can&amp;rsquo;t handle such scale. While they have gradually widened, the velocity of extension by the market has effectively capped the rate at which we had to develop non-exhaustive ways to search. When the village had a single cobbler, shoes were a constant, not a variable to optimize over. Still, when there are ten types of black beans at the grocery store, they can be compared quite readily. But when it&amp;rsquo;s always possible to opt for peer-to-peer sellers in Kolkata over the ~local~ Walmart, people are given the room every day to exhaust their critical thinking skills trying to gauge the expected payoffs of a hundred options, and a million more they know to be lurking, accessible to anyone with the right search terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our minds haven&amp;rsquo;t caught up yet. They can take on waves of epic proportions, but a tide that lifts them high enough to see the world&amp;rsquo;s ginormity will overwhelm. I see two ways out: time and pragmatism. The first just says that after enough time passes, our minds will adjust, will think in different ways to approach this different problem. But that option offers only consolation to people currently. Option two offers that different way. Construct in your mind a noble lie, something appealing but fanciful. Then, believe in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adhering to a set of values fixes those variables as constants. This is Marie Kondo for your mind, with the tiny caveat that beliefs weigh far more than shower organizers, dressers, or homes. The values chosen don&amp;rsquo;t have to conform to Marie Kondo&amp;ndash;like advice. In fact, choosing something already at tension with what FastCompany promises are the best ways to increase productivity is probably best. It&amp;rsquo;s good training for the future. Rather, pick values that will let you do the most of your wants, your in-the-moment pleasures. Do not conflate &amp;lsquo;do the most&amp;rsquo; with &amp;lsquo;most choices&amp;rsquo;. To do the most, you need clear boundaries that, if crossed, bind you to decisions, decisions that you could theoretically even come to regret, but decisions that you need to make. Pragmatism means believing what needs to be believed, even if it can&amp;rsquo;t stand up to rationalist inquiry.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>20 Miles Later</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2019/10/20/20-miles-later/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2019/10/20/20-miles-later/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In 4 weeks, I&amp;rsquo;ll toe the line at the VCU Health ^[Kudos to VCU for ending their practice of suing patients for non-payment! I wish the same could be said for UVA.] &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.richmondmarathon.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Richmond Marathon&lt;/a&gt;. This last month has seen me run consistently farther than I ever had before, so I&amp;rsquo;ve had to find new places to keep my legs and mind busy. At four weeks out, most marathon plans advocate for a very long run, of about 20 miles. I did it yesterday, and I&amp;rsquo;m still not sure if my calves will be ready to go &lt;em&gt;next&lt;/em&gt; Saturday, let alone tomorrow!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conveniently, Charllottesville has a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rivannatrails.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;beautiful 20-mile trail&lt;/a&gt; that circumscribes the city. All of the lands are City parks or private easements, so it tends to be corners of property and scraps of backyards, and a lot of dilapidated industry. But the isolation can be unnerving: I can count on a single hand the amount of women I have seen run alone during the 15+ hours I&amp;rsquo;ve spent on it. There are several sections where the trail curls and the trees lean over and I think to myself &lt;em&gt;what a wonderful place to be attacked&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the vast majority of the trail isn&amp;rsquo;t like this. Much of the trail parallels Charlottesville&amp;rsquo;s poorest neighborhoods, where residents have had to deal with me confronting a lot of my own privilege. The vast majority is me, clohtes only in 5&amp;rdquo; running shorts, a watch, and sneakers taking up space and air outside someone else&amp;rsquo;s home. Here it&amp;rsquo;s the lack of clothing and equipment that define my position. I have a place to store my clothing, I have the resources to clean my sweaty shorts three times a week, I don&amp;rsquo;t need to bring my phone because I&amp;rsquo;m confident no one will look at me like I want their money. For a few minutes each Saturday I take in the atmosphere outside your home, leaving only the sound of my shoes pounding the trail, and my lungs heaving slightly.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Distortion in Vertigo (1958)</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2019/08/27/vertigo-1958/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2019/08/27/vertigo-1958/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Edit 10/20/2019: check &lt;a href=&#34;https://popculturebento.com/the-all-american-gaze-distorted-perspective-in-alfred-hitchcocks-vertigo/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; out at &lt;em&gt;Pop Culture Bento&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hitchcock’s cinematographic style changes with each script and year in which he immerses himself, unlike the storybook qualities of Wes Anderson or the placid &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/quotes/665415-drops-dripped-quiet-talk-went-on-horses-neighed-and-scuffled&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Drops dripped&lt;/a&gt; of Andrei Tarkovsky. &lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt;, at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.com/news/entertainment-arts-19078948&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;dizzying heights&lt;/a&gt; of Hitchcock’s mastery, leads us into John Ferguson’s (James Stewart) mind&amp;mdash;distorted by the lethal, dozen-story fall of a partner trying to save Ferguson&amp;mdash;by forcing us into cramped spaces and mocking our spatial judgment. I argue that in doing so, Hitchcock forces viewers to understand the disorientation and claustrophobia that Ferguson so clearly feels. In doing so, Hitchcock makes reasonable the otherwise unreasonable male gaze of Ferguson and, by association, the effects that gaze causes, though it’s unclear whether it serves to morally justify that gaze. So, in-movie, Hitchcock uses film technique to warp what would otherwise be a black-and-white judgment about Ferguson’s behavior towards Judy Barton (Kim Novak).  Out-of-movie, I finally make the claim that this in-movie phenomenon critiques white American masculinity’s treatment of the Other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of this analysis was impossible for me until I considered David Lynch’s &lt;em&gt;Mulholland Drive&lt;/em&gt;&amp;mdash;there were too many motifs in &lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt; to grab a hold of! Hitchcock employs a &lt;a href=&#34;https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/514a2911e4b0896b36342655/1482995944327-EWLBUKOGUEVV2J7984Q3/ke17ZwdGBToddI8pDm48kDJVOyiZxV_-dowl7sRu02MUqsxRUqqbr1mOJYKfIPR7LoDQ9mXPOjoJoqy81S2I8N_N4V1vUb5AoIIIbLZhVYwL8IeDg6_3B-BRuF4nNrNcQkVuAT7tdErd0wQFEGFSnM_12NgTIazSm1At4R8ulVAcqDD8dBOmEycJv1fx_vd3MyvpBiIzzydoM1I6fLa65Q/image-asset.png?format=2500w&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;contrasting color palette&lt;/a&gt;, his signature(ly disturbing) perplexion with blonde women, and an unforgettable break in narrative. &lt;em&gt;Mulholland&lt;/em&gt; offers those motifs amped up to surrealistic proportions, with color palettes at near antagonistic levels, the blondes shining ever more platinum, though its narrative break is difficult to pinpoint. Connecting &lt;em&gt;Mulholland Drive&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt; makes the interpretation of Hitchcock’s film no easier, but facilitates a shift in mindset that rendered Vertigo much more interpretable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mean this: Lynch is enigmatic as hell, but he continues to give interviews. In these interviews, he surrenders much of his creativity to what he terms “dream-logic”, and it stands out immediately. Dream-logic connects two objects despite their inconsistencies according to logic-logic. Such an approach finds its Western roots entirely recent, coming primarily out of Sigmund Freud’s &lt;em&gt;Interpretation of Dreams&lt;/em&gt;. Its epistemology is usually visual in [Lynch’s] movies, though connections via homonym or punnery are entirely within the bounds of Freudian analysis. While a novelty in 2001 &lt;em&gt;Mulholland Drive&lt;/em&gt; premiered, 1958 saw psychoanalysis at its peak of influence. This rise crashed into Hitchcock’s prior work with film noir, convoluted plots that often involved damaged detectives and female subjects vulnerable physically and mentally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt; synthesizes these two strands. Kim Novak’s characters—one before, one after the narrative break—vie for their freedom against their supposed history. In classic Hitchcock fashion, &lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt; can be summarized as a Wrong Man Film,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:cf-The-Wrong-Man&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:cf-The-Wrong-Man&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; where the protagonist is mistaken for a doppelgänger implicated in deep, deep shit. Unclassically, *Vertigo*’s protagonist is no man; and its protagonist(s) is/are not its central character(s). Novak’s Judy Barton is modeled (mostly) against her will after a prior, dead San Francisco socialite, Madeleine Ester,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:Novak-in-Act-1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:Novak-in-Act-1&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; who herself models a [much more] prior, dead San Francisco socialite. The complicity of each in creating their respective &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iron_cage&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;iron cloaks&lt;/a&gt; of identity is uncertain, but beside the point—Ferguson’s male gaze visualizes these identities before they are realized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often enough, the male gaze is analyzed as a whole, apart from its sometimes very specific set of eyes. I get at Ferguson’s specific set through Hitchcock’s motifs and cinematography. Ferguson’s gaze is set very literally in the film’s opening. Hitchcock shakes up the presumably keen vision of a detective with his partner’s death. The fall and the height and the guilt confuse themselves in Ferguson’s head to deliver a crippling case of vertigo, rendering him unproductive and idle, unmoored from his former senses of intelligence. There is nothing objective against which Ferguson can mark the damage his trauma wrought, no other detectives to which he can compare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hitchock will signify this psychosis slowly at first, then all at once. This chronological pattern approximates the spiral imagery so fundamental to &lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt;. Saul Bass’ iconic movie poster design depicts Ferguson plunging into a line-drawn spiral. This third dimension is added, and reflects the way objects track in wide-diameter circles, speeding as the circles shrink and finally encloses the object.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:Cf-This-comical&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:Cf-This-comical&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Concerned of the obsession his wife (Madeleine) exhibits for a suicidal ancestor, Ferguson’s friend sends him to play private detective. While Scottie takes logical steps to follow the wife’s story, his social isolation and physical trauma get the better of him. His steps culminate in a famous leap into the brisk San Francisco Bay, where, just before, Madeleine plunged, unconscious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.ytimg.com/vi/ih-KeOf3xQQ/maxresdefault.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;*Vertigo*’s massive field of view.&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the dive in, James Ferguson can never quite get himself on solid ground. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://i1.wp.com/www.abelardomorell.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/2017_Flowers-For-Lisa-76-After-Hitchcock%E2%80%99s-Vertigo-2017-copy-1.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;spiral patterns&lt;/a&gt; begin to crop up in paintings, department stores, cemeteries, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://2.bp.blogspot.com/-I5ob7SqVmUQ/T1rcELu28SI/AAAAAAAACaM/bt6R6pd-4a0/s1600/Hitchcock+Vertigo.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The tight spiral of Madeleine, her ancestor, and eventually Judy connects the three in Ferguson’s dream-logic.&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caught in the inner circles of a deepening plot and deepening conspiracy, Hitchcock simulates what Ferguson’s deepening psychosis&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:Note-that-this-m&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:Note-that-this-m&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; must feel like with cinematographic trickery that encloses Ferguson’s figure, disclosing the craze lurking inside his obsessed mind. In *Vertigo*’s camerawork, deep focus and a 2-D plane forces our visual cortex to compare the near and far. The video below demonstrates this several times.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/bDwPJ5IaJ2g&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Those yellow flowers that Scottie walks behind at 1:59 appear taller than him in that moment, and the obscured view traps his figure in the history, mystery, and death that linger after Novak exits the scene. Hitchcock further unsettles viewers in :17, not with the normal technique of a dolly following Ferguson and suggesting danger, but with a shot from below. This camera setting exaggerates the height and length of objects outside focal point, making the 3ft flowers equal the 6ft Ferguson in height. The mastery here is the unresolved tension between these instances of camera trickery and Hitchcock’s concurrent attention to truly large objects. The enormity of the Golden Gate bridge in one famous shot anchors the nearly surreal imagery elsewhere in &lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt;, cementing a permanent unease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add this to the geologic folding that turns ordinary car following into labyrinthine mazes:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/fNyUpJGEnR4?t=73&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And of course, *Vertigo*’s signature camera effect, the zoom-in/dolly-out:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/O888bu0QrMg?t=56&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The spirals (2:13), the huge objects (:36), the zoom-in/dolly-out (1:20) culminate in *Vertigo*’s quasi-climax:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/GjPCk494e5Q&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The scene in Mission San Juan Bautista also bears striking resemblances to the work of Italian surrealist Giorgio de Chirico. De Chirico’s work produces a sense of unease through its emphasis on the uncanny, that which is not quite and yet almost is. I like to think of a composite image, the subimages of which are all perfectly possible, though the composite somehow not being possible. In the image below, which reminds me both of the Mission and the ever-out-of-reach Madeleine, the sky is a natural color for sunsets and the long shadows possible at twilight, but the building is so bright and the shadows so stark that the image could not possibly depict a real event. Hitchcock, toeing the sur/realism line, never leaves us with quite the uncanny images or impossible geometries to prove the sort of dream-logic that Lynch would make explicit, but these scenes add up. With snaking streets, out-of-proportion objects, and color palette, builds a profile of the uncanny without ever letting us put a finger on it. Like Ferguson, the viewer is hard-pressed to resolve the visual inputs Hitchcock offers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://mmbiz.qpic.cn/mmbiz_jpg/Gou4x1ymnaWvmfhCgIsalNJKlyZ04HiczUsV3K7mJbNanian5d0xowY3sDAaWLcOUIwbbkvajPRVBCH9Zy8eBx5g/640?wx_fmt=jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Giorgio de Chirico&#39;s Metaphysical Art movement&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This kind of confusion invites resolution for the viewer into a reality-less vacuum. Similarly, while Ferguson is a detective, used to getting to the Bottom of Things, he can’t in this situation. All his preternatural detective powers have been duped by trauma and deceit. He is painfully aware which way is up and which down, but not much beyond that. Through all the twists and turns, Ferguson never understands (or rather, never is able to convince himself he understands) Madeleine. The history (of Madeleine, of Dolores, etc.) regresses too far for his eyes to penetrate. Unable to free himself from this convoluted plot and detached from reality, Ferguson imposes a narrative on Judy. &lt;em&gt;He&lt;/em&gt; now makes her tick. And the viewer accepts this to some degree because the story is resolution-deficient. Trapped staring through Ferguson’s gaze, escape is&amp;mdash;depending on the specific viewer&amp;mdash;to some extent preferable, even when it carries such gross implications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The endgame of Ferguson’s gaze is sex. The male gaze conjures scenarios&amp;mdash;no matter how fantastical&amp;mdash;where legally-consensual&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:Otherwise-one-wo&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:Otherwise-one-wo&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; sex occurs, and relates those scenarios with the real world in order to judge their plausibility, filtering those implausible scenarios from the gazer’s strategies. A plausible scenario would mean that Ferguson has successfully dissected her, inducting her motives, and&amp;mdash;with them in hand&amp;mdash;~smooth-talked~ her into thinking that his motives overlap with hers. But since Ferguson cannot understand Judy, because he cannot relate fantasy with reality, he resorts to the truly outrageous step of &lt;em&gt;realizing&lt;/em&gt; those fantastical scenarios and their absurd bargaining power disparities, molding Judy so that her [perceived] motives can be &lt;em&gt;induced&lt;/em&gt; to comport with Ferguson’s desires. This decision fabricates the conscience-satisfying, superficially-consensual sex that ends &lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt;. Horrifically, the viewers’ interests are sympathetic to Ferguson’s, begging for plot resolution, but are then [hopefully] spoiled when they are confronted with the idea that their interests imply the exploitation of Judy. From beneath the comfort of 1950’s American entertainment, a violent man watches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In interpreting the greater significance of &lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt;, I benefit again from viewing Hitchcock through Lynch’s rear window:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My childhood was elegant homes, tree-lined streets, the milkman, building backyard forts, droning airplanes, blue skies, picket fences, green grass, cherry trees. Middle America as it&amp;rsquo;s supposed to be. But on the cherry tree there&amp;rsquo;s this pitch oozing out – some black, some yellow, and millions of red ants crawling all over it. I discovered that if one looks a little closer at this beautiful world, there are &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; red ants underneath.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:Lynch-David-and&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:Lynch-David-and&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hitchcock views America somewhat from the outside. He picks a very particular part of the US, one where the histories of people who were not British is readily apparent in depictions of frontier life (and Native death). This choice primarily works to operate on the level of uncanny history, a history that few are equipped to read completely into their own history of America, but with pieces that all can recognize. It’s therefore both easy to dissociate Ferguson’s particular position from their own, while difficult to completely disentangle the silver screen from real life. Stewart’s roles prior to &lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt; included US everyman turned Congressman in &lt;em&gt;Mr. Smith Goes to Washington&lt;/em&gt;, aviator Charles Lindbergh in &lt;em&gt;The Spirit of St. Louis&lt;/em&gt;, a cowboy in &lt;em&gt;Winchester ‘73&lt;/em&gt;, George Bailey in &lt;em&gt;It’s a Wonderful Life&lt;/em&gt;. I cannot think of another actor who so embodied rich, moral American-ness during this time. Hitchcock then takes apart this rich, moral, American figure by finding within him obsession, formidable sexuality, and desperation. A bit of psychological trauma sets off (or reveals?) the ants in this cherry tree. &lt;strong&gt;More specifically, the bent of America is towards taking that which/who is not ours and assimilating them, without dealing with “underlying” issues.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find it difficult to read Hitchcock as directing in so critical a fashion as I have just suggested, given the patent fetishism of Kim Novak’s characters. In that vein, I would echo the interpretation of American men above, but stop short of believing Hitchcock to be fully critical. For him, I don’t think the discomfort of Judy’s situation outweighs his fetish for Novak. While &lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt; is a unique instance of 1950’s filmmaking for its unsettling features and early integration of psychoanalysis, I’m not convinced of any allegations of intent on Hitchcock’s part. It very well may be that old Alfred was the astute critic I have made him to be, but it could equally (in my eyes) be the case that he was utterly obsessed with Novak. To resolve *Vertigo*’s interpretation would be to impose, for all but the most ardent individualist, an idea of its meaning absent context of its author. While I generally distance myself from arguments about authorial intent, I do not want to foreclose the possibility of its import to other viewers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:cf-The-Wrong-Man&#34;&gt;cf. &lt;em&gt;The Wrong Man&lt;/em&gt; (1956) &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:cf-The-Wrong-Man&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:Novak-in-Act-1&#34;&gt;Novak in ~Act 1~. &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:Novak-in-Act-1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:Cf-This-comical&#34;&gt;Cf. This comical &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.spiralwishingwells.com/images/all-wells-and-vortx-steve-1000.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;image&lt;/a&gt; of a charity coin spinner, or how a &lt;a href=&#34;https://images.fineartamerica.com/images/artworkimages/mediumlarge/2/gravity-well-spencer-sutton.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;gravity well&lt;/a&gt; may alter planetary orbits. &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:Cf-This-comical&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:Note-that-this-m&#34;&gt;Note that this means thoughts become detached from external reality. When we understand that no person can diagnose another from anywhere but their own viewpoint firmly in the mainstream of productive society, it becomes clear that the usage of the word ‘reality’ is misleading. Reality does not exist&amp;mdash;it is judged to exist&amp;mdash;but always with psychology this judgment originates from the highly-educated professional class. Understanding what ‘external reality’ entails means Ferguson could both be “detached from external reality” and quite rational in both his and the viewers’ eyes. Hitchcock plays on this truth in many films. Just because you’re paranoid doesn’t mean somebody isn’t out to get you. &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:Note-that-this-m&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:Otherwise-one-wo&#34;&gt;Otherwise, one would have no need for fantasizing. &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:Otherwise-one-wo&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:Lynch-David-and&#34;&gt;Lynch, David and Rodley, Chris (2005). Lynch on Lynch (revised edition). New York: Faber and Faber. ISBN 978-0-571-22018-2. &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:Lynch-David-and&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Federal Register API</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2019/08/03/federal-register-api/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2019/08/03/federal-register-api/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tl-dr&#34;&gt;TL;DR&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I created an &lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt; client to fetch data from the Federal Register, replacing an R package that had not been updated for years. It was my first foray into APIs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United States &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.federalregister.gov/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Federal Register&lt;/a&gt; is the [slowly] clearing house for every revision to US administrative law, regulatory enforcement, and the more stupid forms of jockeying and horn-tooting by federal agencies. The website, charged with the supremely bureaucratic duty of pigeonholing and circumscribing every sort of &amp;lt;&lt;event&gt;&amp;gt; in Washington, is quite beautiful. Its ease, features, and appearance bear the marks of something that is truly for the public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To aid readers, [and the odd corporation trying to stay a step ahead of environmental regulations,] the Office of the Federal Register got a leg up from a developer who made an API client for R. Unfortunately,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:And-quite-ironic&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:And-quite-ironic&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that client has been rendered useless by updates. In the name of openness digital and governmental, I set to work on a new API client that would:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;teach me the fundamentals of APIs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;display some clever solutions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:And-quite-ironic&#34;&gt;And quite ironically for an institution with steeped in such bureaucracy. &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:And-quite-ironic&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
