<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>marathon | Corey Runkel</title>
    <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/tags/marathon/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://runkelcorey.github.io/tags/marathon/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>marathon</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Corey N. Runkel 2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 20 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://runkelcorey.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>marathon</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/tags/marathon/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>20 Miles Later</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2019/10/20/20-miles-later/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2019/10/20/20-miles-later/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In 4 weeks, I&amp;rsquo;ll toe the line at the VCU Health ^[Kudos to VCU for ending their practice of suing patients for non-payment! I wish the same could be said for UVA.] &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.richmondmarathon.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Richmond Marathon&lt;/a&gt;. This last month has seen me run consistently farther than I ever had before, so I&amp;rsquo;ve had to find new places to keep my legs and mind busy. At four weeks out, most marathon plans advocate for a very long run, of about 20 miles. I did it yesterday, and I&amp;rsquo;m still not sure if my calves will be ready to go &lt;em&gt;next&lt;/em&gt; Saturday, let alone tomorrow!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conveniently, Charllottesville has a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rivannatrails.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;beautiful 20-mile trail&lt;/a&gt; that circumscribes the city. All of the lands are City parks or private easements, so it tends to be corners of property and scraps of backyards, and a lot of dilapidated industry. But the isolation can be unnerving: I can count on a single hand the amount of women I have seen run alone during the 15+ hours I&amp;rsquo;ve spent on it. There are several sections where the trail curls and the trees lean over and I think to myself &lt;em&gt;what a wonderful place to be attacked&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the vast majority of the trail isn&amp;rsquo;t like this. Much of the trail parallels Charlottesville&amp;rsquo;s poorest neighborhoods, where residents have had to deal with me confronting a lot of my own privilege. The vast majority is me, clohtes only in 5&amp;rdquo; running shorts, a watch, and sneakers taking up space and air outside someone else&amp;rsquo;s home. Here it&amp;rsquo;s the lack of clothing and equipment that define my position. I have a place to store my clothing, I have the resources to clean my sweaty shorts three times a week, I don&amp;rsquo;t need to bring my phone because I&amp;rsquo;m confident no one will look at me like I want their money. For a few minutes each Saturday I take in the atmosphere outside your home, leaving only the sound of my shoes pounding the trail, and my lungs heaving slightly.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
