<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>YPFS | Corey Runkel</title>
    <link>/categories/ypfs/</link>
      <atom:link href="/categories/ypfs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>YPFS</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© C.N. Runkel 2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>YPFS</title>
      <link>/categories/ypfs/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reserve liquidity facilities shift from advanced economies to emerging markets</title>
      <link>/2020/07/01/reserve-liquidity-facilities-shift-from-advanced-economies-to-emerging-markets/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2020/07/01/reserve-liquidity-facilities-shift-from-advanced-economies-to-emerging-markets/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This post was originally &lt;a href=&#34;https://som.yale.edu/blog/reserve-liquidity-facilities-shift-from-advanced-economies-to-emerging-markets&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;published&lt;/a&gt; on the YPFS Systemic Risk blog&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On June 19, the European Central Bank (ECB) &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ecb.europa.eu/press/pr/date/2020/html/ecb.pr200619~8badb7725d.en.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;joined&lt;/a&gt; the central banks of England, Japan, and Switzerland in scaling back the frequency of their US dollar liquidity swaps with the Federal Reserve (Fed). &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.federalreserve.gov/regreform/reform-swaplines.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Central bank liquidity swap lines&lt;/a&gt; facilitate access to foreign capital during periods of international financial stress. While these bilateral swap operations with the Fed have slowed, the ECB &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ecb.europa.eu/press/pr/date/2020/html/ecb.pr200625~60373986e5.en.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; on June 25 the establishment of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://som.yale.edu/blog/ecb-announces-new-eurosystem-repo-facility-to-provide-euro-liquidity&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Eurosystem repo facility for central banks&lt;/a&gt; (EUREP). The new facility will complement the ECB’s current bilateral swap lines by allowing for less stable currencies to participate in repurchase agreements. This post summarizes the recent activity on Fed swap lines and documents the shift in currency facilities from those aimed at the sturdiest reserve institutions to those aimed at central banks with smaller stocks of dollars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;fed-swap-lines-remain-successful&#34;&gt;Fed swap lines remain successful&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the Global Financial Crisis (GFC), the Fed has maintained unlimited swap lines with the European Union, England, Japan, Canada, and Switzerland. On &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.federalreserve.gov/newsevents/pressreleases/monetary20200320a.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;March 23&lt;/a&gt;, it began offering daily, 7-day tenor swaps on these unlimited lines. This development came on the heels of a March 19 expansion of bilateral agreements detailed by a &lt;a href=&#34;https://som.yale.edu/blog/central-banks-use-swap-lines-to-maintain-the-flow-of-us-dollar?blog=111690&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;previous YPFS blogpost&lt;/a&gt;: the expanded facility would provide up to $60 billion for the banks of Australia, Brazil, South Korea, Mexico, Singapore, and Sweden, and up to $30 billion for the banks of Denmark, Norway, and New Zealand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During a dollar liquidity swap, the Fed enters into an agreement with another central bank that maintains an account at the Federal Reserve Bank of New York (FRBNY). The banks agree to perform two actions: first, the Fed’s dollars are exchanged for the foreign bank’s currency at the prevailing exchange rate; second, at some specified date in the near future, the foreign bank’s dollars are re-exchanged for their own currency at the same exchange rate as the original transaction, plus a small interest rate. The FRBNY is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.federalreserve.gov/monetarypolicy/files/FOMC_ForeignAuthorization.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;authorized&lt;/a&gt; by the Fed’s Open Market Committee under &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.federalreserve.gov/aboutthefed/section14.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Section 14&lt;/a&gt; of the Federal Reserve Act to establish swap lines, and has &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.federalreserve.gov/newsevents/pressreleases/swap-lines-faqs.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;emphasized&lt;/a&gt; the benefits to American households and businesses by ”helping to maintain the flow of credit to U.S. households and businesses by reducing risks to U.S. financial markets caused by financial stresses abroad.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the agreements peg both transactions to the same exchange rate, the Fed bears no risk that turmoil in foreign exchange markets translates to a loss of US dollars. Foreign central banks often use swap lines to get dollars that they can use to provide liquidity to domestic institutions in need of dollars. In 2007, the Fed lent money directly to US branches of European banks in addition to its heavy usage of the swap lines. The upshot of a liquidity swap was that, since the Fed’s swap was with the other central bank, it was not exposed to the risk of default by the downstream borrowing institutions; this risk was borne by the central bank, which determined who it would lend to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though financial strains among countries with standing dollar swap lines have thus far been much weaker than during the GFC, the rejuvenated lines were equally &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2020-06-19/central-banks-reduce-dollar-operations-as-market-stress-eases?sref=qZkWojPY&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;effective&lt;/a&gt; at quelling turbulent dollar funding markets. &lt;a href=&#34;https://fred.stlouisfed.org/series/DTWEXBGS&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Between March 6 and March 23&lt;/a&gt;, the US trade-weighted dollar index jumped to an historical high of 126.47, and posted its largest single-day percentage increase since the series was inaugurated in January 2006. With the acceleration of 7-day swaps on March 23, three days later the index subsequently posted its second largest drop since March 2009. It has not fluctuated by more than 1 point since April 7, though the index has remained higher and more volatile than recent, pre-pandemic levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;library(tidyverse) #plotting, data wrangling
library(lubridate) #dates

tradewt &amp;lt;- fredr(series_id = &amp;quot;DTWEXBGS&amp;quot;, units = &amp;quot;pch&amp;quot;) #retreive percent change in daily trade-weighted US dollar index using fredr
recessions &amp;lt;- read_csv(&amp;quot;start, end
2007-12-01, 2009-06-01
2020-02-01, NA&amp;quot;) #add recessions from https://fredhelp.stlouisfed.org/fred/data/understanding-the-data/recession-bars/
recessions[nrow(recessions), 2] &amp;lt;- Sys.Date() #update current recession with today&#39;s date

ggplot(tradewt) +
  geom_line(aes(date, value), color = &amp;quot;#286dc0&amp;quot;, show.legend = F) + #line plot of trade-weighted US dollar index
  geom_rect(data = mutate(filter(recessions, end &amp;gt;= min(tradewt$date)), #only include recessions ending after start of series
                          start = if_else(start &amp;lt; min(tradewt$date), min(tradewt$date), start)), #trim start of overhanging recession
            aes(xmin = start, xmax = end, ymin = -Inf, ymax = Inf), #define sides of rectangle
            fill = &amp;quot;#978d85&amp;quot;, #Yale shading color
            alpha = .33) + #opacity
  scale_x_date(expand = c(0,0), date_breaks = &amp;quot;2 years&amp;quot;, date_labels = &amp;quot;%Y&amp;quot;) +
  ggrepel::geom_label_repel(aes(date, value, label = datestring), data = mutate(slice_max(tradewt, order_by = abs(value), n = 6), datestring = format(date, &amp;quot;%b %d&amp;quot;)), min.segment.length = 0, label.padding = .1, segment.alpha = .6, show.legend = F, color = &amp;quot;#4a4a4a&amp;quot;) +
  labs(x = NULL, y = &amp;quot;Percent change&amp;quot;, title = &amp;quot;Daily change in trade-weighted US dollar index, 2006 - 2020&amp;quot;, subtitle = &amp;quot;Shaded areas indicate recessions, and six largest one-day swings are labeled&amp;quot;, caption = &amp;quot;Source: Federal Reserve Board of Governors&amp;quot;) +
  theme(plot.title = element_text(color = &amp;quot;#00356b&amp;quot;, vjust = -2), plot.subtitle = element_text(color = &amp;quot;#00356b&amp;quot;, vjust = -1), plot.caption = element_text(color = &amp;quot;#4a4a4a&amp;quot;), plot.margin = margin(r = 10),
        axis.title = element_text(color = &amp;quot;#222222&amp;quot;), axis.text = element_text(color = &amp;quot;#4a4a4a&amp;quot;), axis.ticks = element_line(color = &amp;quot;#222222&amp;quot;),
        panel.background = element_rect(fill = NA), panel.grid = element_line(color = &amp;quot;#dddddd&amp;quot;))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2020-07-01-reserve-liquidity-facilities-shift-from-advanced-economies-to-emerging-markets.en_files/figure-html/plot-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The speed and authority with which the Fed provides liquidity for the largest reserve currency market have &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ft.com/content/df9e34aa-9b5c-11ea-adb1-529f96d8a00b&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;bolstered&lt;/a&gt; the central bank’s reputation. This most recent resurgence of swap lines has led &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2020-03-31/fed-takes-on-role-of-world-s-central-bank-by-pumping-out-dollars?srnd=fixed-income&amp;amp;sref=qZkWojPY&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;some&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wsj.com/articles/the-fed-is-settling-into-its-role-as-the-worlds-central-bank-11585732095&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;assert&lt;/a&gt; that the Fed is not only a central bank to the US, but also to the world, offering short-term emergency liquidity when central banks &amp;ndash; liquid in their own currency &amp;ndash; are strapped for US dollars. As with domestic lender-of-last-resort operations, the transactions have always been initiated by a counterparty, never by the Fed. Although swap agreements are bilateral, the US &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.federalreserve.gov/regreform/reform-swaplines.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;has never drawn&lt;/a&gt; on a currency swap line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;focus-shifts-to-countries-with-weaker-reserves&#34;&gt;Focus shifts to countries with weaker reserves&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Fed’s deceleration of currency swaps prompted &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.economist.com/finance-and-economics/2020/06/20/the-successes-of-the-feds-dollar-swap-lines&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;praise&lt;/a&gt; for the speed and scale of relief. But the facility left unresolved the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ft.com/content/6882defd-bb7a-4732-a5de-a7a69886002d&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;plight&lt;/a&gt; of weaker, systemically less important currencies. Already burdened by higher interest rates on credit, countries without access to Fed swap lines saw a sharp uptick in the costs of accessing dollar funding markets, a Bank for International Settlements &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bis.org/publ/bisbull15.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; published in May found. Access to dollar funding has been exacerbated by capital outflows at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.iif.com/Portals/0/Files/content/2_IIF2020_April_CFR.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;rates higher than during the GFC&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an attempt to provide reserves for dollar-strapped reserve banks, the Fed and ECB have each established repurchasing (repo) facilities for their currencies. The facilities work similarly to currency swap lines, providing short term liquidity and protecting against credit risk by dealing only with central banks. However, these repo facilities lie one step closer to secured loans, requiring foreign central banks to post collateral should they default on loan repurchasing. To protect against exchange rate risk, eligible collateral consists only of sovereign securities denominated in the lender’s currency. For example, the Fed’s Foreign and International Monetary Authorities (FIMA) facility &amp;mdash; detailed in a previous YPFS &lt;a href=&#34;https://som.yale.edu/blog/fed-creates-dollar-repo-facility-for-central-banks-extending-liquidity-to-central-banks-that-don-t-have-fed-swap-lines&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;blogpost&lt;/a&gt; &amp;mdash; accepts US Treasury securities of any maturity, while the ECB’s EUREP accepts euro-denominated debt from any of its constituent states as well as the central bank itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These repo agreements allow foreign central banks to avoid dumping large amounts of sovereign bonds into &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.federalreserve.gov/newsevents/pressreleases/fima-repo-facility-faqs.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;illiquid markets&lt;/a&gt;, ensuring value for both the Fed and the foreign bank in need. But the facilities can be more limited than the swap lines due to shorter maturities and higher interest rates. The FIMA’s repo facility only offers overnight maturities. Though such maturities can be rolled over, the repo agreements contrast sharply in this regard with the swap lines, which offer up to 84-day maturities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, pricing is slightly steeper in FIMA and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ecb.europa.eu/press/pr/date/2020/html/ecb.pr200625_FAQ~8942d3d31d.en.pdf?470e666f74869ebb82847efce694bf7d&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;EUREP facilities&lt;/a&gt;. Where Fed central bank liquidity swaps add &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.davispolk.com/files/the_federal_reserves_actions_address_coronavirus_crisis.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;25 basis points to the overnight index swap (OIS), FIMA adds 25 basis points to the Interest Rate on Excess Reserves (IOER)&lt;/a&gt;. Currently the benchmark US overnight rate, the Federal Funds rate, stands at 0.05%, with the IOER at 0.10%. These prices potentially mean that liquidity will be cheaper for emerging markets than swap lines were for Singapore, which paid 1.09% for a &lt;a href=&#34;https://apps.newyorkfed.org/markets/autorates/fxswap&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;March&lt;/a&gt; swap, but more expensive than recent swaps with the Fed’s standing accounts, which have carried rates around 0.33%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ECB has yet to announce pricing for its facility, which will run until June 2021, but Turkey has been mentioned as a potential applicant. Bloomberg &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2020-06-25/ecb-sets-up-new-liquidity-facility-for-non-euro-central-banks?sref=qZkWojPY&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;reported&lt;/a&gt; that the nation had sought talks with the Group of 20 nations for its inclusion in bilateral swap agreements. For emerging markets, the International Monetary Fund has also been very active in approving emergency fund disbursement and stand-by facilities, and has introduced the new, “swap-like” &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.imf.org/en/About/Factsheets/Sheets/2020/04/17/short-term-liquidity-line&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Short-term Liquidity Line&lt;/a&gt;, and may be on track for support more given its &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cfr.org/blog/what-role-should-imf-play-responding-covid-19&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;still-large reserves&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Debt Mounts for US Retail and Lodging Mortgagors</title>
      <link>/2020/06/18/debt-mounts-for-us-retail-and-lodging-mortgagors/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2020/06/18/debt-mounts-for-us-retail-and-lodging-mortgagors/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This post was originally &lt;a href=&#34;https://som.yale.edu/blog/debt-mounts-for-us-retail-and-lodging-mortgagors&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;published&lt;/a&gt; on the YPFS Systemic Risk blog&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Government-mandated shutdowns in response to the novel coronavirus have triggered delinquencies among commercial mortgages as businesses struggle with revenue. The purpose of this article is to characterize the risks to US commercial real estate posed by COVID-19 responses. Due to reporting incentives, data on mortgages packaged into commercial mortgage-backed securities (CMBS) is more accessible and granular than data on the whole commercial mortgage market. Even though CMBS-associated properties constitute just &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.chicagobusiness.com/commercial-real-estate/another-likely-coronavirus-consequence-rising-landlord-defaults&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;20% of outstanding multifamily and commercial debt&lt;/a&gt;, the data generated by such properties can indicate how the whole commercial real estate sector may be affected. On June 4, commercial real estate research firm Trepp reported its largest jump in delinquencies among mortgages involved in the $1.4 trillion CMBS market, with the rate spiking from 2.29% to 7.15%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is real stress on commercial landlords. But that stress sits narrowly within the commercial market. The same Trepp report disaggregated delinquencies, noting nearly 20% of lodging, and more than 10% of retail mortgages were delinquent in May. Less than 4% of multifamily, office, and industrial mortgages were delinquent over the same period. Despite historically high unemployment, government stimulus supports have perhaps helped sustain rental payments. Publicly traded equity real estate investment trusts (REITs) invested in apartments &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.spglobal.com/marketintelligence/en/news-insights/latest-news-headlines/us-reit-rent-tracker-mall-reit-cbl-received-27-of-billed-april-cash-rent-58888411&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;collected&lt;/a&gt; at least 93% of rents in April, with most trusts collecting 95% or more. Meanwhile, offices continue to operate remotely, and warehousing has become more valuable as delivery services take on new importance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;retail-shows-signs-of-life&#34;&gt;Retail shows signs of life&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The speed at which consumers return to retail and lodging will factor importantly into the viability of mortgages in those sectors. The same data on publicly traded equity REITs reports rent collection figures for several owners of regional malls and shopping centers. Overall, between 50% and 65% of April rents were collected in shopping centers, while regional malls collected just 26% to 30% of rental payments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As states re-open, rent payments may increase quite quickly. In Arizona, Florida, Georgia, and Texas, as of June 2, retail foot traffic &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.adweek.com/retail/retail-foot-traffic-returning-states-reopening-shopping-data/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;had already surged&lt;/a&gt; from its April nadir, but only to 38-52% of 2019 levels. Retail nationwide &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.census.gov/retail/marts/www/marts_current.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;grew&lt;/a&gt; 17.7% in May, beginning to make up for sales contractions in March and April of 8.3% and 14.7% respectively. Further, the distribution of volume among types of businesses is unknown. The lockdowns have already caused the bankruptcy of JC Penney and Hertz, with AMC movie theaters currently being &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/06/09/business/coronavirus-amc-movie-theaters-reopening.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;threatened&lt;/a&gt;. But stock data indicates that investors believe retail real estate has already bottomed out. After crashing in late February, prices of several large &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fool.com/investing/2020/06/09/retail-reits-are-on-fire.aspx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;mall operators&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloomberg.com/quote/BBREIT:IND&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;REITs&lt;/a&gt; have stabilized and trended up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;library(tidyverse)
library(lubridate)

read_csv(&amp;quot;../../static/data/reit.csv&amp;quot;) %&amp;gt;%
  group_by(symbol) %&amp;gt;%
  mutate(adjusted = 100*adjusted/adjusted[date == min(date)]) %&amp;gt;%
  ungroup() %&amp;gt;%
  ggplot(aes(date, adjusted)) +
  geom_line(aes(col = symbol), show.legend = F) +
  stat_summary(fun = &amp;quot;mean&amp;quot;, color = &amp;quot;#286dc0&amp;quot;, size = 1, geom = &amp;quot;line&amp;quot;, show.legend = F) +
  scale_color_grey() +
  scale_x_date(expand = c(0,0)) +
  scale_y_continuous(limits = c(0, 110), expand = c(0, 1)) +
  labs(x = NULL, y = &amp;quot;Percent of Feb. 21 closing price&amp;quot;, title = &amp;quot;Price change of NYSE-listed REITs since first confirmed case&amp;quot;, subtitle = &amp;quot;Unweighted daily average in blue&amp;quot;, caption = &amp;quot;Source: Yahoo Finance&amp;quot;) +
  theme(plot.title = element_text(color = &amp;quot;#00356b&amp;quot;, vjust = -1.67), plot.subtitle = element_text(color = &amp;quot;#00356b&amp;quot;, vjust = -1), plot.caption = element_text(color = &amp;quot;#4a4a4a&amp;quot;),
        axis.title = element_text(color = &amp;quot;#222222&amp;quot;), axis.text = element_text(color = &amp;quot;#4a4a4a&amp;quot;), axis.ticks = element_line(color = &amp;quot;#222222&amp;quot;),
        panel.background = element_rect(fill = NA), panel.grid = element_line(color = &amp;quot;#dddddd&amp;quot;),
        legend.position = &amp;quot;bottom&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Warning: Removed 47 rows containing non-finite values (stat_summary).
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Warning: Removed 23 row(s) containing missing values (geom_path).
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2020-07-01-debt-mounts-for-us-retail-and-lodging-mortgagors.en_files/figure-html/reit_plot-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The market’s gradual recovery may have been informed by other indicators than the overall delinquency rate. Though 7.15% of securitized commercial mortgages were delinquent in May, 70% of those were only one month late. Trepp noted that a large number of mortgages remained in their 30-day grace period or actually reverted to current on their payments, though historically high delinquencies should still be expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite these expectations of recovery, the woes for commercial real estate may have just begun. Financial Times &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ft.com/content/b8eac068-e7c9-42ea-b9bf-6e2b4666f5c3&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;pointed&lt;/a&gt; to June as a crucial test for businesses, since debt two months late often triggers serious penalties. Moreover, data collected by the Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis since 1991 &lt;a href=&#34;https://fred.stlouisfed.org/series/DRCRELEXFACBS&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;show&lt;/a&gt; commercial delinquencies spiking as recessions end (Fig 2). Moreover, bond prices for CMBS exposed to lodging have tumbled. The same Financial Times article noted that BBB-rated tranches exposed to lodging shed approximately 40% of their value since early March. The asset specificity of hotels only lowers the value of real estate already faced with structural devaluation by services such as Airbnb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-r&#34;&gt;delin &amp;lt;- fredr(series_id = &amp;quot;DRCRELEXFACBS&amp;quot;) #retreive delinquency data using fredr
recessions &amp;lt;- read_csv(&amp;quot;start, end
1990-07-01, 1991-03-01
2001-03-01, 2001-11-01
2007-12-01, 2009-06-01
2020-02-01, NA&amp;quot;) #add recessions from https://fredhelp.stlouisfed.org/fred/data/understanding-the-data/recession-bars/
recessions[nrow(recessions), 2] &amp;lt;- Sys.Date() #update current recession with today&#39;s date

ggplot(delin) +
  geom_line(aes(date, value), color = &amp;quot;#286dc0&amp;quot;, show.legend = F) + #line plot of trade-weighted US dollar index
  geom_rect(data = mutate(filter(recessions, end &amp;gt;= min(delin$date), start &amp;lt;= max(delin$date)), #only include recessions ending after start of series and beginning before end of series
            start = if_else(start &amp;lt; min(delin$date), min(delin$date), start)), #trim start of overhanging recession
            aes(xmin = start, xmax = end, ymin = -Inf, ymax = Inf), #define sides of rectangle
            fill = &amp;quot;#978d85&amp;quot;, #Yale shading color
            alpha = .33) + #opacity
  scale_x_date(expand = c(0,0), date_breaks = &amp;quot;2 years&amp;quot;, date_labels = &amp;quot;%Y&amp;quot;) +
  scale_y_continuous(expand = c(0,0)) +
  labs(x = NULL, y = &amp;quot;Rate&amp;quot;, title = &amp;quot;Commercial delinquency rate, 1991Q1 - 2019Q4&amp;quot;, subtitle = &amp;quot;Shaded areas indicate recessions&amp;quot;, caption = &amp;quot;Source: Federal Reserve Board of Governors&amp;quot;) +
  theme(plot.title = element_text(color = &amp;quot;#00356b&amp;quot;, vjust = -2), plot.subtitle = element_text(color = &amp;quot;#00356b&amp;quot;, vjust = -1), plot.caption = element_text(color = &amp;quot;#4a4a4a&amp;quot;), plot.margin = margin(r = 10),
        axis.title = element_text(color = &amp;quot;#222222&amp;quot;), axis.text = element_text(color = &amp;quot;#4a4a4a&amp;quot;), axis.ticks = element_line(color = &amp;quot;#222222&amp;quot;),
        panel.background = element_rect(fill = NA), panel.grid = element_line(color = &amp;quot;#dddddd&amp;quot;))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2020-07-01-debt-mounts-for-us-retail-and-lodging-mortgagors.en_files/figure-html/delinquencies-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;support-for-commercial-real-estate-must-proceed-carefully&#34;&gt;Support for commercial real estate must proceed carefully&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Landlords and owners are navigating treacherous waters should commercial tenants require serious rent assistance. While CMBS loans tend to be non-recourse, it is &lt;a href=&#34;https://spcllp.com/nader-pakfar-risks-non-recourse-carveouts-cmbs-loans/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;standard practice&lt;/a&gt; for loans to feature “bad boy” covenants designed to guard against principal-agent risk. Such covenants provide recourse in the event that borrowers commit actions that (in normal times) are irresponsible. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.arentfox.com/perspectives/alerts/main-street-lending-programs-are-they-compatible-traditional-real-estate&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Real estate&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.maddinhauser.com/Law/DrawCases.aspx?CaseID=3881&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;attorneys&lt;/a&gt; point to two such actions in particular: significant rent renegotiation, and taking on senior indebtedness without investor consent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;US programs have thus far steered clear of these debt covenants, and offer viable channels should further support be authorized. The Payroll Protection Program (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sba.gov/funding-programs/loans/coronavirus-relief-options/paycheck-protection-program&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;PPP&lt;/a&gt;), offering forgivable and unsecured loans to businesses, recently expanded the amount that could be used for non-payroll expenses to 40%, opening the door to rent support. Borrowing terms for the three programs under the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.federalreserve.gov/monetarypolicy/mainstreetlending.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Main Street Lending Program&lt;/a&gt; have also &lt;a href=&#34;https://som.yale.edu/blog/federal-reserve-amends-main-street-lending-program&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;eased&lt;/a&gt;. The Priority and Extended lending facilities (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.federalreserve.gov/newsevents/pressreleases/files/monetary20200608a2.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;MSPLF&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.federalreserve.gov/newsevents/pressreleases/files/monetary20200608a3.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;MSELF&lt;/a&gt;, respectively) require loans to be secured, and prohibit subordination, but carve out exceptions for outstanding mortgage debts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that these programs appear to avoid the dangers posed by “bad boy” covenants, it seems likely that strained borrowers are equipped with the resources to secure credit lifelines to at least prolong defaults for several more months. On the other hand, it seems unlikely that the Federal Reserve (Fed) would engage private CMBS markets in a more direct fashion. Thus far only two Fed actions support private CMBS. In March it &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.federalreserve.gov/newsevents/pressreleases/monetary20200323a.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;included agency CMBS in its plan to make Open Market Desk purchases&lt;/a&gt; of $200 billion of MBS, and in April it expanded the eligible collateral for the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.federalreserve.gov/monetarypolicy/talf.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Term-Asset Securities Lending Facility&lt;/a&gt; to include AAA tranches of CMBS. A previous YPFS article &lt;a href=&#34;https://som.yale.edu/blog/fed-actions-help-agency-mreits-step-off-the-liquidity-roller-coaster&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;found&lt;/a&gt; that the Fed’s purchasing announcement had a positive effect on agency mortgage REITs (mREITs) while having only minimal effects on non-agency residential mortgage REITs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Equity REITs face different issues, principally those of eligibility and restrictions on usage. While property management companies are eligible for both PPP and MSLF loans, it is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jdsupra.com/legalnews/federal-reserve-further-expands-main-87251/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;unclear&lt;/a&gt; as to whether equity REITs are eligible. They may violate the Small Business Administration’s rules making ineligible for loans “&lt;a href=&#34;https://gov.ecfr.io/cgi-bin/text-idx?SID=fa53a93b56da0512f225f4fbcf044d0c&amp;amp;mc=true&amp;amp;node=se13.1.120_1110&amp;amp;rgn=div8&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;developers and landlords that” generally “do not actively use or occupy the assets acquired or improved with the loan proceeds.&lt;/a&gt;” However, equity REITs have applied for, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mycentraloregon.com/2020/04/29/luxury-hotels-real-estate-investment-trusts-benefited-from-ppp-loans/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;received&lt;/a&gt; PPP loans, potentially pushing this issue to the oversight bodies &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.brookings.edu/blog/fixgov/2020/04/15/congressional-oversight-of-the-cares-act-could-prove-troublesome/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;authorized&lt;/a&gt; by the CARES Act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the CARES Act prohibits the payment of dividends by corporations receiving support. While several programs have received blanket waivers from the Treasury Department, the Main Street Lending Facility &lt;a href=&#34;https://som.yale.edu/blog/federal-reserve-amends-main-street-lending-program&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;has not&lt;/a&gt;. The legal structure of REITs requires the payment of dividends, and many REITs have &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.barrons.com/articles/reit-investors-can-expect-dividends-to-be-paid-mostly-in-stock-51586091600&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;opted&lt;/a&gt; to pay mostly in stock. REIT trade associations have &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rer.org/docs/default-source/comment-letters/2020/4-22-20-main-street-lending-program-comment-letter.pdf?sfvrsn=671a0542_2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;already written&lt;/a&gt; to the Treasury Department requesting a waiver for this particular case, while the Internal Revenue Service has &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.bloombergtax.com/daily-tax-report/irs-loosens-requirements-on-reit-cash-to-promote-liquidity&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;reprised&lt;/a&gt; rules adopted during the Global Financial Crisis, allowing REITs to hold (and therefore distribute) less cash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The New York Times &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/06/05/business/economy/coronavirus-commercial-real-estate.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;highlighted&lt;/a&gt; name-brand tenants&amp;ndash;Gap, LVMH, Starbucks&amp;ndash;that had stopped paying rent and started renegotiating leases. The article noted that “the strongest tenants — those most able to pay — are driving the hardest for a discount.” When renters know that the options for landlords are either lease renegotiation or a total loss of income, those with the ability to pay may augment the demands of those that cannot pay, further pressuring landlords.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Deloitte &lt;a href=&#34;https://www2.deloitte.com/us/en/insights/economy/covid-19/covid-19-implications-for-commercial-real-estate-cre.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; noted that real estate development had flagged, with more than half of US construction firms surveyed halting projects. Social distancing rules precipitated decreased demand and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mercurynews.com/2020/04/04/coronavirus-delivers-first-blow-against-construction-economy-could-knock-it-out/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;disrupted&lt;/a&gt; construction sites. Commercial real estate’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reit.com/data-research/research/nareit-research/what-can-past-real-estate-construction-cycles-tell-us-about&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;sensitivity&lt;/a&gt; to economic downturns compounded the effects of decreased demand. The Deloitte report suggested that developers adapt rental properties to meet the needs of a changed society and strengthen resilience to future pandemics. The shock to brick-and-mortar businesses is likely to accelerate permanent transitions to online retail, work, and customer service across sectors. While several large &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theverge.com/facebook/2020/5/21/21265699/facebook-remote-work-shift-workforce-permanent-covid-19-mark-zuckerberg-interview&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;companies&lt;/a&gt; have started these transitions, they will &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2020-05-15/even-the-pandemic-can-t-kill-the-open-plan-office?sref=qZkWojPY&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;likely&lt;/a&gt; take several years to complete. Such a timeframe would flatten and spread the risks to commercial real estate finance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast, the greatest short-term risks posed by US commercial mortgages sit narrowly in lodging and retail, though high-turnover coworking spaces have already seen slashed revenues. CMBS-associated mortgages account for one fifth of outstanding commercial debt. While data are more widely and finely available for properties underlying CMBS loans, concerns similar to those discussed above exist with respect to non-securitized commercial mortgages. Where investors are exposed to lodging, prices have slumped, and questions abound regarding the sector&amp;rsquo;s long-term viability as nearly 20% of the CMBS-associated mortgages were reported delinquent in May. Retail activity is growing, but there is concern as to whether the recovery will be fast enough to stave off default in a sector with more than 10% of securitized mortgages in delinquency, which could hamper the real economy’s general pace of recovery.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Federal Reserve further expands access to Municipal Liquidity Facility</title>
      <link>/2020/06/09/federal-reserve-further-expands-access-to-municipal-liquidity-facility/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2020/06/09/federal-reserve-further-expands-access-to-municipal-liquidity-facility/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This post was originally &lt;a href=&#34;https://som.yale.edu/blog/federal-reserve-further-expands-access-to-municipal-liquidity-facility&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;published&lt;/a&gt; on the YPFS Systemic Risk blog&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On June 3, the Federal Reserve Board of Governors &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.federalreserve.gov/aboutthefed/boardvotes.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;unanimously approved&lt;/a&gt; a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.federalreserve.gov/newsevents/pressreleases/monetary20200603a.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;second expansion&lt;/a&gt; of eligibility under its Municipal Liquidity Facility (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.federalreserve.gov/monetarypolicy/muni.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;MLF&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Authorized by the CARES Act, the MLF can purchase up to $500 billion of newly-issued bonds from qualifying municipalities, using funds from the Fed and Treasury. Until this latest action, the MLF had restricted the eligibility of cities and counties based only on their population. The newest terms guarantee the eligibility of at least two political subdivisions and two revenue-bond issuers from each state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The expansion comes after the Fed &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2020-06-03/fed-expands-municipal-loan-program-to-include-smaller-borrowers&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;once again weathered criticism&lt;/a&gt; from state governors and representatives that the MLF’s eligibility criteria were too narrow. The original MLF criteria designated states, the District of Columbia, cities larger than one million residents, counties larger than two million residents, and one revenue-bond issuer (such as a utility or transit authority) per state as the only eligible recipients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In effect, the original term sheet ceded borrowing privileges to just &lt;a href=&#34;https://som.yale.edu/blog/federal-reserve-announces-new-municipal-liquidity-facility?blog=111690&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;10 cities and 16 counties&lt;/a&gt;. The Federal Reserve at the time said states could funnel the proceeds from bond sales to smaller cities and counties whose budgets had been strained by the effects of the novel coronavirus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this approach, while preserving the Fed’s historical distance from small borrowers, ran into several issues. For instance, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.politico.com/news/2020/04/23/fed-municipal-rescue-205831&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;some states lack the organizational infrastructure to lend to cities and counties&lt;/a&gt;. More importantly, several states face legal impediments to borrowing. Twenty-one &lt;a href=&#34;http://pewtrusts.org/~/media/assets/2017/06/sfh_strategies_for_managing_state_debt_final.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;states require referenda&lt;/a&gt; to issue debt at levels demanded by COVID-19 disruptions, while a &lt;a href=&#34;https://som.yale.edu/blog/barriers-to-access-impede-utilization-of-municipal-liquidity-facility&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;previous YPFS blogpost&lt;/a&gt; noted that several more states require legislative supermajorities to push through bond issuances. The current situation presents unique challenges to meeting such requirements, given that social distancing demands have closed many governing bodies and forestalled the possibilities of voting. In many cases, safe alternatives have not yet been designed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Members of Congress &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.shaheen.senate.gov/news/press/shaheen-urges-fed-to-fix-rules-that-block-city-county-governments-from-receiving-direct-covid-19-relief&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;criticized&lt;/a&gt; the Fed’s narrow interpretation of the CARES Act, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.congress.gov/bill/116th-congress/house-bill/748/text#HA1CEBDD35FD448DB9F77B49E23EADB58&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;which did not specify eligibility criteria&lt;/a&gt; for the MLF. The Fed’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://som.yale.edu/blog/federal-reserve-expands-eligibility-for-municipal-liquidity-facility&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;first expansion&lt;/a&gt; on April 27 extended the program from September 30 to December 31, and lowered the eligibility thresholds from 1 million residents per city and 2 million residents per county to 500,000 and 1 million,  respectively. As a result, the total number of eligible cities and counties increased from 26 to 227. However, even under the amended criteria, several states still lacked a single municipality that met the population threshold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The June 3 terms lowered the thresholds again to 250,000 residents per city and 500,000 residents per county. Should a state lack one or two municipalities that meet these thresholds, governors may designate one or two of the largest ineligible cities or counties. Governors may also designate two non-governing entities that currently issue bonds secured by government revenue. Additionally, multi-state revenue-bond issuers, such as the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey and the Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority, are now also eligible issuers, provided that minimum credit rating thresholds are met.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Fed has not changed the original terms regarding the MLF’s size, and eligible uses of funds. The facility is authorized to purchase up to $500 billion in eligible bonds (allocated among the states as &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.newyorkfed.org/medialibrary/media/markets/municipal-liquidity-facility-eligible-issuers&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;proportions of FY2017 general revenue&lt;/a&gt;), and is backstopped by an equity investment of $35 billion from the Treasury’s Exchange Stabilization Fund, as authorized by the CARES Act. The facility takes the form of a special purpose vehicle (SPV) established by the Fed under Section 13(3) of the Federal Reserve Act. The facility may purchase “&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.federalreserve.gov/newsevents/pressreleases/files/monetary20200603a1.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;tax anticipation notes (TANs), tax and revenue anticipation notes (TRANs), bond anticipation notes (BANs), revenue anticipation notes (RANs),&lt;/a&gt;” and similar bonds with maturities no longer than 36 months, funding up to 20% of a state, county, city, or revenue-bond issuer’s revenue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Small cities are particularly sensitive to economic shocks due to their dependence on sales tax. Brookings &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.brookings.edu/blog/the-avenue/2020/03/31/when-will-your-city-feel-https://www.brookings.edu/blog/the-avenue/2020/03/31/when-will-your-city-feel-the-fiscal-impact-of-covid-19/the-fiscal-impact-of-covid-19/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;reported&lt;/a&gt; that cities in the Midwest, generally smaller than those in the dense East and heavily urbanized West, rely more on sales taxes. Whereas property values are assessed not more than once a year, and income taxes are filed annually, sales tax receipts enter municipal finances at frequencies varying between once a month and once a year. These higher-frequency collections mean that shocks affect sales tax revenues much more quickly than other types of taxes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compounding pressure on the MLF to purchase small-city debt are high-population thresholds and use restrictions on CARES Act grants. Under the Coronavirus Relief Fund, only municipalities with 500,000 residents or more are &lt;a href=&#34;https://home.treasury.gov/system/files/136/Census-Data-and-Methodology-Final.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;eligible&lt;/a&gt; and funds may only be used for &lt;a href=&#34;https://home.treasury.gov/system/files/136/Coronavirus-Relief-Fund-Guidance-for-State-Territorial-Local-and-Tribal-Governments.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;necessary and unexpected expenditures&lt;/a&gt; demanded by COVID-19. Thus, monies cannot be used to compensate for reduced sales tax receipts, a use that is permissable for proceeds from MLF bond purchases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MLF marks &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.politico.com/news/2020/04/09/fed-to-buy-municipal-debt-178222&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;the first time&lt;/a&gt; the Federal Reserve has waded into direct purchases of municipal bonds. In 2011, in the wake of the Global Financial Crisis, Republicans in both chambers &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wsj.com/articles/SB10001424052748704739504576067602380461160&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;balked&lt;/a&gt; at suggestions from Democrats that the federal government bail out municipalities. The then-Chair of the Federal Reserve, Ben Bernanke, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.govinfo.gov/content/pkg/CHRG-112shrg68184/html/CHRG-112shrg68184.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;said&lt;/a&gt; that the Fed had “no expectation or intention to get involved in state and local finance.” The Fed’s legal authority to buy municipal bonds extended to only 2% of the market, and Bernanke noted that there might be other legal restrictions under the Dodd-Frank Act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, in spite of the Fed’s historic distance from municipal debt, the efficacy of the MLF may lead to deeper involvement in municipal finances. The initial announcement of the MLF in April immediately stabilized a $4 trillion market that saw AAA yields &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ft.com/content/e2d20041-0d86-4dea-8016-d1cfcc01f4c0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;jump from just under 1% to just under 3% in a matter of days&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Politico &lt;a href=&#34;https://nam05.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fsubscriber.politicopro.com%2Fdatapoint%2F2020%2F05%2Fpro-analysis-what-you-need-to-know-about-the-municipal-bond-market-101286&amp;amp;data=02%7C01%7Ccorey.runkel%40yale.edu%7Cfcd2daef45404ac856f708d80bade8a3%7Cdd8cbebb21394df8b4114e3e87abeb5c%7C0%7C0%7C637272188841278572&amp;amp;sdata=QLHhjyolYQ3O%2F9SU2ZQfZXgHOnyneICd%2Bjfgje5R7uI%3D&amp;amp;reserved=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;pointed&lt;/a&gt; to House Ways &amp;amp; Means Chair Richard Neal as a catalyst for more intervention in munis. Even before the novel coronavirus, the former mayor of Springfield, Massachusetts, had established himself as a supporter of municipal bonds. However, aid may instead come from traditional fiscal policy routes should the Fed hold firm on its new eligibility thresholds. Neal represents Springfield and its enclosing county Hampden, each of which just miss these newest MLF population thresholds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus far, Illinois is the only state to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ft.com/content/5393bdc7-02a2-4ec7-81c3-4d6088216a6c&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;announce&lt;/a&gt; its participation in the MLF, issuing $1.2 billion in 12-month maturities at 3.82%.The MLF became operational on May 26.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
