<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blog | Corey Runkel</title>
    <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://runkelcorey.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Blog</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Corey N. Runkel 2019</copyright>
    <image>
      <url>https://runkelcorey.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Blog</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Distortion in Vertigo (1958)</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2019/08/27/vertigo-1958/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2019/08/27/vertigo-1958/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Alfred Hitchcock&amp;rsquo;s golden decade began in 1954 with &lt;em&gt;Dial M for Murder&lt;/em&gt;, and ended with &lt;em&gt;The Birds&lt;/em&gt; in 1963. The intervening years saw the Brit direct almost all of the films for which he is so well remembered today, including &lt;em&gt;Rear Window&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;To Catch a Thief&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;North by Northwest&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Psycho&lt;/em&gt;. 1958&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt;, however, has long been considered the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AFI%27s_100_Years...100_Movies#List&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;absolute&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.com/news/entertainment-arts-19078948&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;maximum&lt;/a&gt; of Hitchcock&amp;rsquo;s directorial function. I subjected myself to the movie at least three different times to understand its value among critics, but it is a seriously difficult film to approach: the film splits into two parts with the death of James Stewart&amp;rsquo;s love interest (Kim Novak), a woman whose doppelgänger (also portrayed by Novak) shows her face in the second half; the casting of James Stewart&amp;mdash;with lead roles in &lt;em&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a Wonderful Life&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Mr. Smith Goes to Washington&lt;/em&gt;&amp;mdash;in lieu of transatlantic Hitchcock favorite Cary Grant, reads as an intentional subversion of 1950s Americana; and the director&amp;rsquo;s artistic relationship with blonde women has colored the film a million shades by a million viewers. It was not until I had watched some of &lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rsquo;s descendants, notably David Lynch&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Mulholland Drive&lt;/em&gt; that I felt the impact for which I had longed upon re-watching the film this summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hitchcock&amp;rsquo;s cinematographic style change with each movie he makes, unlike the storybook qualities of Wes Anderson or the placid &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/quotes/665415-drops-dripped-quiet-talk-went-on-horses-neighed-and-scuffled&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Drops dripped.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; of Andrei Tarkovsky. In &lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt;, he leads us into James Stewart&amp;rsquo;s distorted mind, a world shattered by the traumatic death of his police force&amp;ndash;partner, by constricting our range of movement and mocking our spatial judgment. The partner falls from a San Francisco tenement while trying to save James Stewart, and suddenly, like Kim Novak&amp;rsquo;s character in double, Stewart&amp;rsquo;s steps into another&amp;rsquo;s life. This life is more traumatically metaphorical and very much less literal than that of Kim Novak&amp;rsquo;s character, but another life nonetheless. The fall and the height and the guilt confuse themselves in Stewart&amp;rsquo;s head to deliver him a crippling case of Vertigo, forcing him from the force for good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stewart&amp;rsquo;s friend exacerbates this confusion by sending him to surveil the friend&amp;rsquo;s wife, Novak&amp;rsquo;s original character. Such a clandestine project leads Stewart through the winding streets and seemingly circular history of San Francisco, where his friend&amp;rsquo;s wife has taken to emulating a crazed ancestor&amp;rsquo;s appearance. At this point, Hitchcock begins to insert &lt;a href=&#34;https://vignette.wikia.nocookie.net/filmguide/images/1/18/5853.jpg/revision/latest?cb=20120413043431&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;spiral&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://i1.wp.com/www.abelardomorell.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/2017_Flowers-For-Lisa-76-After-Hitchcock%E2%80%99s-Vertigo-2017-copy-1.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;patterns&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://ludditerobot.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/08/Hitchcock-Vertigo-spiral.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;everywhere&lt;/a&gt;. This pattern symbolizes the deepening plot, deepening conspiracy&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:Remember-Hitchco&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:Remember-Hitchco&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and deepening psychotic hole that Stewart finds his character in. The symbolism is patent, however, contrasting with other imagery employed by the director (imagery which would find amplification in what Lynch described as &amp;ldquo;dream logic&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alfred Hitchcock&amp;rsquo;s cinematographical trickery encloses James Stewart&amp;rsquo;s all-American character, disclosing the craze lurking inside his obsessed mind. With deep focus and a 2-D plane, cameras make the near and far appear unified. The video below&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:Massive-apologie&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:Massive-apologie&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; demonstrates this several times. The whole video is a smörgåsbord of labyrinths, San Francisco history, and voyeurism, but turn the clock to 1:59 to see the images I can&amp;rsquo;t remove from my head.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/bDwPJ5IaJ2g&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Those yellow flowers that James Stewart walks behind appear taller than him in that moment, and the obscured view traps his figure in the history, mystery, and death that linger after Novak exits the scene. Hitchcock further unsettles viewers in :17, not with the normal technique of a dolly following Stewart and suggesting danger, but by a shot from below. This camera setting exaggerates the heights and lengths of objects outside focal point, making the 3ft flowers equal the 6ft Stewart in height. But the mastery here is the unresolved tension between these instances of camera trickery and Hitchcock&amp;rsquo;s usage of truly large objects. The enormity of the Golden Gate bridge in &lt;a href=&#34;https://i.ytimg.com/vi/ih-KeOf3xQQ/maxresdefault.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;one famous shot&lt;/a&gt; anchors the nearly surreal imagery elsewhere in &lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt;, cementing a permanent unease throughout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:Remember-Hitchco&#34;&gt;Remember Hitchcock overlaps with noir films, from which he pulls much of his plot devices and motifs. &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:Remember-Hitchco&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:Massive-apologie&#34;&gt;Massive apologies for the aspect ratio, look for higher quality clips to see how wide the film really looks. &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:Massive-apologie&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Federal Register API</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2019/08/03/federal-register-api/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2019/08/03/federal-register-api/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tl-dr&#34;&gt;TL;DR&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I created an &lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt; client to fetch data from the Federal Register, replacing an R package that had not been updated for years. It was my first foray into APIs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United States &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.federalregister.gov/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Federal Register&lt;/a&gt; is the [slowly] clearing house for every revision to US administrative law, regulatory enforcement, and the more stupid forms of jockeying and horn-tooting by federal agencies. The website, charged with the supremely bureaucratic duty of pigeonholing and circumscribing every sort of &amp;lt;&lt;event&gt;&amp;gt; in Washington, is quite beautiful. Its ease, features, and appearance bear the marks of something that is truly for the public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To aid readers, [and the odd corporation trying to stay a step ahead of environmental regulations,] the Office of the Federal Register got a leg up from a developer who made an API client for R. Unfortunately,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:And-quite-ironic&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:And-quite-ironic&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that client has been rendered useless by updates. In the name of openness digital and governmental, I set to work on a new API client that would:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;teach me the fundamentals of APIs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;display some clever solutions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:And-quite-ironic&#34;&gt;And quite ironically for an institution with steeped in such bureaucracy. &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:And-quite-ironic&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
