<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>culture | Corey Runkel</title>
    <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/tags/culture/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://runkelcorey.github.io/tags/culture/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>culture</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© C.N. Runkel 2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://runkelcorey.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>culture</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/tags/culture/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>American Heartbreak</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2019/11/21/american-heartbreak/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2019/11/21/american-heartbreak/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am the American heartbreak–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rock on which Freedom&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stumped its toe–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The great mistake&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That Jamestown made&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Long ago&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;— Langston Hughes
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever I try to recall this poem, I search for &amp;ldquo;Plymouth Rock poem&amp;rdquo;, and freak out beacuse I can&amp;rsquo;t find it for a few seconds. This is because, all along, Hughes alludes to the founding of our nation without ever saying so. He points to our founding virtue, Freedom, and asks the reader to define it&amp;mdash;suddenly&amp;mdash;in their head. This question calls up our national myth, of virile men casting off the oppressive British yoke, which implants in Americans a desire for revolution and newness and independence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find this desire each time I encounter American colonial history. There is the Massachusetts Bay colonizers, and the Virginia Company of London, more than anything else I want to race forward to 1776. American history teaching defaults to setting our cast of characters on the North American continent in order to reach revolution, with that noble end somehow justifying everything that came before (if not ethically, then morally: we suffered, and thus &lt;em&gt;deserve&lt;/em&gt; Freedom). In the same way, the outposts of our frontiersmen and women served to legitimize the murder of indigenous people, conquest of Mexican territory, and deaths of our own colonizers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this myth may be just that, it is a powerful story that is consistently told. Hughes rides its momentum, immediately clipping America&amp;rsquo;s great strides towards Freedom with the realities of chattel slavery. Nothing could be further from Freedom. But Hughes is acknowledging the promise of Freedom: one&amp;rsquo;s heart can&amp;rsquo;t break if it doesn&amp;rsquo;t first beat. By acknowledging the promise along with its failure, Hughes ties this heartbreak inextricably to our nation&amp;rsquo;s founding. This is &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; American heartbreak, bound up with the 400-year history of democracy in Jamestown. Hughes pulls us&amp;mdash;with present tense, with reference to Jamestown, by describing something so hard, so immovable, so central to that other early colony&amp;mdash;into the contradiction hidden in our nation&amp;rsquo;s founding, and still so hidden today.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Aspirational Efficiency</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2019/11/07/aspirational-efficiency/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2019/11/07/aspirational-efficiency/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The easiest way to derail any work that I am doing is by linking to an article ranking and comparing things that will help me live a better life. That article might rank the 10 best productivity apps, it may uncover new services which partition and categorize every second of my day, or&amp;mdash;as it did yesterday&amp;mdash;it could offer me a phone that can satisfy my needs immediately, stripping my day of wasted time. The only certainty is that I, in my manifold time management skills, will click on that link.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought this was a phenomenon entirely local to myself until I saw this &lt;a href=&#34;https://aeon.co/essays/how-did-being-happy-become-a-matter-of-relentless-competitive-work&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; from Aeon, noting that life management has become a juggernaut in consumer retail, with &amp;ldquo;self-care and anti-stress products now rounding out the bestseller list on Amazon&amp;rdquo;. We&amp;rsquo;ve reined in other animals, organizations of people, and our bodies by calibrating each measurable parameter, so why not do the same for our minds? Unfortunately, we don&amp;rsquo;t seem quite as pliant as the optimization equations imply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This logic, made inexorable by limitless access to information, tugs at our happiness. Behind whatever tool or activity or person present before us lurks an alternative, a next-best option. This idea has driven every rationalist attempt at decision making, but its actual calculus has changed considerably since the 1990s. Before then, catalogued libraries and television delivered then-unprecedented access to information. The task of research had become immediately more accessible, but also less clear. Suddenly, more and more causes sprang up to explain each effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The move from card catalogues and TV to Wikipedia and on-demand streaming was a leap in this dimension. Different from past moves was the sheer scale of new information. The closest comparison to make would likely be the telegram that could relay news around the world in minutes, but that did not solve the last-mile problem that our phones and computers did. Similar to past moves is the growing illusion of choice. Most definitions model illusory choice as a free decision between a constrained set of options, like choosing from a soda machine that offers a dozen brands but where every choice is a Coca-Cola product. But rather than onstrained options, I interpret illusory choice as constrained decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our brain budgets time and resources based on prior neurological sequences, updating expectations with each iteration. While we may understand how normal it is not to find an exhaustive cost-benefits comparison of the more than 2,000 results for &amp;ldquo;thimble&amp;rdquo; on Amazon, our brains may not. Our expectations have been conditioned by the norms of evidence-based administration to treat anything less than exhaustive comparisons as failure. This extends to our lives, where exhaustive comparison has meant nothing less than exhaustion. Where once, exhaustive comparisons meant eyeballing dozens, now it means eyeballing hundreds, thousands, or millions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our internal search processes can&amp;rsquo;t handle such scale. While they have gradually widened, the velocity of extension by the market has effectively capped the rate at which we had to develop non-exhaustive ways to search. When the village had a single cobbler, shoes were a constant, not a variable to optimize over. Still, when there are ten types of black beans at the grocery store, they can be compared quite readily. But when it&amp;rsquo;s always possible to opt for peer-to-peer sellers in Kolkata over the ~local~ Walmart, people are given the room every day to exhaust their critical thinking skills trying to gauge the expected payoffs of a hundred options, and a million more they know to be lurking, accessible to anyone with the right search terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our minds haven&amp;rsquo;t caught up yet. They can take on waves of epic proportions, but a tide that lifts them high enough to see the world&amp;rsquo;s ginormity will overwhelm. I see two ways out: time and pragmatism. The first just says that after enough time passes, our minds will adjust, will think in different ways to approach this different problem. But that option offers only consolation to people currently. Option two offers that different way. Construct in your mind a noble lie, something appealing but fanciful. Then, believe in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adhering to a set of values fixes those variables as constants. This is Marie Kondo for your mind, with the tiny caveat that beliefs weigh far more than shower organizers, dressers, or homes. The values chosen don&amp;rsquo;t have to conform to Marie Kondo&amp;ndash;like advice. In fact, choosing something already at tension with what FastCompany promises are the best ways to increase productivity is probably best. It&amp;rsquo;s good training for the future. Rather, pick values that will let you do the most of your wants, your in-the-moment pleasures. Do not conflate &amp;lsquo;do the most&amp;rsquo; with &amp;lsquo;most choices&amp;rsquo;. To do the most, you need clear boundaries that, if crossed, bind you to decisions, decisions that you could theoretically even come to regret, but decisions that you need to make. Pragmatism means believing what needs to be believed, even if it can&amp;rsquo;t stand up to rationalist inquiry.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
