<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>america | Corey Runkel</title>
    <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/tags/america/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://runkelcorey.github.io/tags/america/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>america</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© C.N. Runkel 2021</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://runkelcorey.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>america</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/tags/america/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>David Lynch is Toying With Us</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2020/02/15/david-lynch-is-toying-with-us/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2020/02/15/david-lynch-is-toying-with-us/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I write this post while watching &lt;em&gt;Rabbits&lt;/em&gt;, a work of exceptional mystery but unexceptional tension.
Lynch casts two regulars&amp;mdash;Laura Harring and Naomi Watts&amp;mdash;opposite one newbie&amp;mdash;Scott Coffey&amp;mdash;as man-sized rabbits in what appears to be the &lt;em&gt;Blue Velvet&lt;/em&gt; apartment set.
These short films, available &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLSSx9jvH6luUPl-bqfqaJ8z8vHDqlu5ji&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;on YouTube&lt;/a&gt;, trip over several of Lynch&amp;rsquo;s signature aspects: characters sing haunting songs; mundane life is treated as a social experiment; and Angelo Baldametti&amp;rsquo;s synthesizers underscore everything.
&lt;em&gt;Rabbits&lt;/em&gt; insists that we examine our own tastes and be comfortable with those answers (and inevitably unanswered questions).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though it offers no plot or characters that could create tension in a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=j56WPBaiPYQ&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;conventional story structure&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Rabbits&lt;/em&gt; is seriously intriguing, and hints at larger, unobserved meanings.
This intrigue is not uncommon; in fact, my theory of late has been that Lynch understands that his viewers feel the hints and the suggestions at something grander, his films all metaphysical McGuffins.
In his films, characters do not look at one another&amp;mdash;they see, in flashy close-ups, the uncertain eyes of the other.
Leading women are never conventionally pretty&amp;mdash;they are fantastically upbeat and implausibly platinum, hysterical results of Hollywood insecure appeal to men&amp;rsquo;s wallets.
Cars do not traverse from point to point&amp;mdash;headlights sprint over dark, twisting roadways.
These are cinematic clichés, style that heightens substance when it is used eagerly and genuinely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2013/04/18/lynchrabbits1024_wide-81b3911888e86e687da1a0370b19cc026967ef0d.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Set of *Rabbits*. The camera moves from this fixed position exactly once to zoom in on the telephone.&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is nothing substantive about &lt;em&gt;Rabbits&lt;/em&gt;: Lynch&amp;rsquo;s mastery over cinematic cliché is taken to the brink, and over.
In many Lynch films since &lt;em&gt;Blue Velvet&lt;/em&gt;, characters utter non-sequiters in total deadpan; but in &lt;em&gt;Rabbits&lt;/em&gt;, they utter nothing but non-sequiters, with no story to speak of!
This Baldametti score then adds style to substanceless grunts, sounds English speakers will recognize as words but not as meaningful sentences.
And with some serious hilarity, Lynch adds a sitcom applause over the entrances of each character into this one-room apartment and laughtracks after sentences like &amp;ldquo;It is 7pm&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;I almost forgot.&amp;rdquo;
These outbursts, audio cues to at-home viewers that Important or Funny happenings are taking place, mock TV shows like the &lt;em&gt;Big Bang Theory&lt;/em&gt;, whose live audiences treat academic jargon and references to comic books as the basis for side-splitting guffaws.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The distance between the intelligibility of plot in &lt;em&gt;Rabbits&lt;/em&gt; and the connotations of its audio cues emphasize the contingency of language and the ability of convention to invent meaning from nothing.
It is indisputable that Baldametti&amp;rsquo;s score is ominous, alerting viewers that Something Is Happening, or that audience laughter is comedic, alerting viewers that a Joke Is Occurring.
But simply because a connotation is indisputable does not make it true.
None would dispute the scores ominousness or the audiences laughter because the years of TV and film that we have watch have taught us to connect certain sounds to certain moments.
The work starts with children&amp;rsquo;s tales, where morality is stark and the audio cues used to reinforce a grand, unified message.
By grounding these otherwise unintelligible cues in extra-cinematic morality or realistic emotions, we learn to couple low, industrial sounds with alertness, and human laughter with comedy.
&lt;em&gt;Rabbits&lt;/em&gt; attempts to elicit those emotions by only employing the signifier, while ditching the plot points signified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.ytimg.com/vi/NiOx5yJx-jc/maxresdefault.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The *Persona*-like dream sequences. Nothing says for sure these rabbits sleep, but shifts in color and a demonic face that hovers in the upper left-hand corner match dream sequences in Lynch&#39;s other films.&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps one can argue that the words which immediately precede and follow the &lt;em&gt;Persona&lt;/em&gt;-like interpolated dream sequences are Important, but I am not convinced.
I propose that &lt;em&gt;Rabbits&lt;/em&gt; is David Lynch toying with us.
He wants to know if he can make pure entertainment, works without useful or familiar stories, but which nonetheless strap us into rollercoasters of joy, despair, nostalgia, and humor.
In his other works, this plays out seamlessly.
I (the viewer) achingly try to pin down the plot, and then the meaning of the narrative he created.
This process feels possible, but always out-of-reach in his other works, which ditch the rabbit heads and opt for sequences of dialog that I recognize as events and narrative momentum.
But in &lt;em&gt;Rabbits&lt;/em&gt;, the dissonance between signifier and signified makes the effect clear.
In &lt;em&gt;Rabbits&lt;/em&gt;, the laughter and music become parodic, pointing at the fact that in &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; language, cinematic or otherwise, our grunts are intelligible for no reasons other than Pavolvian repitition and the magic fizz of neurons.
Language is contingent, subject to chance mutation and adoption, and not subject to deep structures or extra-personal validity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>American Heartbreak</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2019/11/21/american-heartbreak/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2019/11/21/american-heartbreak/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am the American heartbreak–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rock on which Freedom&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stumped its toe–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The great mistake&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That Jamestown made&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Long ago&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;— Langston Hughes
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever I try to recall this poem, I search for &amp;ldquo;Plymouth Rock poem&amp;rdquo;, and freak out beacuse I can&amp;rsquo;t find it for a few seconds. This is because, all along, Hughes alludes to the founding of our nation without ever saying so. He points to our founding virtue, Freedom, and asks the reader to define it&amp;mdash;suddenly&amp;mdash;in their head. This question calls up our national myth, of virile men casting off the oppressive British yoke, which implants in Americans a desire for revolution and newness and independence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find this desire each time I encounter American colonial history. There is the Massachusetts Bay colonizers, and the Virginia Company of London, more than anything else I want to race forward to 1776. American history teaching defaults to setting our cast of characters on the North American continent in order to reach revolution, with that noble end somehow justifying everything that came before (if not ethically, then morally: we suffered, and thus &lt;em&gt;deserve&lt;/em&gt; Freedom). In the same way, the outposts of our frontiersmen and women served to legitimize the murder of indigenous people, conquest of Mexican territory, and deaths of our own colonizers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this myth may be just that, it is a powerful story that is consistently told. Hughes rides its momentum, immediately clipping America&amp;rsquo;s great strides towards Freedom with the realities of chattel slavery. Nothing could be further from Freedom. But Hughes is acknowledging the promise of Freedom: one&amp;rsquo;s heart can&amp;rsquo;t break if it doesn&amp;rsquo;t first beat. By acknowledging the promise along with its failure, Hughes ties this heartbreak inextricably to our nation&amp;rsquo;s founding. This is &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; American heartbreak, bound up with the 400-year history of democracy in Jamestown. Hughes pulls us&amp;mdash;with present tense, with reference to Jamestown, by describing something so hard, so immovable, so central to that other early colony&amp;mdash;into the contradiction hidden in our nation&amp;rsquo;s founding, and still so hidden today.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
