<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>america | Corey Runkel</title>
    <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/tags/america/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://runkelcorey.github.io/tags/america/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>america</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© C.N. Runkel 2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://runkelcorey.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>america</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/tags/america/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>In Vertigo (1958), an Uncertain History</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2020/07/30/in-vertigo-an-uncertain-history/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2020/07/30/in-vertigo-an-uncertain-history/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.historyguide.org/europe/valery.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;We see now that the abyss of history is deep enough to hold us all.&lt;/a&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt; places a thoroughly modern Scottie Ferguson&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:Jimmy-Stewart&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:Jimmy-Stewart&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; within a thoroughly modern San Francisco.
It then watches as he slips from his mental moorings into a twisted version of himself.
His cycle of psychological terror constitutes a violent &lt;em&gt;displacement&lt;/em&gt;, and it re-opens two key questions of belonging: of Scottie to San Francisco; and of San Francisco to Scottie.
I will examine only the former today; the latter I leave for later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My argument runs like this:
&lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rsquo;s early scenes depict a San Francisco that is tailored to mobile white men like Scottie.
For his part, Scottie enforced the modern status quo as a San Francisco cop, until his partner died trying to save Scottie from falling during a rooftop chase.
With the danger supposedly over, he finds himself navigating a comfortable and controlled city, with sights/sites located just off the highway&amp;mdash;Fort XX, the Muir Woods, and the Mission San Juan Bautista.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But these parks did not just happen.
Public works efforts had to make the sites palettable to professionals and tourists.
These efforts had to isolate the visual cues of danger from any actual, Wild West&amp;ndash;type danger.
Rather than places to be reckoned with, these are sights to be gawked at.
In the first formulation, the site&amp;mdash;with all its natural and political forces&amp;mdash;participates with those who visit it; in the second, only the visitor is active, while the sight is frozen in space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt; exposes how thin this veneer of safety is.
Between Madeleine&amp;rsquo;s actions and Scottie&amp;rsquo;s vertigo, the film reintroduces the distinct possibilities of danger to these places.
In doing so, it unsettles the stable relationship between Scottie the subject and San Francisco the object.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I contend that a stable subject-object relationship is necessary to Scottie&amp;rsquo;s sense of place; as evidence, I look to his meeting with Gavin Elster.
#Elster meeting exposes Scottie&amp;rsquo;s desires
##Scottie kind of had this with the police force, but he has been neutered and immobilized (the placement)
##Also exposes what SF lacks
#He likes going to these &amp;ldquo;old places&amp;rdquo; b/c he feels powerful and free there, his very life in defiance of the tall trees, colonial forces, and rough seas
##these parks serve as reminders of the passage of time, but they are as much participants in it
##so, unbeknownst to Scottie, the parks lost their oldness. Therefore, the power he feels is invalid
#Madeleine exposes real danger
##This unsettles the relationship, because he now feels the danger
##this change makes it such that he can confuse now with the past
##this flattening of history disorients scottie&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a private reading of &lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt;.
To&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By disrupting the normal order of things, &lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt; thus undermines our () grip of America over San Francisco, and, in doing so, its narrative of progress.
This disruption contributes to a &amp;ldquo;weakening of historicity, both in our relationship to public History and in the new forms of our private temporality&amp;rdquo;.^[Frederic Jameson, &lt;a href=&#34;https://web.archive.org/web/20110806060217/http://homepage.newschool.edu/~quigleyt/vcs/jameson/jameson.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Cultural Logic of Late Capitalism&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Here &amp;lsquo;historcity&amp;rsquo; is that sense that things have changed somehow in our social relations.
By exposing progress as a veneer, Hitchock traps us in a spiral that mirrors Scottie Ferguson&amp;rsquo;s own difficulty escaping his traumatic past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;establishing-a-modern-city-via-the-american-sublime&#34;&gt;Establishing a modern city via the American sublime&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(the flâneur, Gavin Elster)? american tech sublime and the double action&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;disrupting-the-illusion-of-safety&#34;&gt;Disrupting the illusion of safety&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Definitely something here about the fragility of the sublime
Madeleine puncturing the visual membrane of the sublime&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sublime, rather than an instrument which rattles people from their parochial understandings of history to glean a new future, turns them toward a never-ending past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt; is often viewed as the modernist movie. Here instead it is an early example of postmodernism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of &lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rsquo;s lasting images star San Francisco as much as they do Jimmy Stewart or Kim Novak.
Consider for example the massive pylons supporting the Golden Gate Bridge, the looming trunks of Muir Woods, or the towering figure cut by the Mission San Juan Bautista.
These are objects so huge that Hitchcock&amp;rsquo;s camera cannot swallow them entirely, their vastness bleeding over the frame&amp;rsquo;s edges.
And each of them repeat vertical features&amp;mdash;the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_orange#Golden_Gate_Bridge&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;International Orange&lt;/a&gt; suspension cables, endless &lt;em&gt;Sequoia sempervirens&lt;/em&gt;, late-afternoon shadows cast by pale white arches&amp;mdash;that recede into the distance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Succession and uniformity of parts are what constitute the artificial infinite&amp;rdquo; wrote Edmund Burke in &lt;em&gt;A Philosophical Enquiry Into the Origin of Our Ideas of the Sublime and Beautiful&lt;/em&gt;, one of the first modern explorations of the sublime.
He described the sublime as a state when &amp;ldquo;the mind is so entirely filled with its object, that it cannot entertain any other,&amp;rdquo; inciting terror and astonishment at its heights, while &amp;ldquo;the inferior effects are admiration, reverence and respect.&amp;rdquo;
The treatment Hitchcock gives to San Francisco&amp;rsquo;s iconic sights meets Burke&amp;rsquo;s standard.
But what purpose does this treatment serve? How does the voyeurism of Hitchcock&amp;rsquo;s camera change the meaning of these vistas? &amp;lt;&amp;mdash;is this a question for the other post&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These images represent a particular kind of sublime associated with a particular kind of political project.
While great magnitude and manifold features are part of Burke&amp;rsquo;s sublime, he later disavows &amp;ldquo;colonnades and avenues of trees [&amp;hellip;] suffered to run to immense distances&amp;rdquo; as urbane.
However, the ultimate height of construction (and of trees) was not foreseen by Burke in 1757: the technical and natural discoveries in nineteenth-century and early-twentieth-century America would dwarf those of eighteenth-century Europe.
Moreover, metropolitans worldwide realized the need to incorporate great sights into their cityscapes.
Historian David Nye writes of an American technological sublime, a fusion of American technical mastery and pre-American resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I argue that this modification of Burke&amp;rsquo;s typology (which had separated the sublime into natural and architectural modes) can be used to better understand how the expansive imagery in &lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt; contributes to a &amp;ldquo;weakening of historicity, both in our relationship to public History and in the new forms of our private temporality&amp;rdquo;.^[Frederic Jameson, &lt;a href=&#34;https://web.archive.org/web/20110806060217/http://homepage.newschool.edu/~quigleyt/vcs/jameson/jameson.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Cultural Logic of Late Capitalism&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Keeping with &lt;a href=&#34;https://popculturebento.com/the-all-american-gaze-distorted-perspective-in-alfred-hitchcocks-vertigo/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;my earlier analysis of the film&lt;/a&gt;, I maintain that &lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt; presents both a private message concerning Scottie Ferguson&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:Portrayed-by-Jim&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:Portrayed-by-Jim&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and a public message about the social geography of 1950&amp;rsquo;s America.
In the interest of clarity, I focus today only on the public message, detailing how the American sublime clashes pre-modernity with modernity, disorienting Scottie&amp;rsquo;s experience of history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-drives-scottie&#34;&gt;What drives Scottie?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understanding the sublime images in &lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt; begins with understanding how Scottie encounters such pictures.
Since the film is shot (mostly) from his perspective, Hitchcock&amp;rsquo;s treatment of the Golden Gate, the Muir Woods, and the Mission all derive from Scottie.
While his desires have been the subject of several careers in film studies, it will help to simplify by looking at the film itself for direction.
Stewart&amp;rsquo;s body language clues us in to the gravity of his encounter with Gavin Elster, Madeleine&amp;rsquo;s husband.
As Nerdwriter &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UgnNakO6JZw&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;demonstrates&lt;/a&gt;, this meeting has so much to do with each man&amp;rsquo;s power.
This short exchange seems to encapsulate much of the two men&amp;rsquo;s urges:

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/udMms5FKyok?t=47&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

And in the script:
&amp;gt;ELSTER: San Francisco&amp;rsquo;s changed. The things that spell San Francisco to me are disappearing fast.
SCOTTIE: (Scottie smiles at the old prints [of a small, façaded San Francisco surrounded by dangerous and rocky terrain] on the wall.) Like all this.
ELSTER: (Nodding) I&amp;rsquo;d like to have lived here then. The color and excitement&amp;hellip; the power&amp;hellip;  the freedom.
(Though he does not stress the word, the way he lingers softly on the word &amp;ldquo;Freedom&amp;rdquo; makes Scottie look over at him again. Elster looks up and smiles companionably.)&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:Alec-Coppel-Samu&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:Alec-Coppel-Samu&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the mechanisms by which 1950s San Francisco distances itself from its Wild West past&amp;mdash;the long sequences in sleek automobiles, the infrequent references to psychiatry, a brassiere operating by &amp;ldquo;the principle of the cantilever bridge&amp;rdquo;&amp;mdash;are here disavowed in favor of a dangerous and unfamiliar past.
That bra symbolizes surprisingly much of the city&amp;rsquo;s changes.
Its &amp;ldquo;revolutionary uplift&amp;rdquo;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:Vertigo-script-P&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:Vertigo-script-P&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; are designed for the pleasure of men, as much of city&amp;rsquo;s attractions were.
Meanwhile, the comfort provided by the innovative architecture undoubtedly improved women&amp;rsquo;s lives, albeit in small ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By including men and women, the bra is thus a factor of the democratic virtues of the American technological sublime outlined by David Nye.
But it is also a product of that historical concept, designed by an engineer in his spare time, a &amp;ldquo;kind of do-it-yourself thing,&amp;rdquo; as Scottie notes.
This spirit of tinkering that came from outside the state apparatus and wealthy class is the reason why &amp;ldquo;Engineers, builders, and inventors began to occupy [&amp;hellip;] the pantheon of republicanism.&amp;ldquo;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:David-Nye-The-Am&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:David-Nye-The-Am&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
The bra (by its inventor, its target audience, its cantilever design) symbolizes how invention, innovation, and ambitious construction catered to America&amp;rsquo;s middle class.
These criteria of the American sublime would have been alien to a pre-modern San Francisco.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the above is but the first move in Nye&amp;rsquo;s distinctive double action of the American sublime.
Where that first move &amp;ldquo;usurped the place of natural things with man-made objects” conceived as &amp;ldquo;internal improvements”, the second move covered the tracks of the first, assimilating the object of improvement as once again natural.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:Jimmy-Stewart&#34;&gt;Jimmy Stewart &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:Jimmy-Stewart&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:Portrayed-by-Jim&#34;&gt;Portrayed by Jimmy Stewart. &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:Portrayed-by-Jim&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:Alec-Coppel-Samu&#34;&gt;Alec Coppel &amp;amp; Samuel Taylor, &lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt; [script](&lt;a href=&#34;https://the.hitchcock.zone/wiki/Scripts:_Vertigo_(12/Sep/1957&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://the.hitchcock.zone/wiki/Scripts:_Vertigo_(12/Sep/1957&lt;/a&gt;) Part 2, dated 12 September 1957. &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:Alec-Coppel-Samu&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:Vertigo-script-P&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt; script, Part 1. &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:Vertigo-script-P&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:David-Nye-The-Am&#34;&gt;David Nye, &amp;ldquo;The American Sublime&amp;rdquo; in &lt;em&gt;American Technological Sublime&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:David-Nye-The-Am&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>David Lynch is Toying With Us</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2020/02/15/david-lynch-is-toying-with-us/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2020/02/15/david-lynch-is-toying-with-us/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I write this post while watching &lt;em&gt;Rabbits&lt;/em&gt;, a work of exceptional mystery but unexceptional tension.
Lynch casts two regulars&amp;mdash;Laura Harring and Naomi Watts&amp;mdash;opposite one newbie&amp;mdash;Scott Coffey&amp;mdash;as man-sized rabbits in what appears to be the &lt;em&gt;Blue Velvet&lt;/em&gt; apartment set.
These short films, available &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLSSx9jvH6luUPl-bqfqaJ8z8vHDqlu5ji&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;on YouTube&lt;/a&gt;, trip over several of Lynch&amp;rsquo;s signature aspects: characters sing haunting songs; mundane life is treated as a social experiment; and Angelo Baldametti&amp;rsquo;s synthesizers underscore everything.
&lt;em&gt;Rabbits&lt;/em&gt; insists that we examine our own tastes and be comfortable with those answers (and inevitably unanswered questions).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though it offers no plot or characters that could create tension in a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=j56WPBaiPYQ&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;conventional story structure&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Rabbits&lt;/em&gt; is seriously intriguing, and hints at larger, unobserved meanings.
This intrigue is not uncommon; in fact, my theory of late has been that Lynch understands that his viewers feel the hints and the suggestions at something grander, his films all metaphysical McGuffins.
In his films, characters do not look at one another&amp;mdash;they see, in flashy close-ups, the uncertain eyes of the other.
Leading women are never conventionally pretty&amp;mdash;they are fantastically upbeat and implausibly platinum, hysterical results of Hollywood insecure appeal to men&amp;rsquo;s wallets.
Cars do not traverse from point to point&amp;mdash;headlights sprint over dark, twisting roadways.
These are cinematic clichés, style that heightens substance when it is used eagerly and genuinely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://media.npr.org/assets/img/2013/04/18/lynchrabbits1024_wide-81b3911888e86e687da1a0370b19cc026967ef0d.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Set of *Rabbits*. The camera moves from this fixed position exactly once to zoom in on the telephone.&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is nothing substantive about &lt;em&gt;Rabbits&lt;/em&gt;: Lynch&amp;rsquo;s mastery over cinematic cliché is taken to the brink, and over.
In many Lynch films since &lt;em&gt;Blue Velvet&lt;/em&gt;, characters utter non-sequiters in total deadpan; but in &lt;em&gt;Rabbits&lt;/em&gt;, they utter nothing but non-sequiters, with no story to speak of!
This Baldametti score then adds style to substanceless grunts, sounds English speakers will recognize as words but not as meaningful sentences.
And with some serious hilarity, Lynch adds a sitcom applause over the entrances of each character into this one-room apartment and laughtracks after sentences like &amp;ldquo;It is 7pm&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;I almost forgot.&amp;rdquo;
These outbursts, audio cues to at-home viewers that Important or Funny happenings are taking place, mock TV shows like the &lt;em&gt;Big Bang Theory&lt;/em&gt;, whose live audiences treat academic jargon and references to comic books as the basis for side-splitting guffaws.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The distance between the intelligibility of plot in &lt;em&gt;Rabbits&lt;/em&gt; and the connotations of its audio cues emphasize the contingency of language and the ability of convention to invent meaning from nothing.
It is indisputable that Baldametti&amp;rsquo;s score is ominous, alerting viewers that Something Is Happening, or that audience laughter is comedic, alerting viewers that a Joke Is Occurring.
But simply because a connotation is indisputable does not make it true.
None would dispute the scores ominousness or the audiences laughter because the years of TV and film that we have watch have taught us to connect certain sounds to certain moments.
The work starts with children&amp;rsquo;s tales, where morality is stark and the audio cues used to reinforce a grand, unified message.
By grounding these otherwise unintelligible cues in extra-cinematic morality or realistic emotions, we learn to couple low, industrial sounds with alertness, and human laughter with comedy.
&lt;em&gt;Rabbits&lt;/em&gt; attempts to elicit those emotions by only employing the signifier, while ditching the plot points signified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.ytimg.com/vi/NiOx5yJx-jc/maxresdefault.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The *Persona*-like dream sequences. Nothing says for sure these rabbits sleep, but shifts in color and a demonic face that hovers in the upper left-hand corner match dream sequences in Lynch&#39;s other films.&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps one can argue that the words which immediately precede and follow the &lt;em&gt;Persona&lt;/em&gt;-like interpolated dream sequences are Important, but I am not convinced.
I propose that &lt;em&gt;Rabbits&lt;/em&gt; is David Lynch toying with us.
He wants to know if he can make pure entertainment, works without useful or familiar stories, but which nonetheless strap us into rollercoasters of joy, despair, nostalgia, and humor.
In his other works, this plays out seamlessly.
I (the viewer) achingly try to pin down the plot, and then the meaning of the narrative he created.
This process feels possible, but always out-of-reach in his other works, which ditch the rabbit heads and opt for sequences of dialog that I recognize as events and narrative momentum.
But in &lt;em&gt;Rabbits&lt;/em&gt;, the dissonance between signifier and signified makes the effect clear.
In &lt;em&gt;Rabbits&lt;/em&gt;, the laughter and music become parodic, pointing at the fact that in &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; language, cinematic or otherwise, our grunts are intelligible for no reasons other than Pavolvian repitition and the magic fizz of neurons.
Language is contingent, subject to chance mutation and adoption, and not subject to deep structures or extra-personal validity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>American Heartbreak</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2019/11/21/american-heartbreak/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2019/11/21/american-heartbreak/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am the American heartbreak–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rock on which Freedom&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stumped its toe–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The great mistake&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That Jamestown made&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Long ago&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;— Langston Hughes
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever I try to recall this poem, I search for &amp;ldquo;Plymouth Rock poem&amp;rdquo;, and freak out beacuse I can&amp;rsquo;t find it for a few seconds. This is because, all along, Hughes alludes to the founding of our nation without ever saying so. He points to our founding virtue, Freedom, and asks the reader to define it&amp;mdash;suddenly&amp;mdash;in their head. This question calls up our national myth, of virile men casting off the oppressive British yoke, which implants in Americans a desire for revolution and newness and independence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find this desire each time I encounter American colonial history. There is the Massachusetts Bay colonizers, and the Virginia Company of London, more than anything else I want to race forward to 1776. American history teaching defaults to setting our cast of characters on the North American continent in order to reach revolution, with that noble end somehow justifying everything that came before (if not ethically, then morally: we suffered, and thus &lt;em&gt;deserve&lt;/em&gt; Freedom). In the same way, the outposts of our frontiersmen and women served to legitimize the murder of indigenous people, conquest of Mexican territory, and deaths of our own colonizers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this myth may be just that, it is a powerful story that is consistently told. Hughes rides its momentum, immediately clipping America&amp;rsquo;s great strides towards Freedom with the realities of chattel slavery. Nothing could be further from Freedom. But Hughes is acknowledging the promise of Freedom: one&amp;rsquo;s heart can&amp;rsquo;t break if it doesn&amp;rsquo;t first beat. By acknowledging the promise along with its failure, Hughes ties this heartbreak inextricably to our nation&amp;rsquo;s founding. This is &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; American heartbreak, bound up with the 400-year history of democracy in Jamestown. Hughes pulls us&amp;mdash;with present tense, with reference to Jamestown, by describing something so hard, so immovable, so central to that other early colony&amp;mdash;into the contradiction hidden in our nation&amp;rsquo;s founding, and still so hidden today.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
