<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>essay | Corey Runkel</title>
    <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/categories/essay/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://runkelcorey.github.io/categories/essay/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>essay</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Corey N. Runkel 2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://runkelcorey.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>essay</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/categories/essay/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Putting Theory in its Place</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2020/01/20/putting-theory-in-its-place/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2020/01/20/putting-theory-in-its-place/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When statistics disagree with words, theory can be an effective arbitrator. These disciplinary stories impose an otherwordly coherence on an incoherent world. With so much information at hand, I became addicted to theory for this very quality. The few bad habits I struggle to kick have (thankfully) instilled a probably irrational fear of new bad habits. Unfortunately, in kicking these habits and warding off others, I turned to theory to make my decisions. In doing so, I appealed to ever more abstract and cloudy narratives to buttress those closer to the ground (for theory can only be invalidated by other theories). And so, my first two years of undergrad were marked by a myopic embrace that left me pretentious and ill-suited to conditions on the ground floor of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Letting go of theory as the source of knowledge has been such a difficult process for me because of issues I have trusting others&amp;mdash;I compulsively check my girlfriend in areas where she by so many miles has the upper hand of practical and, yes, theoretical experience. By listening to an argument, I myself pass judgment on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://writing.upenn.edu/~taransky/Barthes.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;death of its author&lt;/a&gt;. While I enjoy this ultimate power, it cannot explain why I return to theory when all else fails&amp;mdash;indeed, it is a famed theorist&amp;rsquo;s failure that prompts one of my swift judgments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, it&amp;rsquo;s on the continued survival of authors after meeting my scrutiny that I base my returns. The reasons for these positive judgments are no doubt varied and incoherent to some, but I am sure that many follow a similar pattern. First, a writer will introduce familiar concept in unfamiliar language. Then, this language&amp;mdash;combined with elongated sentences&amp;mdash;renders said once-familiar concept gobbledygook. At this point, my capacity for calling BS on difficult works is hindered by my choice to read almost exclusively ~the classics~. This choice, and the knowledge of this choice, activates a psychological muscle in me that translates prestige as authority. When aggregated, this muscle operates as a sociological pressure. Seen below, the Tennis Court Oath makes abundantly clear in whom authority rests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/6/6d/Le_Serment_du_Jeu_de_paume.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Jacques-Louis David&#39;s *Tennis Court Oath* uses attention to show where power lies. &#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This all vindicates Nietzsche&amp;rsquo;s quote &amp;ldquo;I am not understood. Hence my authority.&amp;rdquo; This logic does not bode well for readers, however. Blinded by high-wattage prestige, one loses with the ability to criticize the ability to think. The authority that difficult, highly-regarded theory held over me also held me in its sway: I assumed that there was something essential to living life to be plumbed in theory, rather than a story told using the dictionary of a particular discipline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last year, I have maintained a weaning off of theory by, ironically, reading more theory. Richard Rorty refreshed pragmatism for a theory-weary America&amp;mdash;not by assuring us that what works in practice works regardless of the theory, but by stabbing epistemology in the back with what can best be termed an analytic deconstruction. Understanding his work proved to be a crucial step in unlearning much of what school had taught me, but elsewhere in my life, I clung to theory, thinking that the less-rigorous exercise, wellness, and movie literature could still be optimized by a turn towards theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I found were concrete ways in which that thought&amp;mdash;that life could be optimized by theory&amp;mdash;disappointed me. This disappointment brought the set of things I Know to Be True up with the set of things I &lt;em&gt;Think&lt;/em&gt; I Know to Be True. In other words, what I had read was made real before my eyes, elevating that knowledge to second-nature status. The vehicle for this realization was cooking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had begun really trying to cook two years ago, when I spurned the atrocities of my university&amp;rsquo;s dining hall. I asked for an Instant Pot that Christmas, and found hundreds of recipes to choose from. What the recipes called for, I did diligently. My girlfriend rarely challenged these steps, for the Instant Pot admits no air to its chamber, let alone the senses that allow facilitate good cooking. Recently, however, I&amp;rsquo;ve moved away from the Instant Pot in pursuit of perfectly-tuned seasoning and picturesque browning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In doing so, the superior wisdom of the cooks around me&amp;mdash;my girlfriend most loudly&amp;mdash;has battered the recipes I originally held so high. Trusting my own senses, and thinking critically about each step, have been given a newfound priority. The genius of cooking is that the tongue is already a great judge of cooking! In this light, it is immediately clear that famous names and convoluted explanations offer nowhere near the precision and attention that the mouth serves up instantaneously. &amp;ldquo;To write is to reach&amp;rdquo; said Barthes, and to cook might as well be added to that list. Each attempt is a venture into unknown territory, where local knowledge trumps the views from nowhere offered by orphaned recipes on cooking websites. Samin Nosrat&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Salt, Fat, Acid, Heat&lt;/em&gt; grounds this truth with a million stories of direction-following as well as rule-breaking. The book explicitly claims to induct the laws of good cooking, but, implicitly, it works because of her history in kitchens around the world. She resists listicle format, step-by-step instructions in favor of narrative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This decision allows for reflection and judgment, and she constantly refers back to cooks&amp;rsquo; own palettes, finger tips, and eardrums. This reference (and deference) does the real work of teaching, imploring readers to become writers and eaters to become cooks. Trying to assimilate her principles with her recipes has already improved my cooking, and the fearlessness with which I annotate her beautifully-illustrated hardback has been a quietly-empowering experience. Cooking has shown me what my great professor Marlon Ross once told me, that great work speaks up to theory instead of letting theory talk down to it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Aspirational Efficiency</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2019/11/07/aspirational-efficiency/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2019/11/07/aspirational-efficiency/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The easiest way to derail any work that I am doing is by linking to an article ranking and comparing things that will help me live a better life. That article might rank the 10 best productivity apps, it may uncover new services which partition and categorize every second of my day, or&amp;mdash;as it did yesterday&amp;mdash;it could offer me a phone that can satisfy my needs immediately, stripping my day of wasted time. The only certainty is that I, in my manifold time management skills, will click on that link.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought this was a phenomenon entirely local to myself until I saw this &lt;a href=&#34;https://aeon.co/essays/how-did-being-happy-become-a-matter-of-relentless-competitive-work&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; from Aeon, noting that life management has become a juggernaut in consumer retail, with &amp;ldquo;self-care and anti-stress products now rounding out the bestseller list on Amazon&amp;rdquo;. We&amp;rsquo;ve reined in other animals, organizations of people, and our bodies by calibrating each measurable parameter, so why not do the same for our minds? Unfortunately, we don&amp;rsquo;t seem quite as pliant as the optimization equations imply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This logic, made inexorable by limitless access to information, tugs at our happiness. Behind whatever tool or activity or person present before us lurks an alternative, a next-best option. This idea has driven every rationalist attempt at decision making, but its actual calculus has changed considerably since the 1990s. Before then, catalogued libraries and television delivered then-unprecedented access to information. The task of research had become immediately more accessible, but also less clear. Suddenly, more and more causes sprang up to explain each effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The move from card catalogues and TV to Wikipedia and on-demand streaming was a leap in this dimension. Different from past moves was the sheer scale of new information. The closest comparison to make would likely be the telegram that could relay news around the world in minutes, but that did not solve the last-mile problem that our phones and computers did. Similar to past moves is the growing illusion of choice. Most definitions model illusory choice as a free decision between a constrained set of options, like choosing from a soda machine that offers a dozen brands but where every choice is a Coca-Cola product. But rather than onstrained options, I interpret illusory choice as constrained decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our brain budgets time and resources based on prior neurological sequences, updating expectations with each iteration. While we may understand how normal it is not to find an exhaustive cost-benefits comparison of the more than 2,000 results for &amp;ldquo;thimble&amp;rdquo; on Amazon, our brains may not. Our expectations have been conditioned by the norms of evidence-based administration to treat anything less than exhaustive comparisons as failure. This extends to our lives, where exhaustive comparison has meant nothing less than exhaustion. Where once, exhaustive comparisons meant eyeballing dozens, now it means eyeballing hundreds, thousands, or millions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our internal search processes can&amp;rsquo;t handle such scale. While they have gradually widened, the velocity of extension by the market has effectively capped the rate at which we had to develop non-exhaustive ways to search. When the village had a single cobbler, shoes were a constant, not a variable to optimize over. Still, when there are ten types of black beans at the grocery store, they can be compared quite readily. But when it&amp;rsquo;s always possible to opt for peer-to-peer sellers in Kolkata over the ~local~ Walmart, people are given the room every day to exhaust their critical thinking skills trying to gauge the expected payoffs of a hundred options, and a million more they know to be lurking, accessible to anyone with the right search terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our minds haven&amp;rsquo;t caught up yet. They can take on waves of epic proportions, but a tide that lifts them high enough to see the world&amp;rsquo;s ginormity will overwhelm. I see two ways out: time and pragmatism. The first just says that after enough time passes, our minds will adjust, will think in different ways to approach this different problem. But that option offers only consolation to people currently. Option two offers that different way. Construct in your mind a noble lie, something appealing but fanciful. Then, believe in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adhering to a set of values fixes those variables as constants. This is Marie Kondo for your mind, with the tiny caveat that beliefs weigh far more than shower organizers, dressers, or homes. The values chosen don&amp;rsquo;t have to conform to Marie Kondo&amp;ndash;like advice. In fact, choosing something already at tension with what FastCompany promises are the best ways to increase productivity is probably best. It&amp;rsquo;s good training for the future. Rather, pick values that will let you do the most of your wants, your in-the-moment pleasures. Do not conflate &amp;lsquo;do the most&amp;rsquo; with &amp;lsquo;most choices&amp;rsquo;. To do the most, you need clear boundaries that, if crossed, bind you to decisions, decisions that you could theoretically even come to regret, but decisions that you need to make. Pragmatism means believing what needs to be believed, even if it can&amp;rsquo;t stand up to rationalist inquiry.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
