<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>analysis | Corey Runkel</title>
    <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/categories/analysis/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://runkelcorey.github.io/categories/analysis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>analysis</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Corey N. Runkel 2019</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://runkelcorey.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>analysis</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/categories/analysis/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Distortion in Vertigo (1958)</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2019/08/27/vertigo-1958/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2019/08/27/vertigo-1958/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hitchcock’s cinematographic style changes with each script and year in which he immerses himself, unlike the storybook qualities of Wes Anderson or the placid “[Drops dripped]”(&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/quotes/665415-drops-dripped-quiet-talk-went-on-horses-neighed-and-scuffled&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://www.goodreads.com/quotes/665415-drops-dripped-quiet-talk-went-on-horses-neighed-and-scuffled&lt;/a&gt;) of Andrei Tarkovsky. &lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt;, at the [dizzying] heights(&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.com/news/entertainment-arts-19078948&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://www.bbc.com/news/entertainment-arts-19078948&lt;/a&gt;) of Hitchcock’s mastery, leads us into John Ferguson’s&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:James-Stewart&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:James-Stewart&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; mind—distorted by the lethal, dozen-story fall of a partner trying to save Ferguson—by forcing us into cramped spaces and mocking our spatial judgment. These techniques make reasonable the otherwise unreasonable male gaze of John Ferguson, though it’s unclear whether it serves to justify that gaze.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it was not until considering David Lynch’s &lt;em&gt;Mulholland Drive&lt;/em&gt; that I could tease out a part of Hitchcock’s trick, there were too many motifs to grab a hold of! Hitchcock employs a &lt;a href=&#34;https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/514a2911e4b0896b36342655/1482995944327-EWLBUKOGUEVV2J7984Q3/ke17ZwdGBToddI8pDm48kDJVOyiZxV_-dowl7sRu02MUqsxRUqqbr1mOJYKfIPR7LoDQ9mXPOjoJoqy81S2I8N_N4V1vUb5AoIIIbLZhVYwL8IeDg6_3B-BRuF4nNrNcQkVuAT7tdErd0wQFEGFSnM_12NgTIazSm1At4R8ulVAcqDD8dBOmEycJv1fx_vd3MyvpBiIzzydoM1I6fLa65Q/image-asset.png?format=2500w&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;contrasting color palette&lt;/a&gt;, his signature(ly disturbing) perplexion with blonde women, and an unforgettable break in narrative. &lt;em&gt;Mulholland&lt;/em&gt; offers those motifs amped up to surrealistic proportions, with color palettes at near antagonistic levels, the blondes shining ever more platinum, though its narrative break is difficult to pinpoint. Connecting &lt;em&gt;Mulholland Drive&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt; makes the interpretation of Hitchcock’s film no easier, but facilitates a shift in mindset that rendered &lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt; much more interpretable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mean this: Lynch is enigmatic as hell, but he continues to give interviews. In these interviews, he surrenders much of his creativity to what he terms “dream-logic”, and it stands out immediately. Dream-logic connects two objects despite their inconsistencies according to logic-logic. Such an approach finds its Western roots entirely recent, coming primarily out of Sigmund Freud’s &lt;em&gt;Interpretation of Dreams&lt;/em&gt;. Its epistemology is usually visual in [Lynch’s] movies, though connections via homonym or punnery are entirely within the bounds of Freudian analysis. While a novelty in 2001 &lt;em&gt;Mulholland Drive&lt;/em&gt; premiered, 1958 saw psychoanalysis at its peak of influence. This rise crashed into Hitchcock’s prior work with film noir, convoluted plots that often involved damaged detectives and female subjects vulnerable physically and mentally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt; synthesizes these two strands. Kim Novak’s characters—one before, one after the narrative break—vie for their freedom against their supposed history. In classic Hitchcock fashion, &lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt; can be summarized as a Wrong Man Film&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:cf-The-Wrong-Man&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:cf-The-Wrong-Man&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, where the protagonist is mistaken for a doppelgänger implicated in deep, deep shit. Unclassically, *Vertigo*’s protagonist is no man; and its protagonist(s) is/are not its central character(s). Novak’s Judy Barton is modeled (mostly) against her will after a prior, dead San Francisco socialite, Madeleine Ester,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:Novak-in-Act-1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:Novak-in-Act-1&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; who herself models a [much more] prior, dead San Francisco socialite. The complicity of each in creating their respective &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iron_cage&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;iron cloaks&lt;/a&gt; of identity is uncertain, but beside the point—Ferguson’s male gaze visualizes these identities before they are realized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often enough, the male gaze is analyzed as a whole, apart from its sometimes very specific set of eyes. I get at Ferguson’s specific set through Hitchcock’s motifs and cinematography. John Ferguson’s gaze is set very literally in the film’s opening. Hitchcock shakes up the presumably keen vision of a detective with his partner’s death. The fall and the height and the guilt confuse themselves in Ferguson’s head to deliver him a crippling case of vertigo, rendering him unproductive and idle, unmoored from his former senses of intelligence. There is nothing objective against which Ferguson can mark the damage his trauma wrought, no other detectives to which he can compare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hitchock will signify this psychosis slowly at first, then all at once. This chronological pattern approximates the spiral imagery so fundamental to &lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt;. Saul Bass’ iconic movie poster design depicts Ferguson plunging into a line-drawn spiral. This third dimension is added, and reflects the way objects track in wide-diameter circles, speeding as the circles shrink and finally encloses the object.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:Cf-This-comical&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:Cf-This-comical&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Concerned of the obsession his wife (Madeleine) exhibits for a suicidal ancestor, Ferguson’s friend sends him to play private detective. While Scottie takes logical steps to follow the wife’s story, his social isolation and physical trauma get the better of him. His steps culminate in a famous leap into the brisk San Francisco Bay, where, just before, Madeleine plunged, unconscious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.ytimg.com/vi/ih-KeOf3xQQ/maxresdefault.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;*Vertigo*’s massive field of view.&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the dive in, James Ferguson can never quite get himself on solid ground. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://i1.wp.com/www.abelardomorell.net/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/2017_Flowers-For-Lisa-76-After-Hitchcock%E2%80%99s-Vertigo-2017-copy-1.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;spiral patterns&lt;/a&gt; begin to crop up in paintings, department stores, cemeteries, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://2.bp.blogspot.com/-I5ob7SqVmUQ/T1rcELu28SI/AAAAAAAACaM/bt6R6pd-4a0/s1600/Hitchcock+Vertigo.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The tight spiral of Madeleine, her ancestor, and eventually Judy connects the three in Ferguson’s dream-logic.&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caught in the inner circles of a deepening plot and deepening conspiracy, Hitchcock simulates what Ferguson’s deepening psychosis&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:Note-that-this-m&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:Note-that-this-m&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; must feel like with a cinematographical trickery that encloses John Ferguson’s figure, disclosing the craze lurking inside his obsessed mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With deep focus and a 2-D plane, cameras force our visual cortex to compare the near and far. The video below demonstrates this several times.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/bDwPJ5IaJ2g&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Those yellow flowers that Scottie walks behind at 1:59 appear taller than him in that moment, and the obscured view traps his figure in the history, mystery, and death that linger after Novak exits the scene. Hitchcock further unsettles viewers in :17, not with the normal technique of a dolly following Ferguson and suggesting danger, but by a shot from below. This camera setting exaggerates the heights and lengths of objects outside focal point, making the 3ft flowers equal the 6ft Ferguson in height. But the mastery here is the unresolved tension between these instances of camera trickery and Hitchcock’s concurrent attention to truly large objects. The enormity of the Golden Gate bridge in one famous shot anchors the nearly surreal imagery elsewhere in &lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt;, cementing a permanent unease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add this to the geologic folding that turns ordinary car following into labyrinthine mazes:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/fNyUpJGEnR4?t=73&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And of course, *Vertigo*’s signature camera effect, the zoom-in/dolly-out:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/O888bu0QrMg?t=56&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The spirals (2:13), the huge objects (:36), the zoom-in/dolly-out (1:20) culminate in *Vertigo*’s quasi-climax:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/GjPCk494e5Q&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The scene in Mission San Juan Bautista also bears striking resemblances to the work of Italian surrealist Giorgio de Chirico. De Chirico’s work produces a sense of unease through its emphasis on the uncanny, that which is not quite and yet almost is. I like to think of a composite image, the subimages of which are all perfectly possible, though the composite somehow not being possible. In the image below, which reminds me both of the Mission and the ever-out-of-reach Madeleine, the sky is a natural color for sunsets and the long shadows possible at twilight, but the building is so bright and the shadows so stark that the image could not possibly depict a real event. Hitchcock, toeing the sur/realism line, never leaves us with quite the uncanny images or impossible geometries to prove the sort of dream-logic that Lynch would make explicit, but these scenes add up. With snaking streets, out-of-proportion objects, and color palette, builds a profile of the uncanny without ever letting us put a finger on it. Like Ferguson, the viewer is hard-pressed to resolve the visual inputs Hitchcock offers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This kind of confusion invites resolution for the viewer into a reality-less vacuum. Similarly, John Ferguson is a detective, used to getting to the Bottom of Things. Here, he can’t. All his preternatural detective powers have been duped by trauma and deceit. He is painfully aware which way is up and which down, but not much beyond that. Through all the twists and turns, Ferguson never understands (or rather, never is able to convince himself he understands) Madeleine. The history regresses too far for his eyes to penetrate. Unable to free himself from this convoluted plot and detached from reality, John Ferguson imposes a narrative on Judy. &lt;em&gt;He&lt;/em&gt; now makes her tick. And the viewer accepts this to some degree because the story is resolution-deficient. Trapped within John Ferguson’s mind, escape is—depending on the specific viewer—to some extent preferable, even when it carries such gross implications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The male gaze exists only in an environment where sexual assault and rape are legally (or in practice, sometimes only socially) prohibited. Faced with these restrictions, the gaze seeks to dissect and then exploit the [primarily sexual] motives of its subjects to &amp;lt;smooth-talk&amp;gt; its way into contractual consent. In other words, the gazer presumes a fixed stance, while the gazee is assumed to be malleable to the interests of the gazer, amenable with the right words or proposition. But for the moment, the male gaze objectifies its subjects so that accumulated behaviors can also be thought of as fixed, indicative of one true whole. The end of this dissection is the formulation of strategies which comport to the fixed character of the man and the inducted motives of the gazee, which end in legally-allowed sex. In failing to dissect Judy’s motives, John resorts to that secondary strategy of the male gaze, conjuring scenarios—no matter how fantastical—that presume a preponderance of bargaining power.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:A-preponderance&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:A-preponderance&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; He then takes what is/was considered the truly outrageous step to realize those fantastical scenarios and absurd bargaining power, molding Judy so that her behavior can be made to comport with John Ferguson’s desires, fabricating superficially-consensual sex. The viewers’ interests are sympathetic to John’s, needing as they do resolution, but are then [hopefully] spoiled when they realize that their interests imply the exploitation of Judy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In interpreting the greater significance of &lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt;, I benefit again from viewing Hitchcock through Lynch’s rear window:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My childhood was elegant homes, tree-lined streets, the milkman, building backyard forts, droning airplanes, blue skies, picket fences, green grass, cherry trees. Middle America as it&amp;rsquo;s supposed to be. But on the cherry tree there&amp;rsquo;s this pitch oozing out – some black, some yellow, and millions of red ants crawling all over it. I discovered that if one looks a little closer at this beautiful world, there are &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; red ants underneath.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hitchcock views America somewhat from the outside. He picks a very particular part of the US, one where the histories of people who were not British is readily apparent. This choice primarily works to operate on the level of uncanny history, a history that few are equipped to read into their own history of America, as well as their (families’) own history in America. It’s therefore both easy to dissociate John Ferguson’s particular position from their own, while difficult to completely disentangle the silver screen from real life. James Stewart’s prior roles were as US everyman turned Congressman in &lt;em&gt;Mr. Smith Goes to Washington&lt;/em&gt;, aviator Charles Lindbergh in &lt;em&gt;The Spirit of St. Louis&lt;/em&gt;, a cowboy in &lt;em&gt;Winchester ‘73&lt;/em&gt;, George Bailey in &lt;em&gt;It’s a Wonderful Life&lt;/em&gt;. I cannot think of another actor who so embodied rich, moral American-ness during this time. Hitchcock then takes apart this rich, moral, American figure by finding within him obsession, formidable sexuality, and desperation. A bit of psychological trauma sets off (or reveals?) the ants in this cherry tree. More specifically, the bent of America is towards taking that which/who is not ours and assimilating them, without dealing with &amp;lt;underlying&amp;gt; issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find it difficult to read Hitchcock as directing completely critically, given the patent fetishism of Kim Novak’s characters. In that vein, I would echo the interpretation of American men above, but stop short of believing Hitchcock to be fully critical. For him, I don’t think the discomfort of Judy’s situation outweighs his fetish for Novak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:James-Stewart&#34;&gt;James Stewart &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:James-Stewart&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:cf-The-Wrong-Man&#34;&gt;cf. &lt;em&gt;The Wrong Man&lt;/em&gt; (1956) &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:cf-The-Wrong-Man&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:Novak-in-Act-1&#34;&gt;Novak in &amp;lt;Act 1&amp;gt;. &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:Novak-in-Act-1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:Cf-This-comical&#34;&gt;Cf. This comical &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.spiralwishingwells.com/images/all-wells-and-vortx-steve-1000.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;image&lt;/a&gt; of a charity coin spinner, or how a &lt;a href=&#34;https://images.fineartamerica.com/images/artworkimages/mediumlarge/2/gravity-well-spencer-sutton.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;gravity well&lt;/a&gt; may alter planetary orbits. &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:Cf-This-comical&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:Note-that-this-m&#34;&gt;Note that this means thoughts become detached from external reality. When we understand that no person can diagnose another from anywhere but their own viewpoint firmly in the mainstream of productive society, it becomes clear that the usage of the word ‘reality’ is misleading. Reality does not exist—it is judged to exist—but always with psychology this judgment originates from the highly-educated professional class. Understanding what ‘external reality’ entails means John Ferguson could both be “detached from external reality” and quite rational in both his and the viewers’ eyes. Hitchcock plays on this truth in many films. Just because you’re paranoid doesn’t mean somebody isn’t out to get you. &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:Note-that-this-m&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:A-preponderance&#34;&gt;A preponderance so great, that no judge could rule that the contract was made freely. &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:A-preponderance&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
