<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>cooking | Corey Runkel</title>
    <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/tags/cooking/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://runkelcorey.github.io/tags/cooking/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>cooking</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© C.N. Runkel 2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://runkelcorey.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>cooking</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/tags/cooking/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Putting Theory in its Place</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2020/01/20/putting-theory-in-its-place/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2020/01/20/putting-theory-in-its-place/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When statistics disagree with words, theory can be an effective arbitrator. These disciplinary stories impose an otherwordly coherence on an incoherent world. With so much information at hand, I became addicted to theory for this very quality. The few bad habits I struggle to kick have (thankfully) instilled a probably irrational fear of new bad habits. Unfortunately, in kicking these habits and warding off others, I turned to theory to make my decisions. In doing so, I appealed to ever more abstract and cloudy narratives to buttress those closer to the ground (for theory can only be invalidated by other theories). And so, my first two years of undergrad were marked by a myopic embrace that left me pretentious and ill-suited to conditions on the ground floor of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Letting go of theory as the source of knowledge has been such a difficult process for me because of issues I have trusting others&amp;mdash;I compulsively check my girlfriend in areas where she by so many miles has the upper hand of practical and, yes, theoretical experience. By listening to an argument, I myself pass judgment on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://writing.upenn.edu/~taransky/Barthes.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;death of its author&lt;/a&gt;. While I enjoy this ultimate power, it cannot explain why I return to theory when all else fails&amp;mdash;indeed, it is a famed theorist&amp;rsquo;s failure that prompts one of my swift judgments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, it&amp;rsquo;s on the continued survival of authors after meeting my scrutiny that I base my returns. The reasons for these positive judgments are no doubt varied and incoherent to some, but I am sure that many follow a similar pattern. First, a writer will introduce familiar concept in unfamiliar language. Then, this language&amp;mdash;combined with elongated sentences&amp;mdash;renders said once-familiar concept gobbledygook. At this point, my capacity for calling BS on difficult works is hindered by my choice to read almost exclusively ~the classics~. This choice, and the knowledge of this choice, activates a psychological muscle in me that translates prestige as authority. When aggregated, this muscle operates as a sociological pressure. Seen below, the Tennis Court Oath makes abundantly clear in whom authority rests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/6/6d/Le_Serment_du_Jeu_de_paume.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Jacques-Louis David&#39;s *Tennis Court Oath* uses attention to show where power lies. &#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This all vindicates Nietzsche&amp;rsquo;s quote &amp;ldquo;I am not understood. Hence my authority.&amp;rdquo; This logic does not bode well for readers, however. Blinded by high-wattage prestige, one loses with the ability to criticize the ability to think. The authority that difficult, highly-regarded theory held over me also held me in its sway: I assumed that there was something essential to living life to be plumbed in theory, rather than a story told using the dictionary of a particular discipline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last year, I have maintained a weaning off of theory by, ironically, reading more theory. Richard Rorty refreshed pragmatism for a theory-weary America&amp;mdash;not by assuring us that what works in practice works regardless of the theory, but by stabbing epistemology in the back with what can best be termed an analytic deconstruction. Understanding his work proved to be a crucial step in unlearning much of what school had taught me, but elsewhere in my life, I clung to theory, thinking that the less-rigorous exercise, wellness, and movie literature could still be optimized by a turn towards theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I found were concrete ways in which that thought&amp;mdash;that life could be optimized by theory&amp;mdash;disappointed me. This disappointment brought the set of things I Know to Be True up with the set of things I &lt;em&gt;Think&lt;/em&gt; I Know to Be True. In other words, what I had read was made real before my eyes, elevating that knowledge to second-nature status. The vehicle for this realization was cooking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had begun really trying to cook two years ago, when I spurned the atrocities of my university&amp;rsquo;s dining hall. I asked for an Instant Pot that Christmas, and found hundreds of recipes to choose from. What the recipes called for, I did diligently. My girlfriend rarely challenged these steps, for the Instant Pot admits no air to its chamber, let alone the senses that allow facilitate good cooking. Recently, however, I&amp;rsquo;ve moved away from the Instant Pot in pursuit of perfectly-tuned seasoning and picturesque browning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In doing so, the superior wisdom of the cooks around me&amp;mdash;my girlfriend most loudly&amp;mdash;has battered the recipes I originally held so high. Trusting my own senses, and thinking critically about each step, have been given a newfound priority. The genius of cooking is that the tongue is already a great judge of cooking! In this light, it is immediately clear that famous names and convoluted explanations offer nowhere near the precision and attention that the mouth serves up instantaneously. &amp;ldquo;To write is to reach&amp;rdquo; said Barthes, and to cook might as well be added to that list. Each attempt is a venture into unknown territory, where local knowledge trumps the views from nowhere offered by orphaned recipes on cooking websites. Samin Nosrat&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/985508716&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Salt, Fat, Acid, Heat&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; grounds this truth with a million stories of direction-following as well as rule-breaking. The book explicitly claims to induct the laws of good cooking, but, implicitly, it works because of her history in kitchens around the world. She resists listicle format, step-by-step instructions in favor of narrative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This decision allows for reflection and judgment, and she constantly refers back to cooks&amp;rsquo; own palettes, finger tips, and eardrums. This reference (and deference) does the real work of teaching, imploring readers to become writers and eaters to become cooks. Trying to assimilate her principles with her recipes has already improved my cooking, and the fearlessness with which I annotate her beautifully-illustrated hardback has been a quietly-empowering experience. Cooking has shown me what my great professor Marlon Ross once told me, that great work speaks up to theory instead of letting theory talk down to it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
