<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>open data | Corey Runkel</title>
    <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/categories/open-data/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://runkelcorey.github.io/categories/open-data/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>open data</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© C.N. Runkel 2021</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://runkelcorey.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>open data</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/categories/open-data/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>YPFS Citation Style Language</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2021/03/24/ypfs-citation-style-language/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2021/03/24/ypfs-citation-style-language/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When I started at YPFS, we did all COVID all the time.
I&amp;rsquo;d wake up, get paid to doomscroll, and pump out some blogs about what was happening. When we reverted to case-writing, a huge backlog of cases had to be prepped for publication.
Many of these were years-old.
They neither shared common formatting nor common citations, and&amp;mdash;because the cases were so old&amp;mdash;the original authors had moved on to bigger and better things.
We needed to solve all the problems that come with a team distributed not only across space but also time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For literal centuries, publications have solved this problem with style guides and time-consuming editing practices.
However, these are only as strong as their enforcement.
Without savvy, patient editors and authors with hours to spare, editing for standardization rightfully takes a back seat to editing for clarity and content.
A somewhat newer solution involves distributing Word templates that authors simply fill in, Mad-Libs style.
But again, you run into the problem of enforcement.
The first time a line breaks where you don&amp;rsquo;t want it to, or you copy the source style along with the text, the Word template ceases to be &lt;em&gt;authoritative&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, for editors reviewing work years later, if citations aren&amp;rsquo;t perfect or comprehensive, finding the original document can be a bear.
These systems do not &lt;em&gt;link the product to the process&lt;/em&gt;.
They allow authors to keep &amp;ldquo;two sets of books&amp;rdquo;: one, incomplete but well-formatted, that gets published; another, complete but unstructured, located somewhere without a link tracing to it.
In this way, Word documents&amp;mdash;for all the ways they liberate formatting and track changes&amp;mdash;are little different from plain paper.
We have had &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hypertext&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;ways&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hypertext&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;connect&lt;/a&gt; product and process for years, but it is hard to generate buy-in.
Some compromise between accessibility (plain-text editors aren&amp;rsquo;t familiar to most) and utility (e.g. Markdown would be ideal) is usually required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our compromise is the amazing reference manager &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.zotero.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Zotero&lt;/a&gt;.
It builds citations using Citation Style Language (&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.citationstyles.org/en/stable/primer.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;CSL&lt;/a&gt;).
CSL imposes it style in Word documents using fields (kinda like those used often for page numbers or automatically updating dates) that it controls.
In this way it is authoritative.
Zotero feeds it information stored in its desktop app.
What you put in is put out on the page.
In this way it connects product to process: to create a correct and nice-looking bibliography requires citing throughout a document and inputting data correctly to Zotero, which is super easy to search and connects documents to their contexts on the web.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CSL, is also open source, which means that we could configure a style to our liking.
While we mostly like Chicago (author-date) style, I and another Research Associate updated it with some contextual information.
I learnt this XML-like language and have been deploying it with Git.
It&amp;rsquo;s my first experience developing software that people actually &lt;em&gt;use&lt;/em&gt;.
This makes a huge difference!
Working with something that will be used in the future by end-users made me think several steps ahead to maintain forward- and backward-compatibility, and reminded me how much I enjoy solving problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the code &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/runkelcorey/ypfs/blob/master/ypfs-mini.csl&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>US Housing</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/project/housing/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/project/housing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project is majorly on hold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love the idea that all these super materialist forces influence how we act and think, and the home is just about the most materialist symbol.
In this country, homes take on new financial dimensions as bastions of wealth, new aspirational dimensions as the base of American Dreams, and&amp;mdash;with covid&amp;mdash;make up the lifeworlds of a good chunk of people.
Housing politics occupied the last year of my time UVA, between the Urban Planning and Politics departments, with &lt;a href=&#34;../../publication/thesis/actors-motive.html&#34;&gt;my undergrad thesis&lt;/a&gt; capping the year.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>YPFS citation engine</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/project/ypfs-csl/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/project/ypfs-csl/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This bit of code takes in Zotero entries and outputs formatted citations.
I wrote about it &lt;a href=&#34;../../2021/03/24/ypfs-citation-style-language/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>YPFS ggplot theme</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/project/ypfs-theme/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/project/ypfs-theme/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project is a bit on hold as I strike the right balance between accessibility and flexibility.
It makes use of &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/yixuan/showtext&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;showtext&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which allows for the installation of custom fonts, but doesn&amp;rsquo;t handle extremely high and low quality as well as &lt;a href=&#34;https://ggplot2.tidyverse.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;ggplot2&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we at YPFS spent our whole days blogging about the pandemic&amp;rsquo;s toll on economies worldwide, we put out a lot of graphs, and they all looked different.
This isn&amp;rsquo;t the biggest deal, but consistent style goes a long way to weave different research threads together.
And with a &lt;a href=&#34;https://yaleidentity.yale.edu/web&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;typekit&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://toolness.github.io/accessible-color-matrix/?n=white&amp;amp;n=light&amp;amp;n=emphasis&amp;amp;n=Yale%20blue&amp;amp;n=black&amp;amp;v=F9F9F9&amp;amp;v=63AAFF&amp;amp;v=286DC0&amp;amp;v=00356B&amp;amp;v=222222&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;palette&lt;/a&gt; as beautiful as Yale&amp;rsquo;s, using Excel and Calibri is something of a shame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This repository is an evolving project to standardize the production of figures within R, an open-source statistical package. Researchers who publish with[in] the Yale School of Management will recognize its distinct use of Helvetica Neue, while affiliated with the University at large will recognize that typekit and palette of blues. However, conforming to the school&amp;rsquo;s style can be a time-consuming process, likely to be ignored in favor of other work. A standard theme can plug the gap caused by tedious formatting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>YPFS web scraper</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/project/ypfs-translator/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/project/ypfs-translator/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;RAs would told me how much time it takes to enter metadata into both Zotero and &lt;a href=&#34;ypfs.som.yale.edu&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;our own archive&lt;/a&gt;.
Because our Zotero library captures more information than our archive, the ideal solution was to export Zotero information to our Drupal content management system.
However, YPFS gets no love from Yale&amp;rsquo;s business-school IT department.
We ultimately find a lot of workarounds to aid our work, and it was no different here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way to cut down on time spent entering metadata was the reverse: instead of exporting to our archive, we could export &lt;em&gt;from&lt;/em&gt; our archive.
This is where Zotero comes in.
It accepts a number of different formats for bibliographic information stored on websites.
Unfortunately, our website exposes metadata in none of these &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.zotero.org/support/dev/exposing_metadata&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;standard&lt;/a&gt; formats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, we needed to slightly modify our idea of how to transfer data between Zotero and our archive.
In this case, we &lt;em&gt;imported&lt;/em&gt; from our archive.
Zotero &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zotero/translators/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;allows&lt;/a&gt; people to volunteer translators that let Zotero read metadata on specific sites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned the basics of JavaScript to write &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zotero/translators/pull/2358&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; bit of code.
This totally felt like learning a new language.
My previous experience with programming had really been limited to data science.
I was accustomed to static products like a plot or table.
Here, I contended with interactivity&amp;mdash;in which a command is triggered by an end-user action&amp;mdash;and inputs not yet defined (a/k/a new webpages created in the future).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result is a plug-in that, once accepted by Zotero&amp;rsquo;s administrators, will allow all users of Zotero to import directly from our archive.
Significantly, it is the only website-specific translator I&amp;rsquo;ve seen that accepts more than just webpage snapshots or PDFs.
This translator will accept audio, video, Word documents, images, you name it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Political Impacts of Residential Mortgages in Crisis</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/publication/thesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/publication/thesis/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Federal Register API</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2019/08/03/federal-register-api/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2019/08/03/federal-register-api/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tl-dr&#34;&gt;TL;DR&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I created an &lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt; client to fetch data from the Federal Register, replacing an R package that had not been updated for years. It was my first foray into APIs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United States &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.federalregister.gov/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Federal Register&lt;/a&gt; is the [slowly] clearing house for every revision to US administrative law, regulatory enforcement, and the more stupid forms of jockeying and horn-tooting by federal agencies. The website, charged with the supremely bureaucratic duty of pigeonholing and circumscribing every sort of &amp;lt;&lt;event&gt;&amp;gt; in Washington, is quite beautiful. Its ease, features, and appearance bear the marks of something that is truly for the public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To aid readers, [and the odd corporation trying to stay a step ahead of environmental regulations,] the Office of the Federal Register got a leg up from a developer who made an API client for R. Unfortunately,&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:And-quite-ironic&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:And-quite-ironic&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that client has been rendered useless by updates. In the name of openness digital and governmental, I set to work on a new API client that would:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;teach me the fundamentals of APIs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;display some clever solutions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:And-quite-ironic&#34;&gt;And quite ironically for an institution with steeped in such bureaucracy. &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:And-quite-ironic&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
