<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>theory | Corey Runkel</title>
    <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/tags/theory/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://runkelcorey.github.io/tags/theory/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>theory</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© C.N. Runkel 2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://runkelcorey.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>theory</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/tags/theory/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>In Vertigo (1958), an Uncertain History</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2020/07/30/in-vertigo-an-uncertain-history/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2020/07/30/in-vertigo-an-uncertain-history/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.historyguide.org/europe/valery.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;We see now that the abyss of history is deep enough to hold us all.&lt;/a&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt; places a thoroughly modern Scottie Ferguson&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:Jimmy-Stewart&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:Jimmy-Stewart&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; within a thoroughly modern San Francisco.
It then watches as he slips from his mental moorings into a twisted version of himself.
His cycle of psychological terror constitutes a violent &lt;em&gt;displacement&lt;/em&gt;, and it re-opens two key questions of belonging: of Scottie to San Francisco; and of San Francisco to Scottie.
I will examine only the former today; the latter I leave for later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My argument runs like this:
&lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rsquo;s early scenes depict a San Francisco that is tailored to mobile white men like Scottie.
For his part, Scottie enforced the modern status quo as a San Francisco cop, until his partner died trying to save Scottie from falling during a rooftop chase.
With the danger supposedly over, he finds himself navigating a comfortable and controlled city, with sights/sites located just off the highway&amp;mdash;Fort XX, the Muir Woods, and the Mission San Juan Bautista.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But these parks did not just happen.
Public works efforts had to make the sites palettable to professionals and tourists.
These efforts had to isolate the visual cues of danger from any actual, Wild West&amp;ndash;type danger.
Rather than places to be reckoned with, these are sights to be gawked at.
In the first formulation, the site&amp;mdash;with all its natural and political forces&amp;mdash;participates with those who visit it; in the second, only the visitor is active, while the sight is frozen in space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt; exposes how thin this veneer of safety is.
Between Madeleine&amp;rsquo;s actions and Scottie&amp;rsquo;s vertigo, the film reintroduces the distinct possibilities of danger to these places.
In doing so, it unsettles the stable relationship between Scottie the subject and San Francisco the object.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I contend that a stable subject-object relationship is necessary to Scottie&amp;rsquo;s sense of place; as evidence, I look to his meeting with Gavin Elster.
#Elster meeting exposes Scottie&amp;rsquo;s desires
##Scottie kind of had this with the police force, but he has been neutered and immobilized (the placement)
##Also exposes what SF lacks
#He likes going to these &amp;ldquo;old places&amp;rdquo; b/c he feels powerful and free there, his very life in defiance of the tall trees, colonial forces, and rough seas
##these parks serve as reminders of the passage of time, but they are as much participants in it
##so, unbeknownst to Scottie, the parks lost their oldness. Therefore, the power he feels is invalid
#Madeleine exposes real danger
##This unsettles the relationship, because he now feels the danger
##this change makes it such that he can confuse now with the past
##this flattening of history disorients scottie&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a private reading of &lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt;.
To&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By disrupting the normal order of things, &lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt; thus undermines our () grip of America over San Francisco, and, in doing so, its narrative of progress.
This disruption contributes to a &amp;ldquo;weakening of historicity, both in our relationship to public History and in the new forms of our private temporality&amp;rdquo;.^[Frederic Jameson, &lt;a href=&#34;https://web.archive.org/web/20110806060217/http://homepage.newschool.edu/~quigleyt/vcs/jameson/jameson.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Cultural Logic of Late Capitalism&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Here &amp;lsquo;historcity&amp;rsquo; is that sense that things have changed somehow in our social relations.
By exposing progress as a veneer, Hitchock traps us in a spiral that mirrors Scottie Ferguson&amp;rsquo;s own difficulty escaping his traumatic past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;establishing-a-modern-city-via-the-american-sublime&#34;&gt;Establishing a modern city via the American sublime&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(the flâneur, Gavin Elster)? american tech sublime and the double action&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;disrupting-the-illusion-of-safety&#34;&gt;Disrupting the illusion of safety&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Definitely something here about the fragility of the sublime
Madeleine puncturing the visual membrane of the sublime&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sublime, rather than an instrument which rattles people from their parochial understandings of history to glean a new future, turns them toward a never-ending past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt; is often viewed as the modernist movie. Here instead it is an early example of postmodernism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of &lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rsquo;s lasting images star San Francisco as much as they do Jimmy Stewart or Kim Novak.
Consider for example the massive pylons supporting the Golden Gate Bridge, the looming trunks of Muir Woods, or the towering figure cut by the Mission San Juan Bautista.
These are objects so huge that Hitchcock&amp;rsquo;s camera cannot swallow them entirely, their vastness bleeding over the frame&amp;rsquo;s edges.
And each of them repeat vertical features&amp;mdash;the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_orange#Golden_Gate_Bridge&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;International Orange&lt;/a&gt; suspension cables, endless &lt;em&gt;Sequoia sempervirens&lt;/em&gt;, late-afternoon shadows cast by pale white arches&amp;mdash;that recede into the distance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Succession and uniformity of parts are what constitute the artificial infinite&amp;rdquo; wrote Edmund Burke in &lt;em&gt;A Philosophical Enquiry Into the Origin of Our Ideas of the Sublime and Beautiful&lt;/em&gt;, one of the first modern explorations of the sublime.
He described the sublime as a state when &amp;ldquo;the mind is so entirely filled with its object, that it cannot entertain any other,&amp;rdquo; inciting terror and astonishment at its heights, while &amp;ldquo;the inferior effects are admiration, reverence and respect.&amp;rdquo;
The treatment Hitchcock gives to San Francisco&amp;rsquo;s iconic sights meets Burke&amp;rsquo;s standard.
But what purpose does this treatment serve? How does the voyeurism of Hitchcock&amp;rsquo;s camera change the meaning of these vistas? &amp;lt;&amp;mdash;is this a question for the other post&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These images represent a particular kind of sublime associated with a particular kind of political project.
While great magnitude and manifold features are part of Burke&amp;rsquo;s sublime, he later disavows &amp;ldquo;colonnades and avenues of trees [&amp;hellip;] suffered to run to immense distances&amp;rdquo; as urbane.
However, the ultimate height of construction (and of trees) was not foreseen by Burke in 1757: the technical and natural discoveries in nineteenth-century and early-twentieth-century America would dwarf those of eighteenth-century Europe.
Moreover, metropolitans worldwide realized the need to incorporate great sights into their cityscapes.
Historian David Nye writes of an American technological sublime, a fusion of American technical mastery and pre-American resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I argue that this modification of Burke&amp;rsquo;s typology (which had separated the sublime into natural and architectural modes) can be used to better understand how the expansive imagery in &lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt; contributes to a &amp;ldquo;weakening of historicity, both in our relationship to public History and in the new forms of our private temporality&amp;rdquo;.^[Frederic Jameson, &lt;a href=&#34;https://web.archive.org/web/20110806060217/http://homepage.newschool.edu/~quigleyt/vcs/jameson/jameson.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Cultural Logic of Late Capitalism&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Keeping with &lt;a href=&#34;https://popculturebento.com/the-all-american-gaze-distorted-perspective-in-alfred-hitchcocks-vertigo/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;my earlier analysis of the film&lt;/a&gt;, I maintain that &lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt; presents both a private message concerning Scottie Ferguson&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:Portrayed-by-Jim&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:Portrayed-by-Jim&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and a public message about the social geography of 1950&amp;rsquo;s America.
In the interest of clarity, I focus today only on the public message, detailing how the American sublime clashes pre-modernity with modernity, disorienting Scottie&amp;rsquo;s experience of history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-drives-scottie&#34;&gt;What drives Scottie?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understanding the sublime images in &lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt; begins with understanding how Scottie encounters such pictures.
Since the film is shot (mostly) from his perspective, Hitchcock&amp;rsquo;s treatment of the Golden Gate, the Muir Woods, and the Mission all derive from Scottie.
While his desires have been the subject of several careers in film studies, it will help to simplify by looking at the film itself for direction.
Stewart&amp;rsquo;s body language clues us in to the gravity of his encounter with Gavin Elster, Madeleine&amp;rsquo;s husband.
As Nerdwriter &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UgnNakO6JZw&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;demonstrates&lt;/a&gt;, this meeting has so much to do with each man&amp;rsquo;s power.
This short exchange seems to encapsulate much of the two men&amp;rsquo;s urges:

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/udMms5FKyok?t=47&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

And in the script:
&amp;gt;ELSTER: San Francisco&amp;rsquo;s changed. The things that spell San Francisco to me are disappearing fast.
SCOTTIE: (Scottie smiles at the old prints [of a small, façaded San Francisco surrounded by dangerous and rocky terrain] on the wall.) Like all this.
ELSTER: (Nodding) I&amp;rsquo;d like to have lived here then. The color and excitement&amp;hellip; the power&amp;hellip;  the freedom.
(Though he does not stress the word, the way he lingers softly on the word &amp;ldquo;Freedom&amp;rdquo; makes Scottie look over at him again. Elster looks up and smiles companionably.)&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:Alec-Coppel-Samu&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:Alec-Coppel-Samu&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the mechanisms by which 1950s San Francisco distances itself from its Wild West past&amp;mdash;the long sequences in sleek automobiles, the infrequent references to psychiatry, a brassiere operating by &amp;ldquo;the principle of the cantilever bridge&amp;rdquo;&amp;mdash;are here disavowed in favor of a dangerous and unfamiliar past.
That bra symbolizes surprisingly much of the city&amp;rsquo;s changes.
Its &amp;ldquo;revolutionary uplift&amp;rdquo;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:Vertigo-script-P&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:Vertigo-script-P&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; are designed for the pleasure of men, as much of city&amp;rsquo;s attractions were.
Meanwhile, the comfort provided by the innovative architecture undoubtedly improved women&amp;rsquo;s lives, albeit in small ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By including men and women, the bra is thus a factor of the democratic virtues of the American technological sublime outlined by David Nye.
But it is also a product of that historical concept, designed by an engineer in his spare time, a &amp;ldquo;kind of do-it-yourself thing,&amp;rdquo; as Scottie notes.
This spirit of tinkering that came from outside the state apparatus and wealthy class is the reason why &amp;ldquo;Engineers, builders, and inventors began to occupy [&amp;hellip;] the pantheon of republicanism.&amp;ldquo;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:David-Nye-The-Am&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:David-Nye-The-Am&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
The bra (by its inventor, its target audience, its cantilever design) symbolizes how invention, innovation, and ambitious construction catered to America&amp;rsquo;s middle class.
These criteria of the American sublime would have been alien to a pre-modern San Francisco.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the above is but the first move in Nye&amp;rsquo;s distinctive double action of the American sublime.
Where that first move &amp;ldquo;usurped the place of natural things with man-made objects” conceived as &amp;ldquo;internal improvements”, the second move covered the tracks of the first, assimilating the object of improvement as once again natural.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:Jimmy-Stewart&#34;&gt;Jimmy Stewart &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:Jimmy-Stewart&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:Portrayed-by-Jim&#34;&gt;Portrayed by Jimmy Stewart. &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:Portrayed-by-Jim&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:Alec-Coppel-Samu&#34;&gt;Alec Coppel &amp;amp; Samuel Taylor, &lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt; [script](&lt;a href=&#34;https://the.hitchcock.zone/wiki/Scripts:_Vertigo_(12/Sep/1957&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://the.hitchcock.zone/wiki/Scripts:_Vertigo_(12/Sep/1957&lt;/a&gt;) Part 2, dated 12 September 1957. &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:Alec-Coppel-Samu&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:Vertigo-script-P&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vertigo&lt;/em&gt; script, Part 1. &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:Vertigo-script-P&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:David-Nye-The-Am&#34;&gt;David Nye, &amp;ldquo;The American Sublime&amp;rdquo; in &lt;em&gt;American Technological Sublime&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:David-Nye-The-Am&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;^&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Putting Theory in its Place</title>
      <link>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2020/01/20/putting-theory-in-its-place/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://runkelcorey.github.io/2020/01/20/putting-theory-in-its-place/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When statistics disagree with words, theory can be an effective arbitrator. These disciplinary stories impose an otherwordly coherence on an incoherent world. With so much information at hand, I became addicted to theory for this very quality. The few bad habits I struggle to kick have (thankfully) instilled a probably irrational fear of new bad habits. Unfortunately, in kicking these habits and warding off others, I turned to theory to make my decisions. In doing so, I appealed to ever more abstract and cloudy narratives to buttress those closer to the ground (for theory can only be invalidated by other theories). And so, my first two years of undergrad were marked by a myopic embrace that left me pretentious and ill-suited to conditions on the ground floor of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Letting go of theory as the source of knowledge has been such a difficult process for me because of issues I have trusting others&amp;mdash;I compulsively check my girlfriend in areas where she by so many miles has the upper hand of practical and, yes, theoretical experience. By listening to an argument, I myself pass judgment on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://writing.upenn.edu/~taransky/Barthes.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;death of its author&lt;/a&gt;. While I enjoy this ultimate power, it cannot explain why I return to theory when all else fails&amp;mdash;indeed, it is a famed theorist&amp;rsquo;s failure that prompts one of my swift judgments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, it&amp;rsquo;s on the continued survival of authors after meeting my scrutiny that I base my returns. The reasons for these positive judgments are no doubt varied and incoherent to some, but I am sure that many follow a similar pattern. First, a writer will introduce familiar concept in unfamiliar language. Then, this language&amp;mdash;combined with elongated sentences&amp;mdash;renders said once-familiar concept gobbledygook. At this point, my capacity for calling BS on difficult works is hindered by my choice to read almost exclusively ~the classics~. This choice, and the knowledge of this choice, activates a psychological muscle in me that translates prestige as authority. When aggregated, this muscle operates as a sociological pressure. Seen below, the Tennis Court Oath makes abundantly clear in whom authority rests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/6/6d/Le_Serment_du_Jeu_de_paume.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Jacques-Louis David&#39;s *Tennis Court Oath* uses attention to show where power lies. &#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This all vindicates Nietzsche&amp;rsquo;s quote &amp;ldquo;I am not understood. Hence my authority.&amp;rdquo; This logic does not bode well for readers, however. Blinded by high-wattage prestige, one loses with the ability to criticize the ability to think. The authority that difficult, highly-regarded theory held over me also held me in its sway: I assumed that there was something essential to living life to be plumbed in theory, rather than a story told using the dictionary of a particular discipline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last year, I have maintained a weaning off of theory by, ironically, reading more theory. Richard Rorty refreshed pragmatism for a theory-weary America&amp;mdash;not by assuring us that what works in practice works regardless of the theory, but by stabbing epistemology in the back with what can best be termed an analytic deconstruction. Understanding his work proved to be a crucial step in unlearning much of what school had taught me, but elsewhere in my life, I clung to theory, thinking that the less-rigorous exercise, wellness, and movie literature could still be optimized by a turn towards theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I found were concrete ways in which that thought&amp;mdash;that life could be optimized by theory&amp;mdash;disappointed me. This disappointment brought the set of things I Know to Be True up with the set of things I &lt;em&gt;Think&lt;/em&gt; I Know to Be True. In other words, what I had read was made real before my eyes, elevating that knowledge to second-nature status. The vehicle for this realization was cooking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had begun really trying to cook two years ago, when I spurned the atrocities of my university&amp;rsquo;s dining hall. I asked for an Instant Pot that Christmas, and found hundreds of recipes to choose from. What the recipes called for, I did diligently. My girlfriend rarely challenged these steps, for the Instant Pot admits no air to its chamber, let alone the senses that allow facilitate good cooking. Recently, however, I&amp;rsquo;ve moved away from the Instant Pot in pursuit of perfectly-tuned seasoning and picturesque browning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In doing so, the superior wisdom of the cooks around me&amp;mdash;my girlfriend most loudly&amp;mdash;has battered the recipes I originally held so high. Trusting my own senses, and thinking critically about each step, have been given a newfound priority. The genius of cooking is that the tongue is already a great judge of cooking! In this light, it is immediately clear that famous names and convoluted explanations offer nowhere near the precision and attention that the mouth serves up instantaneously. &amp;ldquo;To write is to reach&amp;rdquo; said Barthes, and to cook might as well be added to that list. Each attempt is a venture into unknown territory, where local knowledge trumps the views from nowhere offered by orphaned recipes on cooking websites. Samin Nosrat&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/985508716&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Salt, Fat, Acid, Heat&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; grounds this truth with a million stories of direction-following as well as rule-breaking. The book explicitly claims to induct the laws of good cooking, but, implicitly, it works because of her history in kitchens around the world. She resists listicle format, step-by-step instructions in favor of narrative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This decision allows for reflection and judgment, and she constantly refers back to cooks&amp;rsquo; own palettes, finger tips, and eardrums. This reference (and deference) does the real work of teaching, imploring readers to become writers and eaters to become cooks. Trying to assimilate her principles with her recipes has already improved my cooking, and the fearlessness with which I annotate her beautifully-illustrated hardback has been a quietly-empowering experience. Cooking has shown me what my great professor Marlon Ross once told me, that great work speaks up to theory instead of letting theory talk down to it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
